Hey welcome back.
So we're moving on to the third of our elementary sorting algorithms.
The last one for this section.
Before we move on to some of the scarier ones some of the fancier ones let's call it fancy instead of
scary.
So insertion sort.
Actually it's pretty similar to the bubble sort.
And two selections sort I mean grips them all together.
However there are a couple of key distinction some some things that insertion sort is actually good
at.
So this isn't one that's just good to know about.
It's not just a good challenge.
There are situations where insertion sort does well and I'll explain that as we go.
But first let's talk about how it works.
So it builds up the sort by gradually creating a larger half of the array which is always sorted.
So instead of going one instead of finding the largest element at a time or finding the smallest element
at a time it takes each element and places it where it should go in the sorted half.
So let's take a look.
That doesn't really mean much but if this is our initial state we start with this are sorted half the
array is a shown in green.
So right now a half is not the right turn by the way the shorted sorted portion of the array.
And our value we're looking at is three.
So where would we put 3 in order to sort this part.
Well we'd put it before five right.
We insert it into the right place.
Now we hit four.
Where does go.
We insert it between the two.
So now this is our sorted portion.
Then we hit one where should we put that at the beginning and we hit two.
Where do we insert that right there.
Index of 1.
So you can see what happens is that we gradually build up the sorted portion of the array by inserting
one item at a time in the correct place.
So here's a quick walkthrough of it.
If we start with this small array we have three and we take 44 and we figure out where it should go
in our sorted portion.
Well actually it just goes right back where it was because it's greater than three that's where it belongs.
But now we get to 38.
Where should we put 38 in this left portion.
We put it between the two like that then five.
Where should that go.
Well doesn't go there does it.
Nope.
So we have to check the next one to see it go there.
Yes.
In between the two 47 compared to 44 up you just go right where you are 15 compared to 47.
Nope compared to 44.
No compared to 38.
No compared to five.
Yes.
And now we have the sorted array.
So hopefully you can see why is called insertion sort.
We are taking an element one at a time and inserting it in the correct spot.
But as far as the pseudo code what you do you start by picking the second element in the array because
our sorted portion will be considered the first element at the very beginning.
So we don't need to sort the first element.
So we take the second one and we compare it to the one before it and if necessary we swap them.
Then we continue to the next element and check if it's in the correct spot.
So we iterate through the sorted portion the left.
At this point if we've sorted two of them the left two and we figure out where to put the third one.
And we repeat until the array is sorted and then return that array.