All right.
So let's implement insertion sort.
So I have my snippet ready and I'm going to define our function called insertion sort takes an array.
This should be pretty familiar right now.
Return that array and let's call it down here with what should we call it with.
Let's go with 2 4.
Oh wait.
I'm doing a sort of array.
That's not going to work.
Two comma one nine and seventy six and four.
OK.
Hardest part of my day out of the way now picking those numbers.
And actually that's not true.
All of this is hard to explain.
OK.
So we've got this here.
And the first thing we want to do is if we just visualize what we're what we're doing as we go through
rather than starting with the first element because that can be kind of an edge case.
Let's say we've gone through a couple of passes and our RE is sorted.
Up until this point.
So what do we need to do with for for example.
Well what we do we take four and we basically work backwards.
We compare it to 76 and we check which one is larger if Four is larger than it stays right where it
is and we're done.
But if four is less than 76 then what what do we do.
Well what we can do is move 76 up to where 4 is and then we we look down to the next one 9 where does
forfeit.
Well nine is still larger so we move nine.
Up until where 76 used to be.
And then we checked to all fours larger.
So we put four right here.
If that makes sense we end up with this.
So the reason I'm I'm starting from here is because the first easy part is we want to iterate over every
item.
Right.
That's that's obvious.
All these sorting algorithms so far have involved that we start with a loop.
We start roughly at the beginning although in this case we can actually start looping at the first item
first index rather than zero and then we look backwards and we figure out where to start or where to
what to do.
So let's write our loop for our equals 1 rather than zero.
It's not a problem if we do zero.
It's just an extra iteration and will do well.
It's less than the length.
Nope I read at length I mean add 1 to i.
Ok so now what we need to do is first let's make a variable to keep track of the value that we're looking
at.
So let's say that we're looking at four.
We're going to make a variable called I don't know what you going to call it let's go with the far current
value equals array.
I like that.
Now we just want to work backwards.
So this is why it's easier.
Like I said to think that we're towards the end or the middle of the array rather than at the at the
very beginning because there is no backward surely to to work towards.
So let's make another loop to go backwards.
So for var J equals in which we started at.
Well we want to start it at one less than whatever Ayas So if this is if we go back to this example
this is what we're looking at.
If I was right here so that's 0 1 2 3 4 if I asked for we want to start comparing.
I or this number to this number which is going to be index of minus 1.
So J equals I minus 1 to start.
And we're going to make a comparison which we haven't done yet and keep going until eventually we find
the right spot.
So worst case how many times.
For example if this was zero.
How many times do we need to go down.
We need j to be 3 0 1 2 3 and it's be to need to be 1 when needed to be zero.
And then that's where we would put 0.
Index zero.
So for that to work we want to keep going while J is greater than zero is what are greater than negative
1 is one way of doing it greater than or equal to zero.
I always would do I prefer.
I don't know I was going to say I have a preference but I don't really do J.
Greater than yes that's greater than or equal to zero.
So it's OK if we had zero because an Index index goes to zero.
Or you could do greater than negative one whichever one.
All right.
So then we're going to subtract one from J.
Every time.
So this is just our ruffs loop skeleton if you will.
So we pick.
If I is four then we have this loop J that goes from 3 down to 2 to 1 down to zero and then it stops.
So that's just the basic loop.
But we don't really want it to just keep looping for no reason.
We need to start figuring out where this value goes or if we're looking at this example where does zero
fit in.
So what we do we already have ZERO.
In our case stored under the variable current Val.
So whatever it is we're storing ramify in Kernville.
So we have it over on the side.
Just keep it over here the value zero and my console's not very happy about that.
So what happens now is that J is going to start at 76 and move backwards Will J itself isn't J-Stars
at 3 and moves down to zero.
What we want to do now is compare current value to array of J.
So we could write that out basically like this array of J.
If I can type array of J.
And then we want to compare that to current row.
What we want to check is array of J.
Larger than the current value.
So if that's the case if 76 is larger than 0.
We want to move zero down.
Which what that really means is we're going to move 76 up.
So if I show you which are the actual operations.
OK.
So first time through zeroes here we compare current value to 76 76 is larger.
So we actually move 76.
We copy it over to here.
Remember we have zero already saved in a variable so we don't have to do like a swap with a temporary
variable we already have that temporary variable called current value.
So then we move back again to night and we compare 9 and 0 9 is greater than zero still.
So we're going to take nine and put it there.
Now we move down to two.
Two is greater than zero.
So we're going to move it to J plus 1 then we get to 1 which is still greater than zero.
So we move it up to here and then at the very end if our loop is done we're going to take whatever this
value is and stick it right there.
So there's a better way of writing this.
And I'll show you what it looks like it's a little bit confusing to see a for loop like this but this
is one way of doing it.
So our loop goes while J is greater than or equal to zero.
And array of J is greater than current value current value.
So you may not have seen many for the trip like this but this is one potential way of doing it instead
of us.
Second you could do a while loop as well or in any sort of conditional check to break out of for loop.
But what this reads as so Jay starts is I minus 1.
We're going to keep going while J is greater than or equal to zero.
And array of J is greater than the current value.
So if and if at any point for example if instead of 0 this last item was 20.
We're going to go through once array of J is going to give us 76 that is greater so we keep looping
and we want to move 76 to here.
But then we compare 20 to nine and all of a sudden this isn't true anymore.
So we're done looping.
Now we just put 20 right here.
So I was kind of kind of confusing when we when we write it this way but let me just fill in the rest
so if any time we're going through this loop what we're going to be doing is taking a value like this
and moving it forward and moving it forward.
And then we stop at some point.
So to actually move that value forward it's just array of J plus one equals array of J.
So why don't I just do a that log to show what's happening on the log array and actually let's do it
in here.
So we're not sorting just yet because we're not actually replacing the correct value in.
But if I run this OK you can see what's happening.
So we started with one and we look back at two.
Well one needs to go here so we moved two forward.
So we get two to 9 7 76 for we just never added in one.
So to remedy this after this loop finishes that means that we found the correct spot for where we need
to insert current Vau.
So then here all we do is insert current value and it's not array of J.
It's array of J plus 1 because if we walk through this again let's say that we're starting here.
Then J is going to start right here.
So we check which one is larger.
OK 76 is larger.
So remember we have 20 saves in a variable.
We're going to take 76 and move it here.
But J was right here.
So next time through J moves down to here and we compare 20 and nine.
Well 20 is greater than nine.
So we're not going to move 9 forward but we don't want to swopped we don't want to put 20 right here.
We want to put 20 here in this space.
So J is this we want J plus 1.
So array of J plus one equals equal what we call it current value.
And now actually we're done.
So if we step through now what happens let me clear execute.
OK.
I'm printing when we move an item forward which is kind of confusing so we moved too forward.
But then on this line right here we inserted one at the beginning and said do cancel the log right here.
OK.
So where's the start.
Here we go.
So you can see we go through the first time and we put one where it goes goes in front of the two then
we're looking at nine Well it goes where it is then we look at 76 that goes where it is.
But then we get to four.
We need to move for all the way to right here and then we're sorted.
So this one is a bit different.
I know it's a maybe a little harder to understand this code but step through it.
If you if you do get stuck I highly encourage you to just write down what I and J are at every point.
Just one at a time.
Walk through.
It might take a little bit.
Use a shorter array.
Definitely when you're choosing numbers for the array it helps to choose things that make sense that
like work with your algorithm.
If you just pick a bunch of numbers like two two and two where you pick something that's already sorted
it doesn't help that much.
So pay attention to that.
But walk through it if you need some help try to understand what's going on.