So insertion sort.
As far as its time complexity it's pretty similar overall to the other two we've seen its worst case
of and squared is quadratic because were it for the length that the array grows.
We also have to basically make n squared number of comparisons.
But if our data is almost all sorted.
So if instead we were looking at something like I don't know what would work here let's say 1 2 3 4
negative 1 for example.
Well if we start we look at two we immediately find that it's greater.
We don't have to do anything we stop the loop.
Then we move to three.
We find that it's greater than 2.
We don't need to keep going.
We look at four Where could we look at negative one.
All right.
Now we have to go through and put it at the beginning.
But compare that to a totally random unsorted data where we have to continually play something and iterate.
Then we're looking at a much worse time or actually what's the worst possible scenario something like
this where you start.
We get to three.
We have to swap it to here and we get to two.
We have to swap it to the beginning and we get to 1 and we have to swap to the beginning again.
That's the worst case for insertion sort.
But if your data is nearly sorted you're get.
Now another interesting thing that insertion sort is good at.
If you're data there's something called an online algorithm which is an algorithm that can work as data
is coming in as it receives new data.
It doesn't have to have the entire array at once.
So for example let's say that we have some code where people are submitting numbers to us online live.
We're getting them and we want to sort them in.
Don't ask why.
Let's say we wanted to.
With insertion sort because the way that it works that we're keeping one side of the array sorted and
we're inserting items one at a time it doesn't matter what the number is that comes in.
We can place it where it needs to go.
So this that's one strength if you do need if you're looking for a sorting algorithm that works in that
way which probably isn't going to come up but it is worth knowing that because of how insertion sort
works for because we keep one side of it sorted and we insert things in the appropriate place because
of that it works well in a situation where data is coming in live or streaming.
And you need to insert it at a moment's notice.
OK.
So those are the three elementary sorting out rhythms in the next video.
We'll just wrap up talking about their time complexity and space complexity.
And then also do a quick recap of what we learned.