Everyone in this video to talk about the order of the content is arranged in.
So we've established that there is a lot of stuff here and it's pretty varied.
You don't have to go through every single video one after the other like you might with the intro to
C S S course or intro to J.
Yes some of you might be here only for the sorting algorithm stuff or only the data structures and that's
totally fine.
You do not need to go through everything in order.
But however you do it please take your time.
This content can be a little dense.
There's a lot of it here.
Remember that this is the condensed version of what I teach over two and a half three weeks of in-person
courses in a boot camp where it's five days a week eight to 10 hours a day.
It's very intense content and this is three weeks of that.
So even though it might it's only 20 something hours remember that that's just the amount of lecture.
There's a lot of time to digest that and understand it do the quizzes build stuff etc..
So onto the important piece which is please notice the prerequisite lectures in every section.
After the first section and the next section every other section contains at the very beginning a lecture
may just show you here called prerequisites in all caps and all that it contains is information about
which other sections you need to complete.
First before you can tackle this one.
So if you do want to jump to sorting algorithms for example I'd say you want to go to a bubble sort.
Well all that you really need to know.
According to this is Big O notation.
Section 1 if you want to jump to a more complex sorting algorithm like merge sort.
You definitely need to know Big-O notation and Section 6 which covers recursion because merge sort the
way we implement it is with a recursive implementation.
And then there are some secondary considerations.
These are the sections I recommend you check out but you don't have to.
So the first to hear Section 1 in section 6.
You definitely need to understand these are just helpful and you can see as we go later in the course
like we look at binary search trees.
Same thing.
The prerequisites that you definitely need to understand and then things that could be helpful while
not could be things that will be helpful but they're not mandatory.
So please pay attention to that.
Every section has prerequisites.
A text lecture at the beginning.
It's there for a reason.
If you do hop around if you don't want to go through every single section in order make sure you're
paying attention to that so that you don't get confused when I talk about binary heaps and priority
queues in the dextrous shortest path section which if we go to that section you can see here we are.
You can see you need to have binary heaps and priority queues.
Anyway I'll leave it at that.
Just please notice those prerequisites lectures are very helpful.
If you do want to hop around Otherwise you can just go to the content in order.
Get.