Hey welcome back.
So the first of the fancier sorting algorithms that we're going to take a look at is called merge sort.
It's very well known one that was created back in 1948.
A computer scientist slash math mathematician and all around smart guy named Jonathan Van Norman or
Von Neumann wrote the first ever recorded program of merge sort.
It was 23 pages of code for this computer here called Ed VAK.
It's a very large computer.
It was like six six thousand or so vacuum tubes writing code back then obviously very different than
it was today.
But the algorithm the idea was first conceived in 1948.
So the idea behind it it's really a combination of two things merging and sorting.
And actually you can say it's really a combination of three things splitting up sorting and merging
all three things take place.
So it exploits the fact that arrays of zero or one element one element are already sorted.
So if you're asked to sort an array that just consists of the number one and that's it you know it's
sorted or it's just number nine it's sorted or it's empty it's sorted.
So merge so it takes advantage of that fact it works by decomposing an array into smaller arrays.
So that's something known as a divide and conquer algorithm a divide and conquer approach.
We split up the larger array we're trying to sort into smaller sub arrays all the way down.
We keep doing it until we get to zero or one element arrays.
So we would take an eight element array and split it and then split it and then split it until we end
up with eight single element arrays and then we merge them back together.
So here's a little visualization.
Imagine we have this array here 8 3 5 4 7 6 1 2 that is 8 elements.
What do we do we start.
Or the code starts by splitting it in half.
So we're dividing it and we're still not at one or zero element arrays right.
These are four elements.
So we split again.
And now we have four two element arrays.
We're still not there.
So we flip again.
Now what we have are eight single out arrays single element arrays.
So now we merge them together.
So let's focus here.
We take these two arrays and we merge them back.
And as we merge them they are already sorted.
We know that they're sorted.
So sorting merging two sorted arrays is easy relative to merging two unsorted arrays.
So what we do we basically just compare the number which one is smaller while the smaller one goes first.
Which one of these is smaller smaller one goes first which one of these is smaller.
Put that first one goes before you then repeat the process.
Now remerging this array with this array.
But notice this is already sorted.
This is already sorted.
So now we just make a couple of comparisons.
Take the first item compared to the first item.
Which one is smaller.
Put that one first.
Then we take this item compared to that item which was smaller.
OK put four and then we do it again put 5 and then 8 and then the same thing over here.
So we end up with 1 2 6 7 and 3 4 5 8 2 sorted arrays that are smaller.
Now our final merge we put them all together and we end up with this one two three four five six seven
eight.
So hopefully you can see yes this algorithm is a little more complicated but it involves first splitting
up splitting up until we end up with sorted arrays which are zero or one element.
That's that's the base case that's the smallest thing we get to we know they're sorted if they're only
one item wrong or they're empty then what do we do.
We merge them merging sorted arrays is easy.
Well compared to merging unsorted or it's still not that easy and we sort them back until we finish
and we get a totally sorted array.
Here's another visualization.
Here we have eight elements in an array.
And the very first thing that happens is we split them all up into eight individual arrays.
Now they all have each color represents the fact that they're an individual array and then as we merge
them together they change color.
So it starts with the first two.
These are two arrays.
How do we sort them into one three and 44 takes them out and put them back in in that order they're
sorted.
So now we have this is one array here.
So we have seven arrays right away.
One two three four five.
Yes.
Seven can't count.
So next we take these two individual arrays and we sort them into one and put them back.
Now we take these to erase the orange and the red of those two items each and we sort them into one
array like this.
And then we put that back then we have to start on the right side.
So this was the left division.
Now we take 47 and 15 we sort them from two arrays of one item into one array of two items.
Same thing with 36 and 26.
Now what do we do.
We merge these two arrays together.
The yellow and the green.
There we go.
Put that back in.
And now we merge our two arrays of four items at the very end.
There we go.
So that's merge sort.
And as you can imagine there's a little bit of logic involved in the next video.
We're going to implement the first step which is merging.
So we have to understand how to merge two sorted arrays and then the rest is actually pretty easy.
So in the next video we're going to cover that.
We're going to build emerging function.