Hey again welcome back.
So this is the first part of writing merge sort which is writing a function to merge two sorted arrays.
So again we have we assume the arrays are sorted and all you have to do is return the combination of
those two sorted arrays.
So for example I already have it written here.
Well I'm not showing you the code but I have the function call here two sorted arrays one 10:52 that
sorted two 14:19 in one hundred.
That's sorted when I run this I merge them together.
We get one to 10 14:15 ninety nine one hundred.
So one array that is returned.
So that's basically your job if you want to try and do this on your own.
I'll have a solution in the next video.
This part as well.
Personally I always hate saying if something's hard or easy but I think the logic for this one makes
sense.
We'll walk through it though I have pseudo code so I jumped the gun on my slides.
Yes.
It's useful to first implement a function responsible for merging two sorted a race given to sort of
arrays the helper function could create a new one which is also sorted.
And yeah it's important need to consist of all the elements in the two input arrays.
So what do we do if they're not the same size.
We'll cover that.
And as far as how it should work this is something we haven't seen but it should run an O of and plus
M time and and plus M space.
So N and M We have two inputs now to our function one array and then the second array.
So N is the size of the first one.
Amice the size of the second one.
Of course those are two that sound very similar and you probably can't tell what I'm saying and am but
that's the standard way of saying it.
Of writing it down so that just means that if n grows super large but M doesn't grow very large it should
just be 0 of and plus M often and usually and merge sort.
They are the exact same size or one element different in real life.
But if we are working with something and for some reason we're merging an array of a thousand items
with an array of a million items it should be and plus.
So as that one grows anyway.
All I'm saying is that you should visit each item in the array one time.
Right if it was just 0 of N that means that you're going to it's linear time you visit each item once
you iterate over it.
But if it's 0 of any place and that means that we're iterating over each item and each array once.
So here's the pseudo code.
Create an empty array.
So defined a function takes two inputs.
Create an empty array that you'll return at the end and then you start with the smallest values in each
input array started the beginning.
So have two counters one called I one called J.
I recommend using while loops for this.
Personally that's what I'd like to do and you need to have one that starts out they both need to start
at zero.
J and I are two numbers started to Europe while there are still values we haven't looked at.
Meaning while I and J both haven't hit the end of their respective arrays we're going to take the value
of the first array of the first item and then compare that to the value of the first item in the second
array.
Now if the first item is smaller we put that in our result array and then we move on to the next item
in the first row.
If it's the other way around.
If the first array is larger the item in the first array than the value in our second array.
We take the value from the second array and put that in the results and move on to the next value in
the second array.
And then once we finish one array we just push all the remaining values from the other array in.
So for example if we took these two we just write them down here.
These are two arrays and then this is my result that I'm going to return.
We start with two counters.
I and J.
And they start at zero and zero.
So we compare one and two.
Which one is small.
One is.
So we put one here and then we move on.
In this first array we're now looking at 10.
So if I were to put a little marker here like that it's not a very great way of writing that and our
marker over here.
This is going to bite me this is going to be annoying to keep track of is too.
So next time through we're comparing ten into which one is smaller too.
So we put two in here.
Which means that now we need to shift this over and now we're looking at 10 and 14.
So now which one is smaller.
Ten is.
So we put 10 in and then we move this up.
Not this one.
Now we're looking at 14 and 50 which one is smaller 14.
All right.
So then we move this to 99.
And get.
OK 50 in 99 which wins 50 wins.
So then we've now exhausted that array.
And what that tells us if we've hit the end of this all we do is take all remaining values in this other
one because if this is sorted and they have to be sorted in the same way I should have mentioned that
we can't have one in ascending and descending.
They're sort of in the same rate same way whatever is at the end of this array if we have stuff that's
left in the other array we know for sure it's all greater than whatever that 50 in this case.
So now we just add in 99 and then 100 and now we have successfully merge the two arrays.
So that's the approach that I'd like for you to try and take.
Otherwise if you don't want to do it in the next video I'll just show you a solution.
So this is a first important step for merger.