All right.
Come back.
Now let's write the code to make this work.
To merge two sorted arrays.
So if you jumped to this video because you saw implementation in the title I recommend you just go back
and take a look at the rough pseudo code how it's supposed to work.
Just so you understand what we're doing here.
So here I'll start by defining a snippet.
As always I'll call it merge my function and it takes into arrays.
Let's just do a r r one and r r to.
And then here the very first thing we should make is just make a variable called result's
empty array and then at the very end we return results like that.
And then we need to do all of our logic.
So the first thing we'll do is make our two little pointers are going to start with a variable zero
and another one at zero.
Each for each one for a huge array and then they'll move through individually so we'll do let i equal
zero but J equals zero or whatever you could call it a r r 1 index or something.
I'm just going to go with I.
OK.
Now the ball CoreLogic when you have a while loop that that runs while I is less than the length of
the array and J is less than the length basically meaning while there is still data for us to look at
in both if we hit the end of one of them.
Remember in the last video that I showed when we started here than we hit the end of 50 and there were
still data here.
We're going to do something else to this first loop only applies when we're looping through both at
the same time.
So while I is less than 1 length and J is less than $2 like perfect now we just do a simple comparison
of two of J and array one of I.
So it's up to us which one we got to do first.
I'm going to say if a two of J is greater than array I gave one of.
It's so confusing to try to talk about if this is our results we're basically checking if this one is
greater than this one.
What do we do.
We take this and we put it in results.
So if that's the case we're going to say results don't push array.
Oh and I said that backwards.
I'm sorry if this one is greater than this.
Then we take the smaller one and we put it in there.
I don't why we're not trying to do descending order.
We want the smallest items first.
All right.
So we're going to push array one of I if if it is smaller if array one is the smallest thing.
And if that's the case if we actually push array 1 in we then need to move I it's no longer going to
be zero.
We need to move up by 1 and that's super easy for us.
OK.
Now we have an else which is a lot of a lot of times.
I guess we haven't covered the edge case.
If that is the same value.
So instead of doing an else if array 2 is less than 1 because if we just add greater than and less than
we we'd be missing the case of equality.
But we can just pick one we can do greater than or equal two with an else or do greater then and then
have an else which will move which will catch the case when they're equal and when array one is greater.
OK so if that's if that's the case.
Otherwise we do results up push a re two of J.
And then we increment J by 1 because now we're moving up.
So that would be the Do we have that snow in the first time through.
We put one in here and then we're looking at ten in two.
Yes.
Now two is smaller.
So in that case we add two in which is from array of J.
But then we increment J by 1 and we go here.
Array of two I mean.
All right.
So if we look at what actually happens at the end of this loop let's print this out.
Well we're going to return results.
We don't actually need to print it.
It's not complete but it's getting there.
So we end up with one to 10 14 and 50 because what happened is we did this and this we did 10 14 did
50 and then we hit the end because we did 50 and then we added 1 to i.
And we hit the end of the array so this loop broke out.
We finished.
So what needs to happen afterwards once we exhaust one of them because remember our condition while
I is less than a re 1.0 length NJ is less than a shootout length.
Once we hit the end we then just take everything that's left in J an added in or if J.
If this was shorter like here if we hit the end we then take whatever's left in the first array and
added.
So that's easy as well.
I'm just going to do two well loops and I'll just have a while while I is less than one length.
What are we going to do.
Results up push array one of I and then just add 1 to i.
So basically the same logic in here.
It's just that we're not doing a conditional check anymore and I'm going to just duplicate this but
then replace I with J an array one with a right to that make sense.
So whatever happens at the end we merge them as far as we can until we hit the end of one of the arrays.
So let's say we hit the end of array one that means set rates who still has stuff in it.
So Jay hasn't hit the end so Jay will be less than a two dollar length.
In our case if we at the end of year 1 2 3 we get one to 10 14 50.
That means that Jay is currently an index of what is at 0 1 2.
So we have to add this in and we have to add this in.
And then Jay will have hit the end.
Jay will be equal to a rate of length at that point and then we finish and we return results.
Let's see if it works it looks good if we tried something sneakier like an empty array and then the
array one column with three still works because this loop never runs right.
All that happens is that we have a array of two.
So Jay is less than or safe to say we just push in all the results or all of the items in the array
of 2 into results and then return that if we tried doing something like 100 and then over here I don't
know I don't really even have anything worth showing at this point that won't work needs to be sorted.
All I want to show is that it works and it does OK.
So this is the first part of merge sort.
This is the longest part.
Actually if you came up with something better definitely share it in the comments post on the discussion
board but this is a pretty simple way of doing it.
And I think its pretty legible pretty easy to understand and walk through.
So we're going to use this code in the next video where we add on and actually implement merge sort.
Right now this only works with two sorted arrays.
OK.
See then.