All right.
So let's take a look at a more concrete example let's compare two solutions to the same problem.
All right so here's our problem.
Suppose you want to write a function that calculates the sum of all numbers from one up to and including
some number and so if we plug 3 in we should get one plus two plus three which has six the most common
are the easiest to come up with solution.
This is the one that comes to my mind first is to basically create a total variable accumulator and
loop through all those numbers and add them in one at a time starting at 1.
All the way up until now.
So that's what I've done here.
You have a for loop total variable starts at zero and at the end we return total.
We start the loop at 1 we go up until N each time through total plus equals I actually have.
There we go.
I have it open as a snippet here.
If you're not familiar with snippets basically it's a way for me to just rather than copy and paste
code into the console and have to deal with losing it and rerunning it.
And that pain in Chrome you can go to the sources tab and then there's a snippets tab you can click
on and it allows you to create new snippets of a couple of them here and I'm going to use them in this
course quite frequently as an easy way to save code and execute it.
And just to show you how it works here's this same add up to function.
And I am printing it out at the bottom the result of adding up to 6.
So that should be six plus five plus four plus three plus two plus one to execute it.
I can either click over here or you can see the shortcut it suggests to me on a Mac is command enter.
It will say the correct shortcut on a PC.
I think it's control center.
So if I do that now I get 21.
I did it with three hour ago.
I get six.
If I did it with 100 hundred I get 50 50.
OK.
So that's just to demonstrate that that works.
Next there's a second solution.
There's more than these two but these are two that I'm going to use because they illustrate my point.
This one is definitely less intuitive.
As you can see it's a lot shorter it's a single line which doesn't necessarily make it better but it's
very different.
There's no loop involved.
What we're doing is it's more of a mathematical formula.
We take N and we multiply it by n plus 1 divided by 2.
And where this is derived from I'm not going to go into.
I do have slides on it or a slide that talks about how we arrive with this formula if you want to check
it out you can but it is not.
It's not the focus of this video so I don't want to distract from the actual focus which is evaluating
and comparing these pieces of code not actually diving into how we write them.
So just to show you this one it does work.
I have another snippet over here.
I can run the same thing.
Let's do it with six again and I'll do.
Command enter to execute and I get 21.
And just to walk through what happens there.
So the equivalent of taking six plus one first which is going to give us seven and then we multiply
that by six which gives us 42 and then we divide by 2 which gives us 21.
So it does work gives us the same answer in the end.
Again how it works.
We'll leave that be.
All right.
So we established there are two working solutions.
Which one is better.
And of course the first thing that we could ask is What does better actually mean.
Does it mean the faster code in seconds or milliseconds does it mean the code that's fastest when we're
adding a small number versus a large number.
Let's say we want to benchmark it out when we add up all the numbers trans euro and 1 billion.
Is that a good test or is it about how much memory is used.
Is it you know the number of variables that are created that the data that is stored each time that
that function is called.
Or what about something like readability legibility.
How important is that.
Is that better or brevity that's not on here but a lot of people care about that.
They like to minimize the length the number of characters used in their programming.
Not my style personally but definitely valid.
All of these are valid concerns and it really comes down to the situation.
But I think most people would agree that the first two especially for now we're going to focus on speed
will come back to memory usage a bit but these too often can be more important than something like readability.
And unfortunately they often come at the expense of readability and that's sort of the balancing act
of of writing good code is writing efficient code that doesn't use up you know a ton of memory but also
is still readable and doesn't look like complete jibberish.
So we're going to talk about basically all of these play together throughout the entire course.
It will be a recurring theme but we're going to focus on evaluating speed how long code takes to execute
a target to start.
So how do we do that.
Well the simplest way would be to use something like a built in timing functions something like this
where we have our first add up to and then I use a function called method called performance now which
in the browser is just going to tell me the number of milliseconds since the document was created.
Basically since they open the window and then so I'm going to save that to a variable.
Before I call add up to then I'm going to call add up to with what did I do.
It's a billion.
I think it's a billion.
So I'm going to call with a large number.
And then after that finishes I'm going to check performance out.
Now again which should have incremented a bunch of milliseconds most likely.
So I have two numbers.
Then I just subtract them first or the second time minus the first time and I divide it by 1000 because
it's in milliseconds.
And I want to work in seconds.
We don't have to do that last part.
And I printed out.
So this should work.
And I actually have a snippet right here.
Same thing.
So add up to our same one from before.
And we're calling it with 1 billion and we're going to print out how long elapsed.
Let me clear my console first and I'm going.
Executed.
There we go one point to 5 7 5 so one seconds.
Let me do it one more time.
What you actually see I don't think executed.
There we go.
Is that it varies.
So it changes even on my own computer.
Nothing really has changed.
I haven't added code I haven't changed the numbers here.
It's the exact same code but we're getting a different output.
Before I forget.
Let's go over to the second solution.
So the exact same number let me just make sure I didn't leave off or add is zero.
Yes they are the same and I'm doing the same thing taking performance.
Now the beginning and performance start now at the end.
You say should show what that looks like.
You can see that kind of a large number at this point because I've had this open for a number of minutes
if I refresh the page though I just did.
Now it's at 2000 milliseconds which is two seconds.
Now if I did it again we're at six point six seconds.
And if we subtract the two you know four seconds roughly in between.
Anyway we're doing the same thing here.
OK.
So now if I run this you can see we get a way smaller number but it's still actually I guess it doesn't
look like it's changing here is it.
Then the measurements the differences are too small not really to capture.
But my point is that this is significantly shorter in duration.
But the same data as this one.
Here we go at one point two four seconds compared to basically zero seconds.
So that seems like a good sign for this solution.
It seems like it's much more efficient and that's great.
But this process is not the most reliable of manually timing things like this before and after and comparing
it to the other function and it's not that easy for us to talk about.
How would I actually write down how would I give it a label of how efficient this one is compared to
this one.
Is it based off of the percentage of speed.
Is it do I subtract the number of seconds or milliseconds it gets a little blurry.
This brings us to the problem with time which I'm reserving for my end of life memoir title problem
with time.
It's just a nice little sounds very deep.
So the first is that different machines will record different times.
So it's not reliable depending on the specifications on how much of a machine and what's currently happening
on that machine what code is running the time the results you can get will be different.
That doesn't really mean that we'll get the opposite results where the first solution is suddenly faster
than the second one.
But it means that the margins can change the actual measurements could be different and are almost guaranteed
to be different times.
And as we saw this same machine will record different times.
So in my browser I just did the exact same code.
That first example and it differed each time by a little bit which isn't really a problem but it still
shows that it's not precise and that we can't rely on that.
And second of all or third of all I guess is that for fast algorithms things that are happening on a
really really fast scale speed measurements might not be precise enough.
We have two or three or four algorithms and they're all super fast.
They're doing something very quickly.
There still is one that is going to be fastest or most efficient.
But if our timing functions can't figure it out because they're you know the smallest interval of time
that can be measured isn't good enough then it doesn't really help us.
So how do we walk through our code and actually talk in general terms about which code is better without
having to go and time it.
So I want to be clear I'm not saying that timing your code is a bad idea.
I do it all the time but I'm more saying is that it would be cool if there was another way that didn't
involve having to set up a new file and actually go through the process of timing our code.
What if our code takes you know an hour something massive and I'm comparing it to another version that
takes four hours.
I don't want to have to run a test to figure out which one is faster.
We want to be able to assign a value to.
In general terms talk about how code compares to other code without having to go through all of this.
And that's where Big-O notation comes in and that's coming up next.
Cliffhanger sorry.