OK.
Well we talked about the problems with using time as our way of comparing code.
So for not using time what should we do.
Well as very similar thing rather than counting the exact seconds that it takes for code to run which
can change so much what we can do instead is count a number of simple operations that a computer has
to perform because that remains constant no matter what computer we're on.
So if we just simplified it like crazy and said that you know this one algorithm has five operations
to run and the other one has seven.
It doesn't matter what you know the specifications of my computer are or the mood that my laptops in
that day the time we get might be different but the times will always be determined by the number of
operations so we can use that rather than the exact times you can just focus on the number of simple
operations the computer has to perform.
So what I mean by simple operation is if we take a look at this example the shorter one line version
that was faster we've got a multiplication happening.
We have after that an addition.
So that's another operation.
And then we have a division things like the number one or two aren't operations.
The computer doesn't really need to do much there at least compared to multiplication addition and division.
Those are operations so there are three operations and it doesn't really matter what an is if any is
to or if and it's a billion.
There's only three calculations that are happening.
So three simple operations regardless of the size of N whether it's small or massive If you compare
that to our other solution.
The first one.
This one has a few more operations.
So let's start here.
We see a plus sign which we saw in the last video and we counted that as one operation.
But there's a difference here because this is in a loop.
So if any is 5 we're adding 5 things so it's five operations if any is 20 there's 20 pluses.
If it's a billion there's a billion pluses.
So it's not just one operation anymore it's an operations and additions.
And actually it's more than that because the equal sign the equal sign is another.
It's an assignment.
Now I hope you we shouldn't get too bogged down in the details of counting every minute operation because
as you've seen a moment all that matters is the general terms of things are very very fuzzy overview.
So this distinction doesn't really matter.
But to be clear yes this is another operation and it happens as and grows there's more assignments that
happen quickly running through these.
We've also got this here.
So plus plus it is shorthand for I plus equals 1.
So there's a plus in there and there's an equals.
So two simple operations however they happen one time each per.
And that's not a good way of saying that they happen more as an.
GROSS So if it's 10 We've got 10 additions and 10 assignments if and is a billion.
We've got a billion scale with and then appear we've got one assignment so this only happens once because
it's on a loop.
It happens one time at the beginning and then we also have this here this is a single assignment I equals
one that happens once as well at the beginning of the loop.
We start with equals 1 and then we've also got comparisons here.
I less than or equal to end.
And that is in comparison to again if we're dealing with 20 this loop runs 20 times we compare I to
end 20 times.
So yes counting these operations can be tricky overall how and when we say there are if the previous
one there was three operations what do we say about this one.
I mean it's not a static number it's not a constant number like 3.
So how do we generalize it.
There's a lot of ways of counting it.
And of arriving at an answer but it could be as high as 5 and plus 2 right 1 2 3 4 5 plus 2.
So if an is 10 we've got 50 operations plus two that are outside the loop.
So that means 52.
That's one way of doing it.
But what I want to say is that it doesn't really matter because regardless of the exact number whether
it's 5 plus 2 or 2 and or 3 and or even 50 and it doesn't matter because what we care about is a general
trend.
And this is what we're going to see a lot with big-O.
We're focused on the big picture.
So in this case as and grows the number of operations grow roughly in proportion with an.