OK so this will be really quick video but I want to show something.
I'm kind of proud of this is a little widget that I made that helps us understand or plot the time that
functions take to execute and get a general graph a chart that shows us a trend.
So there's only seven of them in here and we're going to focus on the first two add up to first.
I had to give them unique names before they were both called to add up to but add up to first uses the
loop add up to second uses that little shortcut.
See if it's that big enough to see.
And so we select one of them.
Then I can specify a value for N and hit plot and then change and.
And what I'll do is increase and then we'll see some sort of chart that shows what happens as and grows
larger.
And this is basically just done with a timer in the background.
So click plot starts a timer it does the operation stops the timer and then plots it and then we do
it again and it connects the dots and builds a little graph.
So what I want to show you is that if we take this first one out up to second which was the one that
was faster we already know it's faster.
But what we talked about in the last video is that there are three operations three things that take
time and think about it that way.
The other one there was a lot of things that take time but this there's three and there's always three
things that take time.
No matter what end is if it's ten or a billion.
So I'm going to plug in a number for her and like 100 and I'm going to hit plot and it's going to time
it.
So what is plotting for us here is not the number of operations because that's always three it's plotting
the time.
OK.
So we only have one value so it doesn't really mean much.
Let's add in 1000 There we go.
Let's add in 10000.
OK so it does seem like this is an extreme slope all of a sudden but just hang in there because we pop
back up and if we look at the difference here it's a matter of what are we talking about is these.
Remember these are nanoseconds with that little symbol means it's a very small fraction of a second.
So it looks like this chart is all over the place and it is on such a small scale.
But what I want to show you is that we don't really care about that.
We care about a general trend and when we switch over to add up to first I'm going to do the same thing.
But I'm going to start again with one hundred.
So we're going out of the first 100.
And remember that in this case unlike Adams's second well it was a constant number of operations and
up to first the number of operations depends on and because of this loop.
So if we start with 100 OK you can already see that it's definitely slower.
Let's go to 1000 All right it definitely looks slower again.
Ten thousand keep going here.
Keep adding in
going to keep going so that we can get a generalized trend.
OK.
In the classroom took a little bit and the next one will take a couple of seconds.
I'm not going to do it.
But what we can see here is that there's a pretty good line that's pretty easy to follow.
And as n grows larger which is down here the time grows in proportion which we kind of discussed in
the last video although we were talking about the number of operations but this is actually the time
being printed here.
And you can see that it follows what we were talking about.
It's not perfect but overall it's pretty close.
And same thing down here where we said that for add up to second it's always three operations.
It's the same number of operations no matter what end is.
So the time is pretty constant.
It fluctuated as you saw when we were working on such a small scale.
It did go up and down but overall when you're comparing the two this is significantly better.
And if I run this last one here I mean take a look at that and grows the time doesn't really change.
Now if we zoomed in it would be slightly different but it doesn't matter because this is a massive difference
1.2 seconds versus a couple of milliseconds.
So we'll be revisiting this tool to talk about some of these others as we go.
But here are first to generalize trends where we're comparing two algorithms that do the same thing
and you can see that they have vastly different big picture overviews of their performance.