All right.
Welcome back.
So now we're going to talk more about simplifying big-O expressions.
We've already seen a little bit of this.
I'm going to rewind a couple of slides back if you remember this slide where we talked about how counting
all these different operations can be tricky and that it doesn't really matter the exact count.
All that we care about is really the general trend.
And so we simplified this from five and plus two to just.
And we said that as and grows the runtime grows proportionately with and it doesn't matter if it's two
times and or 10 times then or a thousand times and the trend line that we're drawing on that chart is
proportionate with N.
So now we're going to talk about some actual rules we can use to help us when simplifying these expressions.
There are some helpful rules of thumb that we can follow.
Rule of thumbs.
Rules of thumb rule of thumbs.
OK.
Whichever one it is these rules are consequences of the definition of big-O.
Once again that we only care about the broadest fuzziest big picture view.
So constants don't matter.
So if we have something like 0 of two n we simplify that down just to over in 0 of 500.
Simplify that just to 0 of 1 because 0 500 remember is just that's basically saying there are 500 operations
every time no matter what end is and to that line that chart is going to be flat and instead of saying
it's going to be fought at 500 we'll just simplify it down saying that it's 0 0 1 that's how we say
something is constant constant run time 0 of 13 and squared.
Well we don't need that constant we just do over and square it because the difference when we're looking
at this.
Basically if if our graph went all the way to infinity as far as and and we're looking at the difference
between 13 and squared and just end squared and a thousand squared they're all going to look very very
similar.
Once we elongate that chart to that level.
So it doesn't really matter.
So we just get rid of that because now we can compare these and we know that.
OK this is going to be faster than this and this is going to be the slowest.
Just based off of the charts the general fuzzy trends so smaller terms also don't matter.
The constants out front in front of and but smaller terms like this of and plus 10 just get rid of the
10 his own event or in this case 0 of 1000 plus 50 can simplify that just to oven.
You don't need the constants and we don't need the small term at the end.
And how about this one.
And squared plus five and plus eight.
Well once again look at it from a huge huge like imagine we're noter outer space looking at this chart
and we have to figure out what really matters what's the trend at the end of the day.
Five ten plus eight is meaningless compared to end squared.
When you're dealing with a number like if you just plug in the number one thousand five times 1005 and
give just 5000 but n squared 1000 times 1000 is 10 million.
I think I did that right.
So we're talking about 10 million plus five thousand plus eight just as an example.
The difference between 10 million five thousand eight versus 10 million is so small and that's just
when we plug in 1000.
But now imagine we plug in a billion.
And that difference is going to be meaningless from the big picture view.
So we just simplify it down to 0 and squared.
So a couple of things that you can keep in mind when analyzing complexity with big o things get complicated
and you can nitpick and stress out about the individual details.
But there are some rules of thumb again that can help and they don't always work but it's a good starting
point.
The first is that arithmetic operations are constant.
So for adding something or subtracting or dividing and so on that's going to be constant time it doesn't
really matter the size of the number your computer takes roughly the same amount of time to do two plus
two as it does a million plus two variable assignment is also constant.
So the computer takes roughly the same amount of time to make a variable you know X equals 1000 compared
to X equals 20000 or a million.
It's roughly the same accessing element in an array using an index.
So if I have an array and I find the first item or the tenth item as long as I use the index or I'm
working with an object and I have a key that I'm using to access data that's constant runtime as well.
The next rule is that in a loop the complexity is the length of the loop times the complexity for that
whatever happens inside the loop.
So if we were working with a loop that's looping over a list or looping through like we did earlier
is the road to end as and grows that loop grows.
But then whatever happens inside that loop is also consequential because if we have nested loops as
we've seen then we end up with potentially end squared runtime.
So again you don't need to memorize this but it's just nice to.
I'm going to throw them out there so I can come back to them.
So let's see a couple of examples.
Here's a new function.
It's called log at least five.
And just copy it over.
I pasted in and if I call it a pass and a number like 10 and it's going to log 10 but if I plug in one
it prints 1 2 3 4 or 5.
So all that it does is it prints numbers up to N but at a minimum it prints 1 2 3 4 5.
So if I give it three we still get five but if I give it seven we get seven printed out one two three
four five six seven.
So what's the what's the big O here.
How would we categorize this.
So we have a loop and this loop is going to go from 1 to either five or end whichever one is larger.
So we could worry about the five but we only really need to worry about that as is small.
And what we care about is what happens and grows larger.
So it's and continues to grow and grow and grow towards infinity.
What happens to the runtime.
Well if and is 10 million this loop is going to run 10 million times.
This five doesn't matter.
So we can just simplify this and say that the big-O of this is over of and because this and grows the
number of operations grows in proportion with N.
So here's another one.
This is the opposite log at most 5 pasted in.
And if I try hopes there we go at most 5 if I plug in 30 it still only gives me 5.
I plug in 3.
It gives me three.
So it's going to take whatever is smaller if I give it a large number it's going to if it's larger than
5 it's only going to log 5 if I give it something less than 5 then it will log.
Oh it's also important.
It's only with positive numbers.
If I give it a zero it doesn't do anything.
And that is important to note because as n grows here it kind of doesn't matter because we're going
to take the min which is five.
So if Enge approaching a thousand this loop runs five times and is approaching a million the loop runs
five times if any to then the loop runs two times and three times.
So the graph would actually look like you know two and then three and then five and then it's say static
at 5 and we can simplify that by saying that it's end gross which is what we care about the big-O of
this is just constant it's 0 1.
So rather than 0 5 Remember we can simplify that down and say Oh for one.
So if we were to plot both of these out what we see the general trend is something like this where I
forgot to have all those little transitions we can ignore all these other ones we haven't talked about
things like a log and log in.
But what I've done here is just put them all in a chart so we can see first of all 0 1 is a flightline
and that's great if we can have runtime of one.
That is fantastic to have constant runtime it's pretty rare when we're dealing with some more advanced
algorithms something like of n it's ok you can see the general trajectory it's much better than something
like quadratic and squared runtime.
So when we have something like log at least five as and grows this direction the runtime is also going
to grow and when we have at most 5 the second one which we said had constant runtime as and grows once
we get past the first little one two three four once we get past the first four and we approach infinity
and it's going to always be 5 which we just say and it's always constant.
So I know that this is a lot and some of you might be struggling with it and that's to be expected what
I think is most important going forward is that if I'm if I say something like this algorithm that we've
just written has a runtime of oh events squared that you could identify that that is not as good as
something like Of end.
For example and I could show you this chart but I just hope that you can understand after the end of
the section we're not done yet but by the end of the section what it means when I say that something
has 0 0 of and or 0 of one constant runtime and how that compares to some of the other options.
And like I said we haven't gone over all of these yet.
So we'll get there.
Next up a couple little exercises simplifying expressions.