Hey welcome back.
So we're still talking about searching algorithms but now we're talking about a different type which
has to do with searching for substrings in a larger string.
So there are two that we're going to focus on.
And the first one is that naive string search I don't think there's actually a name for this.
This is just the most basic common way of doing this problem.
And then we're going to see a better implementation.
That is definitely a little more complicated in the next video or two videos from now.
But we're going to start with the basic solution.
So imagine that you want to count the number of times a smaller string appears in a longer string.
A straightforward approach involves checking pairs of characters individually.
Let's imagine we have this string here.
Harold said haha in Hamburg.
So if we were searching for just a single character like I don't know the letter II for example that's
very easy.
That's basically what we've done.
You just do a linear search.
You could treat this as an array.
Right.
Each check is this and I hope is this and why is this and why is this night over and over until you
find a night or until you hit the end.
So that's nothing new.
If we're searching for a single character we can use what we've already done instead of accessing items
in an array we access using an index in the string.
Just like this right with zero.
And I would check 1 and it would check too.
But if you're checking for a pattern for example I want to see if H A ha ha ha is in there that takes
some more work because we're no longer just checking a single character against a single character.
We're checking.
OK let's walk through the string and it looks like we have an H that to match.
And then we have an A O that's a match.
And then in our op not a match anymore.
So then we start over and we look for an H again.
So I actually have a little diagram here.
Imagine that this is our long string we're searching through and we're trying to find o m g inside of
this.
So the simplest approach is going to involve basically if we put them next to one another we're going
to start by walking one character at a time and we're just going to check is this w here equal to the
0 at the beginning or are these two characters the same.
No.
OK.
Move on.
Now we have a match.
Oh.
So now we move on to the second character.
We're looking for an M.
We don't find one.
So we move on w no we don't find that.
So we move on again.
OK.
Oh and oh that's a match.
Now we move on to the next character.
MNM.
That's good.
G and G.
And we hit the end of our short string we found a match.
So now we we add a counter we increment something to keep track of how many matches we found.
We found one so far.
Now we move on to the M.
So basically we do it for every single character here and we start at the beginning of our smaller string
and check it against every individual character in the longer string.
So that's not a match that's of a match.
That's not a match.
Now we have a match at the O.
Then we check the next character m check which still match G and we increment.
I don't know why this when I made this side I just checked.
These are the same size.
Somehow when it's there's some weird bug when it's being displayed.
But these should be count evenly.
There's two matches and that's what we want to do.
We want to try and implement this naive string search.
So there is a better way of doing this but it involves a lot more code that we'll see in two videos
from now.
And it has a much fancier name but this approach is one that just takes a couple of lines.
A couple of loops.
Let's walk through the pseudo code.
So the idea again is for you to try and implement this on your own using the pseudo code.
If you have the time or willpower or energy here's the steps.
So loop over the longer string.
So I guess I didn't say define a function this time but to find a function that takes two strings and
just call it maybe string search.
It takes the larger string and then the pattern that we're looking for.
And then you loop over each character in the longer string and then we have another loop over the shorter
string.
And then we just check.
Basically if the characters don't match break out of the inner loop so stop.
And if they do match.
If we find a match for 0 for example and O M G then you move onto the next character keep going until
you hit the end of the short string.
And if you do hit the end of that short string that means that you find a match.
So if you complete the loop find a match increment the count of matches and then return the count at
the end.
And so if Count should start at zero we don't need to have any special error handling if there are no
matches count stays at zero.
So just return the count at the end.
So hopefully that makes sense.
Loop over the longer string inside of that loop a nested loop over the shorter string.
And then if you make it to the end of that shorter string and you haven't broken out yet then add one
to the counter.
OK so give it a shot in the next video we'll have a solution.