All right.
Welcome back.
So in this video we'll go ahead and implement the naive string search algorithm.
So I already have a snippet created do this wherever you prefer sublime some text editor a snippet yourself.
It doesn't matter.
So I have one called Search naive string and I'll close that for now.
First let's just define the function so it needs to accept two strings.
I'm going to call it naive search and it accepts the long string and a short string or long and pattern.
I've also seen that pattern like that.
I like short though.
And then the first thing that will do is just do a sample call down here so naive search and let's say
for example that would we would be calling it with maybe Loree mold.
Hello elde.
As a verb and we're searching for EHLO well in that string.
OK.
So first of all we're going to need to get some loops going as this pseudo code mentions loop over the
longer string and then nested inside loop over the shorter string.
So let's just start with the most basic loop over the long string.
So for var i equals zero while I less than long length I plus plus.
So that should give us every eye.
We just look at it and execute this make Consul a bit bigger.
C'mon.
All right.
So we get zero to 10 there's 10 or 11 characters in there.
Then let's do the same thing this time for J or whatever whatever letter you prefer.
But J is the standard one h i j k.
Yes.
Yeah ok for var J equals zero.
J This time is less than short length J plus plus it gets a little confusing when you start working
with i and j keeping track of which one is which.
So if we just printed out I comma J each time through.
Those are going to be numbers.
So why don't we do instead let's do long of-I So we see which character we'd be referencing.
And short of J.
Now we're going to get a lot of prints.
This is a nested loops so we're looping 10 times here.
But each of those 10 times we're looping three times for the L-A well.
So if I clear this out I'll make this larger and try it again.
All right.
So you can see what we get here is basically we start with L on both of them out and out.
And then the Eneloop goes to 0.
So we have L and O and then l l again and then we move to 0 and we start over o n l o n o o n l.
OK so what do we actually want to do.
Rather than just printing them out.
Well the first thing we can do.
Let's forget the fact that i and j are numbers.
And let's just say that there are the letters exactly.
It's a little easier to talk about.
So let's say that I started L and J also starts as l.
So remember that I is her outer loop so I is going to stay L as we progress through EHLO Well if that
makes sense as J increases as to increase three times and then reset.
In order for eye to increase once we start the loop is l j is l.
We compare them looks good.
Whenever there isn't a match we break out of this inner loop and we move on to the next iteration.
But let's let's just focus on in this case there is a match.
ELEANOR HALL So what do we do next.
Well the next comparison is still going to be L but it's going to be compared to 0.
Because we're moving basically J moves on and it becomes O because we're looping through this first.
But that's not going to work.
To directly compare 0 and L because we know that's not a match.
So what we want to compare it to is one more than l.
So as we move through J We want to also look ahead in I even though I it's going to be stuck at zero
if that makes sense as we look through this as our short pattern allwell continues to loop.
We're still comparing to out each time.
So instead we want to look ahead and the best way to do that or one way at least that I'm going to do
it is by adding I to J.
It is kind of confusing.
But now if we go back to numbers and we say they both started at zero.
OK.
So there's a match.
Now J goes up to 1.
So we're going to compare Elo of one which is 0 to this string.
The gold but instead of zero we're going to add them together.
So where we were before plus where we are now in J.
Which means that we're going to look ahead to 0 because that would be index of 1.
So that's a match next time through our short string right index of two.
So we're going to compare this L and we are going to add 0 plus 2 to give us index of two of this string.
Looking ahead and it's not a match.
So then we break out.
That means that we started again at all.
But then once we get up to here which is what index of 0 1 2 3 4 5 index of 6.
So in the scenario where we are here index of six in the large string index of 0 in the short string
there is a match.
Right.
Those are matches.
So then we move on.
And the short string J goes up by 1.
It now becomes 1 but we don't want to compare lower levels of index 6.
We want.
The old index 7 and we add them together.
So hopefully you can see the approach we're looking ahead and to do that.
It's not too bad.
All we do is add I and J together and access using that new index access the long string.
So here's my approach sort of con. about logging.
We'll just basically check if the short string of J is not equal to the long string of I Plus J.
Now if that happens and we'll break out.
So let's let's make this a loop.
I mean a conditional like this.
This means break out of this short loop and start on J again at zero.
So anytime there isn't a match We're going to break.
So if I add this constant log in there now I'm printing short J and long i Plus J.
I'm going to clear out like this and let's see what we get.
OK.
So our comparisons we start with L and L that makes sense.
There's a match.
So we don't break out and we move on to 0 and we compare 0 to the next character which is 0 and then
there's a match.
So we move on again to L and we compare it to our in which case there wasn't a match.
So if I added in a console that log here to say break and rerun this you could see what happens.
So it looks like there's a match L and L O N O.
And then there isn't a match.
So we break and when we break what is happening there is that J is being reset.
This inner loop is going back to zero meaning we started elegant but the outer loop I moves on.
So now we're starting here at 0.
So after that break we do L and O.
And that's not a match that to break.
So then we move forward again.
This time we're talking about R and L and that's not a match.
So we break we keep going until finally we get here and there's a match.
So then we move on and there's another match and another match.
But what do we not have right now.
We're not actually incrementing any sort of counter when we find a four match.
So we found a full match right here.
Elo Well they all those are two pair or three pairs that matched correctly.
So what we need to do is make a variable appear.
Let's just call it.
Count equals zero.
And when should we increment counts.
Well the way that we know that we have successfully made it through this string.
Because if we get to the last character and there's a match if we've made it to that point that means
that J is going to be whatever the last character in the short string is.
If that makes sense so if we had told ELO Ltd we know that we finished.
If J is 0 1 2 3 4 if J is for or in this case if J is 2.
If we've made it to that point.
So we can just add a conditional check just to an if and then we just check if J is equal to the short
string length but minus one because of length it's going to be greater than the index.
If that's the case let's add one to do plus two plus plus like that.
And then at the end let's return count let's see how many braces do I have.
So that's conditional loop loop.
OK here we go.
OK so let's see what happens now.
So why don't I add a of log in here.
Found one clear my Consul rerun the whole thing started again.
OK.
So if you see we have the same exact thing almost a match but there's not a break.
Keep going.
But then hooray we found a match.
And so this code is printing.
So count is going up by 1.
So if you get this if it works for you or if he had a slightly different solution but you're still it's
working.
That's all that matters.
If you have two loops and you're getting it to work your logic can be slightly different.
You could work from the end for example.
You don't have to work from the beginning forward or you could work backwards.
That doesn't really matter.
But if you have it working great.
If you want you can stick around and we can walk through this one more time just to see exactly how
it works.
I'm going to shorten this up because like some of the other solutions we can put these on single lines
make it a little nicer like that.
Same thing with our second if we set up here just like that and it still works should still work at
least are getting results printed come back consul.
Yes we're getting one.
Cool.
All right.
So if you want to stick around for the extra walkthrough Let's try it one more time or something different.
Let's try it with L O which in this case we should get two matches.
Is that working.
Yes we get two.
All right.
So what's happening here.
Well we loop through every character for example.
So it's where we start.
And on the second string we look through every character.
So we started well and immediately we check if this character doesn't match I Plus J of this character
so I and J are both zero.
So this means for checking the first characters together 0 0 0.
So if they don't match immediately break out and that means that we move on.
And that eye is now right here.
So if they do match though which they happen to match what do we do.
Well since we're still in this loop we move on.
Jay is now pointing to this but I still hear.
So now we add those two together.
Jay is now one is still zero.
So that gives us a total of one and we compare this to that and there's a match at which point we increment
count because J is equal to the length of the short string.
That's how we know we're on the last iteration J and this case would be equal to 1 0 1.
When we get to 1 and we haven't broken out yet if we get to this point that means we found a match.
All right.
So then it repeats again until it finds this match.
So hopefully that's clear.
And if we try it with something that isn't in there like pop we should just get zero.
And we do.
So we don't have to account for anything because we have this count variable.
It's unlike binary search for example where we had to handle errors not errors but we had to handle
those edge cases.
If we don't find anything the count euro.
All right.
So that is an implementation of naive string searching.
Next we're going to see a better implementation of a different sort of string search algorithm.
Definitely a little more complicated and longer but it be fun to talk about.
I think.