They will come back.
So when this section we're talking about search and searching algorithms and when I say search some
of you might think of something like Google right away.
Now the algorithm behind Google and its search is very complex probably one of the most complicated
algorithms out there and it's probably more like 10 different algorithms that are being tested at any
given time and things are being tweaked.
Not to mention the fact that this algorithm changes so much depending on who you are your browsing history
the things that you've done and the things you've clicked on.
So when I search for howler monkey I might see different results than if you search for howler monkey.
So we're not going to even try and recreate anything like this.
What we will get to later in the course not right now but later once we cover graphs and trees and other
complicated data structures We'll discuss how to search and traverse something like a graph which is
closer to what Google is doing.
We're not going to talk about the machine learning behind all of this and how it decides you know what
is best tailored to me cold versus to someone else down the street.
We're just going to talk about when Google first started before you even cared about people in ads and
tracking all of that if there even was a period.
Who knows.
I doubt there was.
But if there was then we're going to kind of approximate that.
But for now we're focusing on are even simpler searching algorithms that are really commonly used.
But we may not often call it search for example but say that we have a string and we're checking to
see if if there's another string contained in that string.
Or let's say that I have a Web site and I want people to sign up and they add their user name and they
sign up the username and password.
All we need to tell them if their user name is taken.
So let's say there's not even a database don't worry about how this works.
Let's say I have an array of user names if somebody types in a user name into the form and says OK I'm
going to be I hate cash that's going to be my username and password will be secretly loves cats 72 or
something.
If I hit enter I need to.
Me the developer needs to take that username and somehow figure out if it's taken.
So if I have a list of user names how am I going to figure out if this I hate cat is contained in that
list.
And javascript has many built in ways of doing this.
You could for example do index of it's a simple one and let's try that username set index of.
I hate cats.
This is using a searching algorithm.
Behind the scenes and so we get 11.
And if it weren't in there like that we should get a negative one.
There are some others that will see some other options but what we're going to talk about in this section
is how these are working behind the scenes and how we can implement our own versions of some of these
functions built in methods and how we can search across arrays and strings.
Or one more really quick example if we had a list of states an array in the US.
I apologize for being America centric in video but if this is what we had we wanted to make sure a user
was putting a valid state.
Well we could check it against this but how are we going to do that what's the best algorithm.
We're going to get into that in this section.
So what are our objectives.
First describe what a searching algorithm is.
We kind of talked about that a bit and we're going to implement linear search on arrays.
Then we're going to talk about a slightly better algorithm binary search on sorted arrays.
So we'll talk about the pros and cons of those approaches.
Then we'll implement a naive string searching algorithm as well as something called the KMP string searching
algorithm.
So this section is really the first where we're getting into named algorithms in the recursion section
for example we talked about how to write a solution to the factorial problem but it didn't have a name
like we haven't really seen code that has a particular name to the solution but that's going to change
in this section and that will be something that we see throughout the course is a recurring theme.
We'll talk about sorting those particular names for a lot of common sorting algorithms.
So those are our goals and the first thing we're going to do with the next video is implement linear
search.