OK so in this video on to implement our basic linear search.
So here's the pseudocode again.
You can write a function or call it let's just call it index for linear search and it's going to accept
an array and a value.
So we can start there.
So I've made a snippet already called Search linear I'm having them.
I'll start with search just like I did with recursion so that they're just grouped together.
So I made that over here new snippet and it closed that away now.
And let's define our function calls linear search and it takes an array and a value.
Let's do it like that.
All right so that's the first step.
So I should be able to call it like this.
Then your search pasand my array of will just do numbers.
Thirty four fifty six one two and then the value I'm looking for is 1 and it should return the index
which is 0 1 2 which should return to.
So the next step is to just loop through the array and check if the current array element is equal to
the value.
So let's start by looping through the array.
That's going to be a for loop or I mean you could do a WHILE loop if you wanted to.
You could even just do a foreach.
There's many ways that will do Forfar equals zero.
We're going to go from the beginning.
So while I is less than array length.
Add one to my and then you need to check if the current array element is equal to the value.
So we access the current array element with R R R R array of.
I am going to check if it's equal to the value.
So we need to make this an if statement.
And if that's the case what are we going to do.
We're going to return.
Well we want to return as you can see here the index at which the element is found.
So that's pretty easy because we already have I which is why I chose not to use a for loop or excuse
me for each other you can still do for each with an index.
But we have I right out of the box because for a loop.
So we just return I.
So in this case I will be zero.
We start we check is array of equal to the value.
No is 34 1.
No.
Next up is 1 is 56 1.
Nope.
Next time through eyes 2.
So we check array of 2 which is 1.
Is that equal to one that we're looking for.
Yes.
So we return I which is 2.
Then we have our final catch all if the value is never found return negative 1.
And the easiest way to do that is just after the loop.
That means we've hit the end.
So if we haven't returned by now that means it's not in there.
So we can just return negative one just like that and a small simplification that we can make we can
get rid of.
You can do this on a single line.
The if statement the conditional just move that back up there like that.
Just shorten it a little bit but it's just a personal preference.
So if Trayvon is triple equal to value return I.
So now let's test this out.
It's a linear search of this we should if it works get 0 1 2.
Going to use command enter to run it.
And there we go we get to let's try it again this time to add some other numbers.
And let's check for 56 which is actually.
Wow.
I'm so bad at picking round numbers I pick the same number twice.
Let's change this one to be 51 and if I run it we get index of 6 0 1 2 3 4 5 6.
Finally let's test it on something that's not in there like 100.
We get negative 1.
Now if I still have my state's array Rigaud because I made this a snippet I should be able to do linear
search pass in states and then check what's the index of Texas for example.
And we get 50 and if I check for you one more.
How about Texas with an X-ray.
It's not in there.
Cool.
So this is linear search.
This is what behind the scenes the builtin index of is doing any of these basic searches that we already
talked about in javascript.
What else was there that was 1 0 find index index of includes all of those are using a linear search
and the last thing we should talk about is the big O of this.
So take a moment and try and figure it out.
The time complexity as the length of that array grows how does the time that it takes the worst case.
How much time does it take.
And the answer is that it's over.
And so as our RE gets longer we have to do more searches we have to do more operations if we're searching
for the last item Wyoming.
We might have to do 59 or we would have to do 15:9 searches but if our states were instead 5000 States
and we're searching for the last one we would have to check 5000 different items.
So as and grows is the length of the array grows so does the amount of time.
So this is 0 0 and it's linear which is also it's called venir search give it away a little bit.
And next we're going to see another search that works differently where if the data is sorted as I hinted
at there's a better way of searching.
And it's a little bit more complicated but it's a fun sort of first algorithm to step things up a bit
from linear search and it's faster.
So we'll see that in the next video.