Welcome back.
I've decided to make a separate video on big-O for linear search.
I've actually already covered this content but I realized some people were skipping through videos and
not watching everything.
So if I have a video titled linear search Big O.
I found more people will actually watch that because it's really important stuff.
Same thing for binary search after this.
All right so here's a quick video on how linear search performs at least as far as time complexity is
concerned.
So best case we have an array of a million integers or 50 integers.
The very best case is that we find the thing we're looking for right away.
So that's the best possible scenario right.
That's pretty rare.
Depending on the size of your data the worst case is 0 of an.
So if we have a million integers in an array and we're searching for the last one or we're searching
for something that's not in there we're going to have to look a million times.
We have 50 things in there and it's the very last element that we're looking for.
We're going to have to look 50 times and average is also 0 7 and you might think well isn't it actually
less than an on average because sometimes will find it.
You know right away sometimes you'll find it in the middle of the array.
Two thirds of the way.
Three quarters of the way.
Should that average out somewhere.
And the answer is No not as far as Bingo is concerned we care about just the general trend.
So as an grows the length of the array grows or the length the string or whatever we're working with
so does the average amount of time it takes.
Remember we throw away all constants.
So two and a half and point to five.
And those are constants.
We ignore those and we just simplify it to 11.
OK so that's linear search.
It's the best we can do with an unsorted piece of data.
But next we're going to talk about binary search which is much better and I'll have a separate video
afterwards.
Once we learn how to implement it on the big O of binary search and how we derive it.
That's coming up.