All right.
So let's get on with the details of the implementation like I did in the last video or two videos that
go for a linear search.
I'm going to give you some rough pseudo code some some kind of bullet points that you can follow and
you can fill in the blanks.
It's not going to be a line by line guide to what you need to do but it should set you on the right
track.
And if you have the time the energy the willpower to do it to actually write it out yourself I highly
recommend it.
It's not terribly long it's a maybe eight lines.
Definitely less than 10.
And two of those are just the function definition anyway so it's pretty short and definitely worth your
time.
So write a function call it binary search and accepts a sorted array.
Remember we have to assume that it's sorted and a value that you're looking for.
And let's also assume we're only working with numbers for now.
Then you need to create two variables one that's going to point to the index that the left were starting
at so 0 for our left arrow or left pointer and then a right pointer at the far other end of the array.
The end.
So that's going to be whatever the length is minus 1.
So we'll have left is 0 and then right is 10 or 1000 or whatever the end of the array is then roughly
what you're going to do.
You're going to loop over and over and there's two things that you're checking for.
One is have you found the element.
So while you haven't found the element keep looping But along with that there's a second condition which
is you want to make sure that you're only looping while the left comes before the right pointer and
then you're also going to pick the middle and you can just take an average of the left and the right
not the values you should remember but the position.
So if left starts at 0 and right starts at 10 then you could take the middle to be five and then you're
basically going to loop and you're going to check first of all is the element equal to the middle is
the middle.
What we're looking for if it is then just return we're done.
So if you find that value return the index if the value is too small then you're going to move the left
pointer up and if the value is too large you move the right pointer down.
And then finally at the end if you never find the value just return negative 1.
OK.
So there is some flexibility in your implementation.
There's a couple of things I didn't mention here that we'll talk about in the next video like small
changes we could make but this is a rough outline.
You pick a left pick a right you pick a middle and then you loop and you basically keep looping while
you haven't found while the middle is not the answer then you're going to check if your value is less
than or greater than the middle.
And then depending on that you reassign the left or the right and you pick a new middle.
So in the next video I'll have a solution walkthrough.