All right.
Welcome back.
The next pattern we'll talk about it's called the sliding window.
So this really is useful when we have a set of data like an array or a string again and we're looking
for a subset of that data that is continuous in some way.
So for example here's a string.
And if I ask you to write a function to find the longest sequence of unique characters.
So you know you would start.
Let's see.
Well we've got HGL those are three unique characters in a row but then we hit another L right here.
So this is the longest one we have so far.
Nope that's only that's not going to work.
So then we can look at L O T H E R and that's looks like it's going to be our longest string of unique
characters.
Unless I'm losing my mind here because then we hit this eve.
So anyway this is one example of a problem we could solve with a sliding window approach.
The other one I'm going to show you has to do with finding a max subarray sum.
So we pass in an array like this.
And then a number and we're trying to find the max sum of two digits that are next to one another or
in this case four digits that are next to one another.
So this would turn 10 because the two digits next to one another that have the largest sum are eight
into which is 10 and it will come right back to this.
So what we do is we make a window which can be a single variable or can be a sub array or even another
string if you want it to.
And we move that window depending on the condition.
We slide it up usually from left to right.
If we start at the beginning you could go from right to left you could start in the middle I guess.
But usually we move the window from the left.
The beginning of the element or the beginning of the array or string towards the end.
And sometimes you might make a new window.
So I'll show you what that really means.
But it's useful in these problems where we're keeping track of a subset of data in a larger set of data.
So back to this problem.
Right a function called Max subarray sum which accepts an array of integers and a number called.
And so it doesn't have to be sorted the array.
This is just any integers in an array.
And then we pass and the second number is already mentioned and your function should calculate the maximum
sum of an consecutive elements in that array.
So whatever we pass in here like Erda showed you two should return 10 because 8 and 2 is the largest
sum of two consecutive numbers.
Here we have four.
Well what's the largest sum of four numbers we know at 17 and I believe that is.
I think it's these four right.
That's seven eight nine yeah.
17 and it's close because there's you know this subarray here gives us 16 I believe.
So right and we've got this one here which also gives us 16 but this one is the largest sum of four
continuous consecutive numbers which is 70.
Also you know an edge case if it's empty should return NULL anyway.
That's the problem.
And to solve it there's a couple of approaches.
Of course the naive version the simple version is basically to start right here.
Let's actually go with this example for start right here in a loop and then have a second loop that
looks ahead and sumps together four items and you create a variable to keep track of that sum.
So what is that.
That would give us 7 8 9 10.
So we'd start with that and then we move forward 1 and we have a new sum starting from here and we add
these four together using another loop and then we compare that to the sum we had before we take the
maximum and we keep track of whatever the maximum is.
And then we would move forward from here and try with the second loop.
One two three four.
Some that together and we keep doing that and I have that solution right here.
So I'll copy it over and let's just quickly walk through it.
When we call it the very first thing we do is just make sure once again an edge case.
If the number is greater than the length of the array if we're trying to find the largest sum of three
consecutive integers and there's only two in there or zero we just return no.
Otherwise we make Max.
And I started it at negative infinity because I wanted to account for if we had an array that was all
negative numbers.
Our biggest sum would still be negative.
So starting it at zero doesn't really help us.
We're only working with positive sums.
So I did negative infinity.
That's not a huge deal.
So then what we do I should mention we take an array and a number.
This is the the number of digits we're trying to sum together.
And I create a loop so this loop starts at 0.
It goes until the end of the array will almost to the end of the array and I'll show you where it actually
goes.
What we're doing here is if we're looking at three digits in a row we're going to start here and add
these three and then add these three and keep going.
And we don't want to go all the way to the end and try and add three more or two more digits together.
We don't want to go here.
We want to stop here so that we hit the end of the array with our son.
This is the last place we could start are some that make sense if we're looking for three digits if
we're looking for five digits.
This is the last place we could start.
So that's what this is doing here.
And then we add one to I.
OK so for adding three digits together that first loop is just going to start a loop here and then we'll
go to here.
Here here here here and stop right here for our last sum then what we do is make a variable called Temp
temp it's just going to start at zero.
We have Max and so will store some Each time through.
So well together these three.
And then add together these three and compare it to max and then had to get these three.
And if it's larger than our current max We'll update Max to be temp.
So that's what I'm doing here.
So our second loop goes through J equals zero.
J is less than J plus plus.
So numb is the number of digits.
So we have I starting here.
And then the second nested loop right here that is going to look ahead and add 1:54 and then add 9 into
our temp variable as well.
That's what this is doing array of I Plus J.
So where am I.
And then we add Plus J were J has gone up by one index which is just a way of summing these three together.
Then we check if temp is greater than Max Max equals temp.
So we update Max if our temp sum is larger and the very first time through Max is negative infinity.
So no matter what we do we'll be updating Max to these three digits.
And why don't I just print out our state of do concert log temp and then also Max like this.
And when I call my code on this subway on this array I mean you can see that we start off first couple
of times.
We have 17 the first three digits some to 17 and then actually again we get 17.
Then next time through we're looking at nine two one.
So that gives us 12 so we don't update.
Max Max is still 17 but temp is 12.
Then what do these three 11 these three gives us 14.
Then we get to here and now we hit 19 and this temp is now larger than the old Max so we update Max
to be 19 and then that is our max for the rest of the array and we return 19 at the end.
So let's talk about what's not good with this solution.
So it doesn't seem like this nested loops is that big of a deal when we're talking about three items
when we're only trying to sum three things together and that's true.
But if we had a really long array which I'll type up real fast let's say we have this massive array
and we're trying to find the largest sum of 20 consecutive digits.
What would happen is that we have this first loop.
I that's going for every single item or almost every single item technically doesn't go all the way
to the end it stops what 20 digits before the end.
But we go all the way through and each time we're summing from the beginning 20 this I'm just going
to guesstimate 20 or so digits we're going to sum it together and then we're just going to move forward
one and loop 20 times again and add them together and we keep going.
And this can be really inefficient especially 20 is still a very small number in the grand scheme of
things.
If we had a huge array remember with Big-O notation we'd take things extend them way out towards infinity.
So let's say we have a million items in here and we try to find the largest sum of 10000 or 0 or even
100000 digits in a row.
It's really inefficient to continuously do this and update and now add together another 100000 digits
and then move forward one add together another hundred thousand digits.
It's just not efficient.
And a rule of thumb is you can just say it's and squared.
And each time there is nested loops.
So there are better ways of doing this which is where our sliding window approach comes in dumped at
it.
Here's a sliding window.
All right.
So here's how this one works.
I'll just copy it over.
First thing you can see though it is O of and it's linear complexity.
We only loop one time.
Technically there's two loops written down but we only go over the entire array one time.
So let me show it to you.
Here it is.
What we do is at the very beginning we sum together the first.
If we're looking for three digits in a row we sum together these three and then rather than starting
a loop here and summing together these three and then starting again and adding three together again
and keep going in that fashion like we did in the last solution here what we do is we keep a variable
that just has this total right here and all that we need to do to figure out the next.
Some of these three digits we don't have to read add 6 and 9 and 2 we can just subtract this number
and add this number or to give you a better example if we go back to this massive array.
Let's say I'm summing these digits together.
If I want to figure out this sum that comes after it starting from this to instead of this one.
Let's do something slightly more manageable.
Let's say I'm going from this one up until this for I don't have to read every number together to calculate
this.
All that I have to do is subtract the 1 and add the 5.
So that's the sliding window.
We're going to create a sum that goes from here up until.
Let's just say here and then to slide it over.
We don't recalculate everything we just subtract this number.
So we moved the window up like that.
And then we add this number.
So that's what I'm doing here.
I get rid of this massive array again and we hopped back.
We have this maxim and 10 some.
And I have my edge case.
If it's an invalid array and we're looking for a number that's too large we return all then we create
our first sum.
So let's say I pass in three.
Ok that works.
We're going to just start at the beginning and sum together the first three digits and store that in
a variable which is called Maxim and that's it.
We don't keep looping.
So we just loop three times and added together.
Then I said attempt sum equal to Max some so we just have these two variables and Max sum is what I
will return at the end.
Now what I do is I start another loop and instead of starting from zero at the beginning I start if
this is what we added together already.
I'm now going to start my loop from here.
If we're adding three digit to the time we already did this.
So now I'm going to start here.
I already have a variable with this sum which is what do we get 17.
I'm going to take that variable which is called Temp sum.
I'm going to add two and I'm going to subtract two.
Which is stupid because we get the same thing.
But then next time through say we're looking at these three.
This is our current sum which is 17 again.
What we do now is I add one and I subtract six.
And so then we're looking at 13 know 12 I'm looking at 12 and we take the maximum between maximum and
temps.
So math that Max is an easy way to do that you could also just do an if statement like we did over here.
If temp is greater than max and this just updates maxim If temp sum is larger than what is in max.
So this solution allows us to loop over the array one time.
So if we're talking about a million digits in the array we're still only going over the entire thing
once and we don't have to continuously read loop with a nested loop all that we do each time through
the loop is a single subtraction.
Technically there's a subtraction in here but we're subtracting one of the array values and adding one
array value.
And that's a sliding window.
And it's much much way way better much more efficient.
In the grand scheme of things it's.
Oh.
And instead of quadratic and square.
And I should prove that it doesn't work for you execute it we get 19.
Let me just de-clutter things.
All right.
We get 19.
And that indeed is the largest Some of these three here.
Is that right.
Yes.
It gives us 19.
Awesome.
Moving on.