Hey welcome back.
The next pattern we'll talk about is called divide and conquer.
And this is actually a real thing.
It's a documented name.
It didn't just make it up like some of the other ones.
So you can google it you can read about it in textbooks and the way I'm going to approach this video
is a little different than how I did for the previous patterns in this section.
I'm not really going to type of code because we do a lot of divide and conquer algorithms in this course.
Most of them are a little bit more complex.
So when we get to sorting algorithms we talk about many sorts I think seven different sorting algorithms
maybe six I don't remember.
And two of them at least quicksort and merge sort that we discuss are examples of divide and conquer
algorithms or we'll get to earlier on before sorting.
We get to searching algorithms we talk about binary search where that is a divide and conquer algorithm
when we get to binary search trees.
We talk about dividing conquering.
So it will come up more.
It's a little more advanced.
I don't want to try and take the entire binary search.
There's like three videos I have on it.
I don't want to try to condense that into one five minute video here so I just want to introduce the
idea of dividing and conquering.
So what we do is we take a larger set of data usually an array of string.
It could be a linked list or a tree even when we talk about those.
But let's just say in array for now and rather than starting from the left and moving all the way to
the right.
Let's say we're searching for value.
We start by dividing it into smaller pieces and then doing something to each smaller piece to determine
where to go next.
So we divide up a larger chunk of data into smaller chunks.
And this depending on the problem can be a significant helper but not always the classic example of
the one will be starting with.
Once we get to searching algorithms which is pretty soon it's called binary search or just search is
what I'm calling the function.
But technically it's called binary search.
So it accepts an array of sorted numbers it has to be sorted.
So one two three four five six.
So what we have here write a function called search that accepts a value and it returns the index where
that value is found.
So if we pass in 4 it should return 3 because 0 1 2 3.
That's where 4 was found.
If we pass in six it should return index of five.
If we pass in 11 it returns negative 1 because 11 is not found in here.
So the naive the easier approach is to start from the left and just look let's say we're looking for
11.
We start on the left and we check is this 11.
Nope.
OK Loopt the next thing is this 11.
No is this 11.
And we'll just go all the way through the array.
That would be 0 0 of.
And we go through the entire array one time and we either find it or we don't remember that it's sorted.
So that solution looks look something like this.
We have a single loop.
It's time complexities.
And this is called linear search.
We actually have a quick video on this later on binary search actually involves something a bit different.
It's a divide and conquer algorithm.
So if we hop over here and we take a look at a sorted array and we mix up some of the numbers it's not
just let's see.
All right let's say this is my array and I want to know if the number 15 is in there.
What we could do is start here with Lanier search.
Are you 15 or are you 15.
No.
And loop all the way until we find 15 here or we can use binary search where we divide the array up.
So we just pick a middle point because it's sorted.
So let's say this is our middle roughly and we check is the value we're looking for greater than 8 or
less than 8.
And because it's sorted.
This will work and the value we want is greater than 8.
We're looking for 15.
So we can ignore all of this.
Just don't even look at it because we know it's somewhere up here or it's not in the array but it's
definitely not below 8.
So then we look at this summary.
We've divided it up.
Now we got to conquer it.
So we pick a middle element and this time if we pick 15 as our middle we'll that's nice and easy.
Imagine we have a much larger array.
This is still very small in the grand scheme of things.
Let's say we had a million digits in there sorted.
If we were looking for a value that was towards the end for example and we started all the way from
here and looped all the way through there would be a lot of iterations although if we knew that the
value we were looking for was large and might be better to start from the right and moved to the left.
But either way it still is much slower than binary search where we take a middle value like this.
Let's say we're looking for our nine hundred and fifty.
We'd start here and just roughly say that middle actually don't think it's that the middle is closer
to here anyway so let's just say this is the middle is 950 greater than this.
Yes.
So ignore everything here.
Now here's our new division that we're looking at.
Let's pick something in the middle let's say it's like right here and we care about is 950 greater or
less than or equal to 9:13 it's greater.
So now we only look at this portion.
And now we pick the middle again let's say 9 16.
Well it's greater than 16.
So we look at this.
Now we pick the middle.
Well there's only two elements it will pick 917 it's greater.
So then we look at this.
That's not it.
So we know 950 is not in here and that only took four steps versus potentially starting at the beginning
looping.
It might take what it takes and steps where n is the length of the array or that's the maximum steps
to figure out something is not in here.
We have to look at every single value if we just start at the beginning anyway.
So dividing and conquering can really save a lot of time.
It can complicate your code a little bit if you do want to take a look at the solution for binary search.
Like I said we have multiple videos where we build this and we talk about how it works and we talk about
how we get to log n which if you didn't watch the log video in the big O.S. you don't remember what
log is technically log based to of and we just simplify it.
Don't worry about it we will come back to that we have a whole video on binary search or multiple videos
but I just wanted to introduce the idea of dividing and conquering taking a larger subset a larger set
of data and dividing it into smaller subsets and ignoring other ones or in the case of a merge sort
quick sort we actually will go and merge things back together sort of sew them back in one at a time
from smaller pieces.
So those algorithms definitely take some more work.
They're broken up into like three or four videos each.
They come later in the course.
But I just wanted to introduce the fact that dividing and conquering is it is a thing.
It's a really commonly used pattern.
It just happens that most of the time we use it for more complicated algorithms not for you know small
things like finding unique sequences in a string.
So usually for larger more complex things like sorting a really large list of data.
So look forward to that if that intrigued you in any way we will learn some real divide and conquer
algorithm starting with binary search and then later on merge sort and quicksort.
OK.