Everyone welcome back.
So this section is a continuation or it accompanies a previous section they're meant to go together.
So if you didn't watch that one I'd definitely recommend you start there.
I say that about pretty much everything but in particular these two go hand-in-hand.
So we're still talking about algorithms difficult problems to solve.
How do you even approach a difficult problem how do you get better at solving them whether it's in an
interview or on a side project to working on.
So we talked about sort of two different steps or two things devising a plan for solving problems before
you write a line of code.
How do you even approach a new problem something that's real.
Real head scratcher.
And then the second thing is mastering common problem solving patterns.
So the last section was devoted to that first point to make that clear.
Lovely green color.
So we're done with that.
We talked about an approach.
Now we're going to talk about some common patterns that sometimes can come in handy.
And I want to say that this section can be a bit of a letdown this material.
I've seen a lot of students sort of get disappointed because they built it up as some sort of cure all
little notebook of patterns that they need to memorize.
And then every problem they ever face every interview challenge every face.
They'll know exactly what to do and that's not the case at all.
In reality there are some common patterns that we'll discuss that do apply to multiple problems.
There are common approaches to writing code sort of archetypes or problem but that does not mean that
you cover every possible scenario on earth.
So it might help you in one out of five.
One out of 10 challenges you have to face.
But even if it's only 1 out of 10 that's still helpful and worth knowing.
So there are lots of these patterns and some of them have names that are official.
Some of them have not official but names that are recognized.
Other people like divide and conquer for example or greedy algorithms.
But some of them are things that aren't necessarily well-known names.
The concept might be well-known but if you tried to google something like frequency counter as far as
I know you'll probably find more results about a detector for counting the frequency of a sound or a
wave form or something.
That's what that is.
So some of these aren't really official terminology but all of these are different approaches different
patterns for writing code.
And when I say pattern I think that can get a little confusing.
I like to think of them as sort of programming mechanisms different pieces that you can put in or or
through a blueprint.
I think I've said that a couple of times.
So we're going to start off with a frequency counter.
We're not going to cover all of these in this one section but we're going to cover a couple of them.
And the way it will work is I'll introduce the idea explain it and then do an example where I show you
sort of a poorly written solution to a problem.
The naive approach and then the approach using the pattern that I'm introducing and then I'm going to
try and give you as many opportunities to practice on your own with exercises and solutions and that
sort of thing.
So first up we're going to talk about the frequency counter pattern that's coming up next.