Welcome back.
So the first pattern we'll take a look at.
It's not really called frequency counters.
I don't think it's actually called anything officially but that's the name I'm using because the idea
behind it is that we use an object usually in javascript to basically collect a bunch of values and
their frequencies.
So this is useful and and in algorithms and challenges when you have multiple pieces of data multiple
inputs you need to compare them to see if they consist of similar values.
If they are anagrams of one another if a value is contained inside of another value anytime you're comparing
pieces of data to inputs or more than two and frequencies of certain things occur.
And I know that sounds really wishy washy and not that useful but I'll show you a couple of examples.
So what makes this a good approach or a nice pattern is that it's usually over and time compared to
the easier solution which often involves nested loops which is going to give us of and squared quadratic
time.
So let me show you an example problem because this probably doesn't make much sense yet.
OK so here's a challenge.
Write a function called same which accepts two arrays and the function should return true if every value
in the array has its corresponding value squared.
In the second array.
So in the first array there's a bunch of values and we want to know if the second array has the exact
same values but squared but the order doesn't matter.
So it doesn't have to be identical just squared.
That could be mixed up but the frequency of Malco values must be the same.
So here's an example.
1 2 and 3 and 4 1 and 9 should return true.
So 1 squared that's in here two squared is in here four and three squared is in here nine.
But the order is mixed up and that's ok.
However something like this.
Let's look at the second one.
One two three.
Comma 1 9 is false because it doesn't include two squared which is 4 1 2 1 and 4 4 1 is also false because
the frequency needs to be the same.
So just because one squared is in disarray and two squared is in disarray doesn't mean that the frequency
is the same.
So we need to have one in here two times because we have one and another one.
We need to have four in here one time because that's what we have over here right.
Two is in here once.
So the frequency matters.
It's not just checking if there is a one.
If there is a 4 if there is a 9 it's making sure there's the correct number.
So if you want to try this go ahead and posit you don't have to try with this frequency counter pattern
which we haven't really introduced.
But if you want to you could try that or come up with a nested loops solution.
But here is what I'm I don't like calling solutions naive because they're often not that easy to come
up with even when they're labeled as naive naive.
More so just means not the best possible solution in this case.
So here's a naive solution where we use nested loops.
Technically we're only writing one loop but then we're using index of which is itself looping.
So I'm going to hop over and demonstrate how this works first just to make sure we're clear on it.
So the idea is we have two arrays.
Let's say I call it with 1 2 3.
And then my next array will look like.
Let's go with 9 4 9 1 4 like this.
OK.
And let's actually add another two in there and another four.
So this should return true because we have 1 squared.
We have two squared.
We have three squared and we have another two squared four.
OK.
So the approach here the very first thing we can do to check a nice little edge case or it's not even
an edge case just we can tell immediately if the two arrays have different lengths then we're done.
There's no way for it to be true if there's an extra value in here that isn't over here or vice versa.
So we return false.
That part's easy.
That's a nice short circuit but here what we're going to do.
Not sure right out of that return true.
We're going to loop over this first array or we could look over the second one instead.
And we're going to call index of where we pass in the square of each value.
So we loop over this array.
We start at 1 and 1 is a silly example because one square just one.
But we're going to ask what is the index of 1 squared in array 2.
So in our case if we take one what's the index of 1 squared in this array.
It's this index right here which is index of 1.
It's very confusing.
A lot of ones.
And then what we do we check if the correct index is negative one meaning it's not in there.
We return false and we're done because if we had something in here like five and we're trying to see
what index in array to contain 25 five square it while nothing does it returns negative one that means
that we have a mismatch and we're done.
But in the case of one if it is a match and it is right here then we're going to call a rate to splice
that correct index comma 1 and that effectively what that does is it removes one from this array.
So then we move on to two and then we're going to look at two squared.
What's the index of two squared in this array.
Well there's two of them just gives us the first one.
So it's going to turn this index.
So this is not true right here.
We don't return false.
We keep going.
We live another day another loop iteration and we remove it from the array using splice and then we
look at three squared and it's in there.
So we remove it then we get to the end of the array and we look at to what is the index of 2 squared.
Well that's four.
That's it.
We remove it.
We hit the end of the array and we never return to false.
So we return true.
So you don't have to do this solution with index of.
You could manually iterate over the entire array yourself which is basically what index does.
So we have one loop and then a second for loop that loops over me commands a couple times that loops
over this array and looks for one squared is just one squared is this one squared.
Yup.
OK.
Now we look at two and we loop over the entire array but we would need to still splice or we needed
a way to remember how many times we've already encountered this for so we can also apply this for this.
We need to make sure that there's the same frequency of values.
Anyway just to show you how it works as we go through.
Why not just do that log array 2.
So you can see it shrink as we go.
And then here I'll call same on those two and let's execute it.
And you can see the first time through looks like this.
And then we're looking for a one so we remove one.
And now a re two looks like this.
Next time through we're looking for two squared so we remove four and we have this.
Next time we're looking for three squared which is nine.
We remove it.
We end up with this and then next time through we look for two squared and then we're done.
We hit the end of the loop and we return true.
OK.
So that's the naive approach because it is of and squared it's quadratic time.
This index of iterating over the entire array or potentially iterating over the entire array which is
a nested loop.
So as an grows the length of our arrays this grows as does this and it's nested so that the quadratic
relationship.
We always want to try and avoid nested loops whenever possible.
So this is where the frequency counter pattern comes in.
Instead of looping over the first array and then checking for each value in a subgroup over the second
array we can loop over each array one time individually which is what I'm doing here.
So here's one loop Here's another loop.
Remember that two loops is vastly better than two nested loops.
Two separate loops.
This is going to be you know to n if and is a thousand characters or a thousand elements.
This means two thousand iterations but if we have 1000 on the outer loop and then 1000 times on the
inner loop we're looking at 1000 times 1000 which is a million compared to what we say 2000 anyway.
So I won't make you you know study this in the browser here or in the slides.
I'll show it to you and show you how it works.
But it is over.
And so it's linear time much better than if and squared.
All right.
So here it is pasted my same my same line that already says same.
Very confusing.
And let's step through the basic idea here.
So we use an object and there's actually two objects and each one is going to create.
It's going to count the frequency of individual values in the arrays.
So we'll end up with two objects at the end.
Let me just print them out so you can see that.
So that log frequency counter 1.
So that applies to our first array and then cancel that log frequency counter 2 and also start by running
this code so you can see what we end up with.
This is the so we get true.
That's our return value because these two are the same according to what we should return true.
That's what we want but if we look at these objects that were generated we end up with each object has
a value or a key like one.
And then it tells us the number of times that occurs in that list then we get to the number of times
2 is in that list to look at the number of times three is in that list 1.
Right.
If we look at this we're compiling an object that just tells us how many times each value is in that
array.
And then same thing down here except we're doing it for the second array.
So we say there is one nine there are two fours.
There is one one.
Then the magic is so constructing this only is one iteration over each array to make this.
It's not that hard but then the magic part is that we then just do one more loop and we loop over either
one.
You could do it either direction but we loop over the first object here.
And for each thing we take a look at one is.
It's a simple example I shouldn't use that one.
Let's take a look at two.
We look at two and we see that it exists or it occurs two times.
So that tells us that we need to have 4 occur two times.
And our other object or we look at three it occurs one time in our main first object the first array.
So that tells us nine needs to occur one time three squares three times three is nine in the second
array.
So that's what this logic is doing here.
So to help me illustrate this I've updated this I've added a 5 and an 11.
So these are the same length but they're not the same as far as our criteria because this 5 does not
have a 25 corresponding to it.
And we have an 11.
We don't have whatever the square root of 11 is in here.
OK.
So if I execute this now I also move my counsel that logs up so that we can see them because I had them
down here and we were returning false and we wouldn't see them printed out anyway.
What's happening now is that we're looping over this first frequency counter object.
This thing that we constructed constructing it was relatively simple.
Hopefully that part makes sense.
We start with an empty object and then we just loop over every value in the array.
Could use a for loop.
I like using a form of if you're not familiar with the four of syntax it's just a nice way of flipping
over like an array or a string.
We just make a placeholder variable like vowel and that corresponds to each element in the array.
So for each vowel in array one we're going to add one to the frequency counter if it's already in there
or we're going to initialize it to 1.
So we end up with just this little object that tells us how many times each thing each element occurs
in that list.
Then we loop over this first one and we're going to look at each key.
So we're going to look at one which one is boring so I'm going to skip it.
We're going to look at two and we'd check is two squared.
That's what this is.
Is that a key in frequency count or two.
So two squared is four.
So is there any four in our second object and there is.
So this part doesn't return false.
Then we check OK.
Do the values correspond.
If there were two twos there needs to be two force.
And if there's not if there's a mismatch we return false.
So it's not just a matter of checking if there is a 4.
We need to make sure there are two fours as we discussed then we keep going you know we hit three and
we check is nine in the second object in Adis and do the values match one matches one then we get to
five.
Is there five squared which is 25.
Is there a 25.
No.
So we return false.
So hopefully you can see why this is better.
At least in terms of big-O complexity as we increase the size of these arrays we're talking about how
many loops here three loops over the entire size of the array whatever the largest array is.
Let's just say I mean they need to be the same size in order for us to even make it to this point because
if they are mismatched we quit right here.
So our two arrays have to be the same size.
Let's say a thousand like 30 talked about the thousand elements we have roughly 3000 iterations Here's
a thousand.
Here's 1000.
And here's a thousand more.
And remember that it's very it's very easy it's quick to access data inside of an object.
Does it matter how many things are in there.
It's just the way that objects work we actually talk more about this later in the course.
So this is three and roughly where it's the length of the arrays and we simplify that.
Just two of end complexity.
Compare that to our naive approach where we have squared.
So if we're talking about you know a thousand a length of 1000 for each array that's a million iterations.
If we have a nested loop Yes.
Again we're using index of.
But we're talking about a nested loop that's the index of it's doing.
It's just a shortcut so we don't have to type it all out inside of a loop that roughly a million operations
worst case.
So this is a lot lot worse.
Why don't you put it that way.
So the idea behind the frequency counter usually use an object and you use that object to construct
a profile sort of a way of breaking down the contents of an array or a string.
Usually some sort of linear structure like an array or a string and then you're able to quickly compare
that breakdown to how another object looks.
That was constructed from a string or an array.
So we had two arrays.
We break them down into objects that sort of classify what's in those arrays and then we can compare
those objects and this allows us to improve our code significantly.
So I'm going to show you another example coming up that has to do with anagrams.
Hopefully it will help cement how this works and then we'll move on to another pattern.