All right.
So here's my solution for anagrams.
Again there's many ways of doing it but the way that I wanted you to try was to solve it with a frequency
counter use an object construct it using a loop and then use a second loop that's not nested.
So we still maintain our big-O of of and time complexity.
Here's my version.
So it's called valid and Graham and Graham and it takes two arguments first and second if I called them
and the very first thing I did just like before if the length of those two strings is different if they
don't match then immediately we can throw it out.
There's no way for it to be true.
There's no possible anagram of two strings that are different like they have to be the same.
So we return false right away.
Then what I did was made an object called look up you could call this frequency counter or just object
O.B. J.
I wouldn't call it object Sabet idea but obey is OK.
So look up and I'm going to loop through the first string right here and I'm going to create an object
that is a breakdown of the first string.
So if I called valid Let's just grab one of these examples like this one right here.
So this should return true and the first thing that I'm going to do I'll just model this object here.
We're going to go through we loop over it.
So I starts at 0 as less and first at length.
Plus plus it's going to loop over this first string which is called first and I'm going to take the
first character the very first time through using a variable called Letter.
Just to make my code a little cleaner instead of writing first I all over the place.
So this letter's going to start at A and I'm going to check if my look up object already has a in it
and it's empty right now.
So it doesn't.
So this line is going to either set it equal to 1 or we're going to add one.
If it's already initialized to a value.
So in our case there is no A in our object.
If this is our object.
So we add we initialize it to 1.
This is not true.
It returns falsie because there's nothing in there.
And so we set it to 1.
So we set a equal to 1 then we go through for an and we set an equal to 1.
Right then we get to you again this time we look up a well it's already in there.
So this time this part runs we add one look up of a plus equals one.
So he said it to two.
OK.
So we construct the entire object first and just so you can see what that looks like at the end of that
log.
Look up right here and run my code.
This is what we start off with.
So I constructed this look up and now we're going to actually use it.
So we're now going to loop over the second string and we're going to compare each character to our look
up object that we created based off of the first string.
And what we'll do is because you know we have multiple like a is in here twice or three times so we
can't just check in here.
We need to make sure A's in there exactly the number of times and they're equivalent.
So what we'll do is subtract one from a.
So if we start it and we're going to find and and then we'll subtract 1 percent and set it to zero.
If we find a we're going to go to AA and subtract 1.
Now we need to find two more A's.
And we keep going.
So just to show you that we loop over the second string we make a placeholder variable called letter
that is just going to store the individual letter.
And at the beginning and the first thing we do if we can't look up that letter.
Meaning it's not in there like if we were looking for an S and there's no s in here as a key then we
return False we're done.
Otherwise we subtract 1.
So we go through and we look for and.
All right.
Well said to one well now we subtract one and it's set to zero.
And so now we go through again and we're looking at a.
So we find a way to set it to two and then we move on to G.
We set G to zero.
We subtract 1 and we go to egg then we subtract 1 and we go to our.
We subtract 1 goes to zero and we go to a we subtract 1 again.
So it goes to zero and then we go to M and we subtract 1 and we're done.
And so we don't have to do any check at the end we don't have to see is everything zero or anything
like that.
Let's say somehow would be an example if we had some random letter here like an S like this.
So we'd have to set to 1 and we have another m.
So we just did this M and we crossed it off and set it to zero.
Then we get to an M again.
Well this time we look up a letter and it's going to give us what is the value for m is zero because
zero is falsie.
If we run not look up of letter not zero.
That means this is true.
So we will return false.
So if we ever encounter zero that means that there is a problem because we've exhausted basically what
this represents or the characters that we've gone through in our first thing.
So all we have left is an essay.
There has to be one s over here in order for there to be a match.
And if instead we get to zero.
That means that we're working on a character in the second string that didn't exist in the first string.
So it's a nice simple solution I think.
I kind of like it I think it's kind of cute.
It involves you know just two simple loops does not involve nested loops which you could do easily.
We could start with an A here and loop over the string and then look for it in the second string.
And we could start and end and look for an end in the second string and that would involve nested loops.
And of course we would also have to pay attention to making sure that we were crossing things off or
removing things as we went.
So that we were not you know getting a false positive.
Hopefully you can see how it is a helpful pattern in this scenario.
Any time you have multiple pieces of data and you need to compare them in particular if we need to see
if they consist of the same individual pieces whether it's anagrams or you're trying to see if you know
if one array is equal to another array squared each individual piece or what else have I seen.
If you need to tell if numbers consist of the same digits just in a different order.
There's a lot of applications for this.
Anyway moving on to our next pattern.