Everyone will come back.
This is going to be a really quick section.
I just want to take what we just learned talking about Big-O notation.
Time and space complexity analyzing code performance take that content and apply it to the stuff we
already know.
So before we get to the advanced algorithms and sorting and crazy data structures let's just talk about
what we get for free.
The basics in javascript so things like arrays and objects built in methods loops.
How do they perform.
What are the easy things the fast things we can do to an array.
What's the method that might be slower than you would expect.
That's what we're going to talk about and it's going to be really quick.
Again I'm not going to teach these things from scratch not showing how an array works or what it is.
We're just going to talk about how it performs.
So first our objectives understand how objects and arrays work through the lens of big-O.
So various operations.
Is there a fast way to insert to an array or slow way that sort of thing.
Explain why up spoiler explain why adding elements to the beginning of an array is costly gave it away
and we'll talk about why that is and how it works and if there are alternatives or if there's a better
way of inserting and then we'll compare and contrast the runtime for arrays and objects but also they're
built in methods.
There's a lot of these methods we get for free.
Like the built in javascript sort for an array for each object that keys object has own property.
All that stuff we're going to discuss but it's going to be quick and this isn't I should sit out and
say this isn't a something you need to memorize it's not something that you know you need to refer to
the slides.
I just want to give you a chance to take what we've learned about big-O and apply it to something tangible.
Before we dive into these crazier algorithms.
All right.
So let's start first we're going to discuss objects.
It will be nice and quick.
So don't go anywhere.
I'll see in the next video.