All right welcome back.
So let's begin by talking about objects talking about them through the lens of Big O and performance.
Hopefully you're familiar with them.
If not I don't have time right now to teach them but I may or may not have some courses on them.
So they are unordered data structures and everything is stored in key value pairs.
For example like this object literal I'm storing in a variable called instructor.
We've got three key value pairs are so objects work well when you don't need order of course.
And also when you want fast access and insertion and removal so no order but everything else.
Almost everything else is very quick.
And when we say quick I'm talking about constant time for insertion removal and accessing data.
So objects are very fast.
I mean that's the fastest we can go.
Constant time will come back to searching in a moment.
We up over here.
Here's the same exact object we.
Later in the course have a section called hash maps where we actually learn a data structure that explains
how objects work behind the scenes how things are actually stored.
So what happens when when we say instructor should have first name set to Kelly what does javascript
actually do.
A computer can't necessarily just access a place in memory called first name.
So there are some additional steps involved along the way.
There's something called hashing we talk about it later in the course but all that you need to know
is that javascript is able to add something into an object store a new piece of information in constant
time.
It's also able to retrieve something in constant time and you can also update something in constant
time which is really the same as retrieving it.
You're just changing it.
Same with removal.
So it's quick it's fast.
For all the basic operations there is no order so there's no beginning of the object there's no end
so it doesn't matter where you insert because there is no where.
That's a bad way of putting it but you can't insert at the beginning or in the middle or the end of
the object there's no repercussions.
You just add in using a key.
All right so insertion removal and access are all constant time very quick if you want to learn more.
Remember there's a section on hash tables and hash maps where we go into that and you'll understand
hopefully understand how it is cost and time searching however is o of and it's linear time.
And when we say searching it doesn't mean looking for a key.
For example first name because as we've already seen accessing information with a key is constant time.
What I'm talking about is checking to see if a given piece of information is in a value somewhere.
If it's on this side of the colon we have no easy way of doing that.
We would potentially have to check every single item every property.
So that's what this little black box is signifying green box.
I guess if we wanted to know is true stored in our object somewhere we'd have to check first name what's
your value and then we look at it.
It's Kelly All right.
That sounded instructor What's your value.
True.
All right.
So there is true in here but potentially you know as the number of properties in there grows and grows
so does the amount of time it takes to do that.
So now let's go on to some of the methods that objects come with things like keys values and entries.
Those three are all.
And so if we have bovver back to Chrome and we take a look at key states object keys and then we pass
in the object.
So if we do it for instr. we get this array with the keys.
This is all of time because as the number of items in there gross we're going to have to visit every
single thing once and add it to this array.
We're not going to put the source is going to do the code.
Same thing with values hopefully that makes sense if we have a hundred elements or a hundred properties
in our object there's 100 things 100 operations we need to do.
There's usually more.
But it runs roughly in line with and it might be two and it might be 15 but that still simplifies to
0 7 and then that also is the same for entries.
Right.
And technically entries is a little more work potentially having to compile the key and the value.
But it all just simplifies to over and at the end of the day remember.
Okay.
So lastly we've got has owned property and has own property is a little different repasts and a property
like first name and it just tells us it has first name it doesn't have a first name and this is constant
time and hopefully that makes sense why it's constant time.
If we're able to access information in constant time if we have the key first name we want the value.
We should also be able to check if a key exists in pretty much the exact same time.
So in summation objects are really quick for pretty much everything.
However there's no order and we'll see coming up with arrays.
Arrays can be pretty fast for a lot of things but the order also can slow them down depending on what
we're doing.
So objects are basic.
They work very well in a lot of situations.
Key value pairs all the operations inserting accessing updating removing all constant and time searching
is pretty rare but it is over and it grows and grows.
It's linear and then the methods like keys and values and entries where we're creating an array based
off of the data inside the object file as the object grows so does the number of operations the amount
of time it takes to compile those.
So those are of it.
OK so the next array is a little more interesting because there's some variation there's some nuance
to it that's coming up.