All right.
Welcome back.
Let's talk about a raise through the lens of big-O performance and how do they compare two objects.
Quick side note if you've never seen a raise are not familiar with them.
Definitely go learn about them first.
This is not I'm not teaching them here we're just talking about them and how they perform.
All right.
So the big selling point of arrays of course is that they are ordered there is an intrinsic ordering
to the data unlike an object where things just float around in a gelatinous mass.
And that's often very useful if we need order but it can come at a cost for some of the operations.
Anyway here are two different arrays of course you can store whatever you want and there are different
types of data.
Mix it up and each element has an index a numeric value that corresponds to it.
So this is the zeroth item the first and the second item.
And in general arrays you use when you need order.
If you don't need order then you probably don't want to use an array if you're just trying to store
random data together.
You could still use an array but if you're really trying to optimize for performance there are other
options.
And even if you do need order we're going to see some other structures coming up like a singly linked
list and a doubly linked list that still encode order.
There is still a linear.
It's a list structure where each element is in a particular spot and they're all connected in an order.
But they sometimes can perform better than arrays depending on what you need.
So arrays are not the only order data structure on Earth.
They're just the only one that we get for free in javascript anyway link this comes later.
So when you need an order you can use an array of course but often that can come at a cost depending
on what you're trying to do especially around insertion and removal it can complicate things.
So accessing data in an array is always very quick.
You can see here Access is 0 1 just the exact same as we talked about with an object.
When I say access what I mean is if we have this array with three items called names if I ask for names
of zero I remember that once too easy.
It's the first one.
Let's say I ask for names of two.
It's constant time to give me Andrea.
So a misconception that I've seen a lot of students have when you have a 10000 element array and you
ask for the nine thousandth element let's say Javascript isn't going through every single element in
counting all the way up to 9000 and accessing every element and then getting to the one you need and
giving it to you.
You can think of.
There's a direct shortcut to each element.
If you have a number if you have an index and the array goes that far of course that's the one condition.
It's a valid index.
You can jump immediately to the data.
So it doesn't matter how long the array is.
It doesn't matter if you're looking at the last item the middle item or the first item.
It's constant time.
OK.
So now that that's out of the way let's talk about insertion and removal.
So it really depends on where we're inserting.
Let's start with insertion and it has to do with this order as I've mentioned.
Each element has an index that corresponds to it.
And if I want to add something in but say I want to add in the name Raj.
Well if I add it to the very end like right here by pushing onto this array that is constant time is
0 0 1 and that's because there's really nothing.
There's nothing difficult about that.
We can add to the end of the array and we give it a new index.
It's sort of like adding into an object it's constant time it's super simple.
It doesn't require much work.
The problem comes when we try to insert at the beginning of an array.
And the reason for that has to do with these indices.
If I tried to insert rush here you can already kind of see what happens.
Our indices are totally messed up.
Michael is no longer element 0.
Melissa is not element 1.
Andrea it's not element 2.
So we have to re-index every single element in the array.
And this is simple for a four element array.
But if we're talking about thousands and thousands of elements re-indexing every single one is not a
trivial task.
So if we were inserting at the beginning of an array we're talking about 0 of end time because we have
to do something once roughly once for every single element.
Now that doesn't mean that it's exactly one operation for each element remember.
And it could be of 10 and 0 of 2 and 0.5 and it's just that the amount of time it takes roughly grows
in proportion with the size of the array.
And all right so inserting in the beginning is problematic.
The same goes for removing from the beginning.
So if we do have Raaj at the beginning let's say this is our set up.
Now this is so annoying having to type all of this like this if we remove Raj like this.
Everything's wrong.
Right.
We have to re-index again just the other direction we need to set Michael index or his index is one
Malissa goes down.
Sorry 0.
Melissa goes to one Andre goes to two.
So you can see how this becomes difficult.
Adding and removing from the beginning of an array is best to avoid if you can.
But often it's meaningful to add to the beginning of an array.
If you're trying to put something at the beginning of an order for example you may need to say I'm not
saying you should avoid it at all costs.
It's just good to be aware that it's not as efficient as adding in removing at the end so push and pop
always faster than shift in unshipped.
Unless of course it's an empty array in which case adding to the beginning or end is the same thing.
All right.
So we talked about insertion and removal.
It depends on where we're inserting always inserting removing from the beginning is worse than adding
to the end and removing from the end.
Accessing is fast no matter where.
If we're talking about 10000 elements accessing the middle element is just as fast as accessing the
second element and then searching the fastest we can do of is oh.
We'll discuss this in the searching section.
All write our own basic javascript search if we're talking about an unsorted array where there's no
order to the data.
If I wanted to know if I had say another ten thousand names in here and I wanted to know if Robbie was
in there we have to check potentially every single element.
So as the number of items grows in that array so does the time potentially that it takes to find that
item.
So search grows 7 it's linear.
And we spend a lot more time talking about search and potential optimizations you can make specifically
when your data is sorted but that comes up later.
All right so next we'll talk about some builtin Array methods and their performance and then we're pretty
much done.