Hey welcome back.
This is part two of the simple five step program to changing your life and realizing your dreams.
As long as your dreams have to do with solving problems that doesn't include family problems medical
problems personal problems problems with their pets peeing on your brand new furniture.
It only applies to code programming challenges.
Unfortunately and I've been viewing this through the lens of interviews but it really does apply to
any sort of code challenge that you're trying to solve on your own.
OK so step one was understand the problem.
Step two after you've done that explore concrete examples.
So we're back in our cinder block cell.
Our interviewer has asked us a question.
We have a moment of panic.
We start by understanding the question trying to figure out make sure we understand the inputs the outputs
all that stuff we talked about.
The very next thing that I do and I recommend all students all my students do and we talked about interview
prep is come up with concrete examples.
This is tied very closely to understanding the problem.
So coming up with examples can help you.
I just said this cheese can help you understand the problem better.
Examples also provide the checks so that your eventual solution if once you have a solution you can
tell if it works how it should.
Because you know at that point you already have the examples you know the inputs and outputs that you
should get.
So if you have those examples you can check your work but also you can learn more information by doing
these examples.
And this applies on a larger scale things like user stories.
These are examples that you're not familiar with user stories.
It doesn't matter that much but if you're working on a product like an Instagram when they're solving
a challenge they're building a new feature.
You bet that they start with user stories at some point they do which is basically given an input output
except the input is you know a user action.
What should happen after that.
Or unit tests on a smaller scale but still you know bigger context than an interview unit tests are
used all the time to help lay out you know how something should work for a smaller feature.
OK.
So here are the steps that I take around exploring concrete examples.
So you're faced with a problem.
The first thing that I do is start with simple examples and I literally if if I'm in an interview or
if my students are in a mock interview I tell them.
All right.
You've restated you've restated the problem already you understand it.
Now write down two or three simple examples with an input and then the output.
And I really actually like to write this down so I have it and I can look back at it.
So simple examples the ones that should make you know the easiest use cases then progress to more complex
examples.
And then what about edge cases explore examples with empty inputs that will often give you some insight
into how the problem should work especially in an interview setting.
Explore examples with invalid inputs.
So this is more useful I'd say in the real world.
What happens if a user enters something that is invalid.
Right.
We have to think about this all the time.
So let's explore this with a concrete problem.
So our interviewer asks.
Write a function which takes in a string and returns count of each character in the string.
It's a relatively straightforward problem but there are many questions many examples that we could try
out and use to learn about the problem.
OK.
So someone just asked me to solve this problem.
I'm in an interview I want to check that I understand it first.
So I try and restate the problem do all this stuff from the last video then I like to come up with a
couple simple examples to make sure I understand it.
So let's say our function is called Char count.
I would literally write this out.
So char count like AAA with four days.
Well that should return something that looks like this.
I would assume return's counts of each character in the string this is we've already gathered that it
needs to return an object.
Let's say instead of an array or some other data structure.
So I would try this you know and that's how it should work I guess chart count of Hello should return
something like this.
But already there's a question that I have which is should it just return the letters that are in there.
What about the letters that aren't there.
Do we want to include you know B zero and C is zero.
Because if we did that it might make our code a lot easier if every letter was already in there set
to 0.
Then it makes it simpler as we go.
We don't have to add in a or b if it's already in there.
We just have to increment it.
So that's a question that I would try and clarify.
So the next step was progress to more complex examples.
So what about something like this if somebody did something like my phone number is blah blah blah and
that's not a valid phone number as far as I know.
So if this was an input what would we expect to return.
Do we want to account for spaces.
That's an important one.
What about other characters dollar signs underscores numbers that's a big one.
Are we going to put numbers in there and an even more important one that definitely would come up.
What about this.
Hello.
Hi.
Are there you know how do we store an upper case and lower case H.
Do we ignore casing How should this work should or object have h uppercase one h lowercase one or just
h two.
So these are more complex inputs and examples that it would really help to understand and it would help
us to simplify the problem or understand it better by asking these sort of questions.
These examples are really just another form of understanding the problem better before we tackle it.
So it ties in to the previous video a lot.
Understanding the question.
Next up explore examples with empty inputs.
So what if you know somebody does char count and doesn't pass anything in like this or an empty string.
What do we want to return to we want to return an empty object at the end.
Do we want to return.
No.
Or false or undefined or maybe an error.
And that's tied to exploring examples with invalid inputs.
So what if somebody passes in something that isn't a string they pass in a number where they pass in
an object or they pass in no.
There's all sorts of these edge cases.
And understanding these edge cases.
In an interview setting.
Often it's not that important usually but it can be really important in the real world to help you build
a more robust solution something that is more foolproof.
So it's still important to keep that in mind.
And sometimes it can give you a bit of insight into how the problem works or how you should solve it.