A welcome back.
So I said at the very beginning of the course we had a little math the whole sections pretty mathy.
But this last video in particular is condensed with some math we're talking about logarithms.
As you can see whether you learn about logarithms at one point or you learn about logarithms at one
point and forgot it all or you never learned about it.
I'm going to try and just make it pretty simple and also quick because it doesn't actually matter that
we're masters with logarithms.
The reason I'm even showing it to you.
Guess that's where I should start.
Is that some algorithms that we'll see have a big.
That isn't simple it isn't big of one or of and nerve and squared.
These are very common complexities and we've seen them and I think they're pretty easy to comprehend.
Hopefully but there are some big old expressions that involve some more difficult math or less common
expressions.
And something that comes up more than I personally would like our logarithms.
So that's why I'm showing it to you.
We will have and I'll show you in a bit.
Some algorithms in this course where their time complexity instead of being of end might be 0 of log
n..
So what's let's start with what's Lague what's logarithm.
So put simply a logarithm is the inverse of exponentiation.
So just like division and multiplication are a pair logarithms and exponent exponentiation are a pair.
So here's what you might see.
You would read this as log base two of eight equals three.
And what we're really asking or calculating here is two to what power equals eight.
So if we take two and we raise it to some power what power will give us eight.
Two times two times to give us eight.
So the answer is three.
So two cube equals eight.
Here's just that same thing written down again log.
Base 2 of a value equals the exponent.
You can switch it around and say two to the exponent equals value.
Just like if we had one divided by two equals 0.5 you could switch that around and say that two times
point five equals one.
It can move things around.
They are the inverse exponentiation and logarithms.
Now logarithms aren't always working with base 2.
You could have logged three of something three to what power gives us 8 or Lague 5 or 10.
The most common ones though are the binary logarithm which is log 2.
So two to what power.
Then there's also the base 10.
So 10 to what power gives us and some answer.
Then there's also log E which not going to go into but probably should have said that anyway.
There's there's a third very common out for them.
However for what we're concerned about we care about the big picture and we're going to get the two.
We're just going to say log because first of all it's annoying to write all this.
This is subscripted I think it's subscript not superscript to knowing to format this but also it doesn't
really matter at the end of the day because if we're comparing the graph of a constant time and a quadratic
time and log n time it doesn't really matter if it's log based to log base 3 log base 10 it's going
to be the general trend that we care about.
But just so that we're clear this isn't actually a mathematical operation on its own.
You can't just take the log of a number you need to have a base.
So we need to say log to log 10.
But in the slides and in literature that sounds stupid in literature in things that you'll see online
around Big-O notation the shorthand is just log if you want a rule of thumb just a calculated roughly
the binary logarithm of a number roughly measures the number of times you can divide that number by
two before you get a value that's less than or equal to 1.
So if we have 8 we're going to divide it by two and it's still greater than 1.
So we're going to divide by 2 again it's still greater than 1 2 but by 2 again.
Now we hit 1.
So that means 3.
We divided three times so the answer is three.
Twenty five however doesn't go cleanly.
There's no way of dividing it by two evenly.
So we divide by two and by two again and again and again and then we're finally below 1.
So this tells us that it's one two three four.
Somewhere between four and five.
And the answer is four point six four.
So the actual calculations are not that important.
What matters here is if we take a look at it on a chart.
So logarithmic time complexity is great if you have an algorithm with log n time complexity.
I'll show you which one it is here.
Here we have Consta time in red and then right above that an orange we have video of log and you can
see that up front it's a little steeper but then it really tails off and is very gradual.
And this is great if you have an algorithm log in time from Potsie.
Fantastic.
So that's why I'm showing it to you because it compares very favorably to things like event.
There's another common one we'll see.
And.
I'm not going to go into examples just yet but both of them involve logs so I figured I should show
you.
It's not as good but it's still better than something like and squared the quadratic time complexity.
So really the point at the end of the section even if you're stuck on some of the math what I hope we
have is that later in the course I'll show you two algorithms.
I want to be able to point to one and say this one has a log and time complexity.
This other one has 0 of and time complexity.
And I hope that you can look at this chart and understand that.
Cool.
The first one is better.
It's at least more efficient it's faster because Lagann is much better than 0 7.
The larger and gets doesn't grow that much.
The runtime with long end but it grows a lot in proportion with an 11.
OK.
So that's kind of that's why I'm introducing it here.
We have a bigger picture of these are the most common big-O expressions.
Like I said the math we don't have to worry about too much but I just want you to know what a log is.
Let's talk about where this will come up.
So certain searching algorithms do have logarithmic time complexity and we will see those as we go in
the progress of the Course also efficient sorting algorithms involve logs.
So not all soring algorithms but some of the more efficient ones do.
So we'll see that as well.
And then finally recursion another topic.
So basically there's three reasons here none of which we've actually discussed.
So this might not make a lot of sense I'm basically saying in the future we're going to see it at this
place this place and this place searching algorithms efficient sorting and recursion and that has to
do with space complexity with recursion not time.
So hopefully these will make more sense once we get there.
Really again it comes down to just having this nice picture here I want to see if I was teaching this
in a classroom and have this up on the wall at all times like laminated printed out and I'd have a long
stick and I'd whack it on the wall and point it for every algorithm point at one of those lines and
I'm going to try and kind of do the same virtual thing in this course on my.
OK.
So let's do a quick recap.
We covered a lot to analyze performance of an algorithm.
We use Big-O notation.
It has to do with big high level big picture trend as the size of an input.
Gross We want to know how the runtime changes or how the space complexity changes.
So Big O can give us a high level understanding of time or space complexity.
It doesn't care about precision just general trends.
Time-Space complexity as measured by big-O depends only on the algorithm not on the hardware.
So yes the actual time it might take to run one algorithm on my computer compared to some supercomputer
will definitely be different.
But the general trend won't be big O is basically measuring the number of operations that happen whether
an operation takes 10 milliseconds in my computer or one millisecond on another computer which is pretty
slow anyway.
But you that and Big-O notation is everywhere so we're going to get a lot of practice and that's why
it's coming first in this course.
I feel kind of bad about it.
Like I've said before because it's not the most welcoming topic and it's kind of a rude awakening but
it gives us a context to discuss things.
I mean to go back to that terrible analogy of the Richter scale with earthquakes.
It gives us a way of discussing how earthquakes compare their magnitudes to same idea we can compare
algorithms now and say oh this one is great.
This one is terrible because it's space complexity is X or it's time complexity is x.
Anyway let's let's call it a day here.
Let's stop now.
And we'll see you in the next section.