All right.
So we finally actually introduced the term big-O we've basically been talking about we go without actually
saying the term Big-O notation.
So let's actually let's review it now.
So big-O is just a way of formalized fuzzy counting.
It allows us to talk in a very formal way about how the runtime of an algorithm grows as the inputs
grow.
That's it.
It's a way of describing the relationship between the input to a function or as it grows and how that
changes the runtime of that function.
The relationship between the input size and then the time relative to that input.
So we don't care about the other details only the broad trends.
So we've already been talking about broad trends we talked about OK's and grows here.
And this first solution down here it doesn't matter.
It doesn't impact the time that it takes but in our second solution which is confusingly called add
up to first and grows down here the runtime also grows in proportion.
Basic roughly in a linear one to one pattern with that.
So that is big so what we've been talking about we just haven't actually been using the correct label.
So here's a bit of scary text.
We say that an algorithm of or is Big O of f then if the number of simple operations the computer has
to do is eventually less than a constant time f event and increases it's a bunch of jibberish really
what it's saying though is that there's a bunch of these.
I'm just going to put them on here for now.
There's a bunch of options.
If you haven't seen this notation by the way this just means a function with an input of N and then
the output.
So we're describing the relationship between the input and then the runtime.
So it could be linear meaning that as and scales the input the runtime scales as well which we've already
seen.
It could be something different could be quadratic whereas and gross the run time square is related
to the Square event.
Or it could be constant which you've already seen as well as and grows.
It doesn't really have an impact because runtime is always constant which we simplify down to one or
it could be something entirely different.
We'll get to some of these other options later on in the course and later in the section you can always
come back and just think about it as well and grows as an input grows.
What is this chart going to look like.
Is it going to grow roughly proportionately within.
Is it going to be constant.
If we had a square it would be a lot steeper than this.
One thing I want to highlight is that when we talk about big oh we're talking about the worst case scenario.
So we're talking about basically the upper bound for runtime.
So let's revisit our examples from earlier.
This first add up to where we only had three operations and it's constant It's always three operations.
So the line we looked at was this one down here that roughly is constant.
Remember in the real world it's not up.
It goes up and down a little bit.
Runtime does vary but overall the trend is that it's flawed.
So we could say that this has a big one and this is the notation that we'll see.
So when you see a big go and then in parentheses you see one or you see end or end squared or and log
and or log in things we haven't gotten to that is telling us that as and grows as the input to this
function grows in this case it has no change it's not reflected in the runtime.
But if we take a look at this one add up to and same name.
This was the one that had a bunch of operations that are happening where we said that it grows and grows
the runtime grows basically in a 1 to 1 ratio the number of operations is eventually bounded by a multiple
of.
And it doesn't actually matter if it's 1 and or five 10 or 15 because at the end of the day we simplify
it down just to end.
And we're going to talk about the rules for simplifying these expressions.
But basically we're concerned with just the order of magnitude.
So we don't care if it's 5 10 or just plain old.
And it's the same when are charting in on a massive chart and we're zooming way out and we're just carrying
a carrying in a fuzzy way.
I guess is what you would say.
So here's another example we haven't seen.
It's called Count up and down and all that it does is copied over.
I don't actually have a what do you call it the snippet for it but let's just plug in 10 Okay.
So our output is going up 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 at the top going down 9 8 seven six five four three two
one zero back down.
All right so if you're trying to figure out the big 0 for this function we'd start by saying.
All right.
So here as n grows we have roughly an operation to have a loop.
So there's big of and here because this as Ed grows this loop grows same thing down here and grows this
loop grows.
It's just doing the same thing in the other order going back down.
So you might think the big n it's to N.
But remember that we don't care about that we care about the big picture.
So we simplify it to big.
And so if we go back to our performance tracker I do have count up and down added in here so it's plotted
out with one hundred one thousand ten thousand and you'll see I think that's a small do it's taking
a while the next one will take forever.
There we go.
And you can see there we get that chart that we discussed.
This is the big picture of anything that has big O of N and we have one more example.
This one's different.
We haven't seen this yet.
So we have a nested loop.
So what it does it is called Print all pairs.
And if I plug in five it's going to print every pair of the numbers 0 to 5 0 0 0 0 1 0 2 all the way
up to 5 5.
And I don't I won't show the example but you can trust me that's what it does.
And there's two loops.
And just like we discussed with the loop this loop is based off of and this first one.
So that's big-O of N.
Right.
And gross This is going to be any number of operations roughly.
But then we have a nested loop which is also the same thing.
O of N which just means that as and grows this loop the number time it run a number of times it runs
grows as well.
But this is not oh of to N which simplifies to of N because it's nested.
And that gives us something else and over an operation instead of an event operation is 0 0 of and squared.
So what this means is that as n grows the runtime roughly grows at the rate of end squared.
So that's a pretty significant difference.
And if we plot it out which we will in just a second you'll see that.
But hopefully that makes sense and I pause over that makes sense of why there is such a difference.
Because if we step through this if and is let's just think about the number of pairs if any is.
We have the pairs 0 0 0 1.
Then we have to pair 1 0 and 1 1 to those four pairs.
But if we increase and to three all of a sudden we have nine pairs.
I won't go through them all but it increases very quickly if we increase to four.
We've got 16 pairs.
So I said I wouldn't do this but I added it into my console print all pairs.
If we do too.
There you go we get the four pairs for three.
We get a lot more 9.
Now if we go here and plot this print all pairs I mean you start small and do 10 1.
I'm not even going to go to 100 right away let's do 50 now let's do one hundred.
Two hundred and twenty hundred and fifty.
All right so you can see what we're working with here.
And try 200.
Might take a little while.
OK I'll leave it at this.
This is a different overall trend a fuzzy version of the chart.
We're not looking at a linear thing whereas as gross the runtime is roughly proportionate it's proportionate
to and squared so as and grows larger the runtime grows even larger it grows and times and larger roughly.
And just to show you this if I increase this to 300 it's going to take a lot lot longer and I think
I was playing around a 500 earlier and that was about as much as my computer browser wanted to do at
the time.
Oh dear.
OK.
There you go.
You can see that this is what used to look very steep.
Now that we've added it in five hundred It doesn't look so bad.
And now it looks really steep which is the exponential curve.
Remember that it's just a generalized way for talking about how efficient an algorithm is as an input
and grows.
How does that change to reflect in the runtime.
So we've seen a couple of options.
We saw up to first which was basically big-O of n as and grew the output the runtime grew relative to
end.
Then we had up to second add up second which was constant.
It always took roughly the same amount of time than we had count up and down where it was the same as
add up to first if and gross if it triples than our runtime is roughly going to triple.
And then finally we saw print all pairs which was our first quadratic and 0 of end squared where as
an increases the runtime increases roughly at a rate of end squared.
So I'm hoping I didn't lose you there if I did.
Well we have some exercises after this.
Hopefully it will help out a little bit.
I recommend that you play around with that tool but be careful because if you play in Super large numbers
it will take forever and or crush your browser window and you'll have to quit that window just have
a word of warning.