All right welcome back.
So now we shift gears a little bit and we're going to talk about something called space complexity.
Everything we've talked about so far we've been worrying about time about how fast algorithms run with
the runtime.
That's called time complexity.
We've been analyzing the runtime of an algorithm as the size that the input increases.
Now let's talk about what happens to the space that an algorithm takes up as the size of the input increases.
We can still use Big-O notation for the same thing use the same formal syntax for describing what happened.
But now we're going to focus on space.
The amount of memory that's taken up so there's some basic things we have to get out of the way.
One is that obviously as an grows if we're approaching infinity the size of the input itself which is
and is going to grow.
So we're going to ignore that part.
You might hear the term auxilary space complexity if you do some research.
If you read Wikipedia or something that refers to the space required by the algorithm only not including
the space taken up by the inputs.
That's what we're going to talk about.
We care about the algorithm itself because our end is growing.
That's the big end and big.
Oh that's good.
That's kind of the point we're going to say that as and grows we assume that the input end is going
to grow.
So let's not care about that space let's care about what repercussions that has inside the algorithm.
So unless otherwise noted when we talk about space complexity technically we're talking about auxilary
space complexity.
Hopefully it's not too scary but basically it just means we're focusing on what happens inside the algorithm.
So some basic rules of thumb.
The first is that most primitive things like booleans numbers undefined null and Javascript are constant
space so it doesn't matter what the size of the input is.
If the number is 1 or the number is 1000 we can consider it constant space doesn't matter for a boolean
is true or false takes up the same amount of space.
Strings are a bit different because they require 0 of space so if and is the length the string.
If we have you know the input grows to a thousand characters Well that's actually that's a bad example
if it goes to 50 characters the string takes up 50 times more space than a single character string.
Same thing with reference types arrays and objects.
Generally we're talking about O event where and it's the length of the array or the number of keys for
an object.
It's not really a length technically but so if and is if the length of an array is forwarder compared
to another one that is two it takes up twice as much space as the shorter array.
So let's take a look at an example.
So here we're focusing on not time complexity we're focusing on space complexity.
So this function called some it takes an array and it just sums all the items in the array.
So we have a variable total start to 0.
Then we have a loop that goes from 0 to the end of the array.
And we're just adding in the value of each item in the array to the total variable.
And then we return it at the end.
So again space not time.
So we're concerned about.
So what are the things that take up space.
Well no matter what the array length is we have one variable called Total one number and then we're
looping through.
But we're not concerned about that time again.
And then we have a second declaration inside the for loop equals zero.
So that's another number and that's it for space.
We're coming back to the total variable we're adding into it but that doesn't matter.
That takes time.
But the space is already there.
So no matter what the size of the array is of end or in this case a r r as it grows might be a thousand
items it might be a million items.
Well it might be 10 or 50 or thousand.
Let's start simple.
It doesn't have an impact on the space that's taken up because we only have these two variables and
they exist no matter what.
We're not adding new variables based off of the length we're adding to the total variable.
But we're not making a new variable.
So that really just means we have constant space of one space.
It's always the same no matter the size of the input.
Here's another one.
So this is called double.
It takes an array and well why don't I just copy this one and show you.
So I've copied it in and it's called Double pass in an array of 1 to 3.
What does it return to me.
An array with two items is what I say.
An array with three items is saying like.
But each one has been doubled.
And what's important to note it is making a new array.
So it starts with making that new array.
Then it loops over the length of the first array and then it multiplies each item and pushes that on
to new array and then returns new array.
So what does that mean for the space complexity of this as the array length grows as the input approaches
infinity.
But to ignore the fact that javascript can't handle that what happens to the space that this algorithm
takes up in here.
So yeah we have this.
We're going to make a new array no matter what every time.
But that's not that significant when we consider this right here we have this new array and it's getting
longer and longer and longer directly in proportion to the length of the input.
So if the array is 10 items here we're storing 10 items in a new array.
If this is 50 items or storing 50 items here in a new array and returning that so the space that's taken
up is directly proportionate to N to the input array.
So end numbers we get 0 of and space.
So we don't need to care about things like this we can simplify it down just to the fuzziest level which
is of end rather than of and plus one or something like that or actually plus 2 because we also have
this.
Those don't matter.
So I know it's a lot.
And it's it's hard to understand right away.
And it might not click.
That's ok though we have some exercises but I want to make it clear that you do not need to master this
before we move on.
I should just delete the whole point is that I should have in ten section so now will have a couple
of solutions and I want to be able to say hey the space complex.
Yeah this one is great.
And the time to flex this one is terrible and squared time complexity but constant space complexity
or something.
And you should hopefully be able to understand what I mean by that.