Hello welcome back.
This is part two of sorting algorithms.
This is intermediate sorting algorithms.
So we have three more to look at.
And basically we're learning these separate because they are much faster but they're also a little bit
more challenging they're less intuitive to write on your own They're meteor Giusi or algorithms that
take more time to understand but they're also the payoff is that they're faster and I'm going to prove
it to you.
I'm going to show you at least one example of just how much faster they can be in this video.
But first I want to add an important note which is don't be scared when I've taught this before I think
a lot of students feel bad because they struggled through the beginning elementary sorting algorithms
they weren't able to write everything on their own.
That's totally normal.
And when you get to these three these algorithms are harder they're stepping it up.
Don't don't feel pressure to write the code yourself period but especially not the first time through.
So I'm going to give you pseudo code for the adventurous souls who do want to try and implement it on
their own.
But really this section is more about walking through the code and understanding how it works.
Being able to explain the algorithms not being able to rewrite it word for word character for character.
On your first try.
So keep that in mind.
We're going to go through it.
Focus on how it works.
Focus on being able to explain back to me for example what each line of my code does.
Rather than you feeling the pressure to come up with everything from scratch because these are challenging
and these are algorithms created by academics that have been around for a while that have been tried
and tested.
So please don't worry don't be too intimidated.
I don't want it I'm turning nobody away.
All right.
If the last section was hard for you that's OK.
Don't feel bad that this one is called intermediate.
OK.
So our objectives first understand the limitations of what we have learned so far.
Bubble's selection and insertion.
What's wrong with.
Well we should say what's wrong what are those shortcomings.
We're going to implement three sorts implement merge sort of quicksort and radix sort.
But first I promised I would show you a demonstration of how much faster the algorithms were going to
learn now are.
So the sorting algorithms we've learned so far don't scale well.
They actually work pretty well on small a 20 item array.
They work pretty fast but they do not scale well if we're working with a 100000 elements for example.
So if we actually tried bubble sort I'm I'm going to scale it down and just do 10000 elements.
It takes quite a while I'm going to show you right now.
So what I have here so here's my bubble sort implementation and down here I have a little bit of code
that makes an array of oh no this is $100 and I can't count.
Never mind.
It is 100000 elements and I'm going to start by showing you bubble sort.
Now what this code does.
I just copy this over and change this number to be 10.
It just picks 10 random numbers and sticks them in an array.
So if I do 100000 we're going to have an array that's 100000 random numbers.
There shouldn't really be any ordered period.
I mean it's technically possible they could be already sorted but that would be insanely unlikely with
100000 items.
Ok so I'm going to do this now I'm going to hit enter.
It's going to make the array that just takes like a split second but then bubble sorting it's going
to take a little bit.
So Command enter started.
And how am I going to talk about pass the time here.
Well let's see when I write what I'm going to say here.
He got some time to pass.
Well it's a nice day outside and I'm in here recording.
There we go.
Looks like it just finished so I don't know exactly how long that was.
I think I also put a cut in the middle of this because I took a sip of water and then I realized that
I was going to sound really bad on the camera from gulping.
So anyway that was about 20 seconds of my time.
Now if I do the same thing with Merge which I already have in this file merge sort.
We're not we haven't learned it yet but just watch it clear and read you run the same code so 100000
items but now pass it into merge sort.
Wow look at that.
I mean that's crazy how much faster that was.
That was like that was less than a second compared to 20 something seconds.
Now if I added another 0 here which I'm not going to remember the bubble sort is quadratic.
So that has serious implications when we add another zero when we're squaring the time basically.
That's huge.
That's a huge difference so I'm not going to do it.
But with merge sort I mean we'd still notice a difference but it's nowhere near the time difference.
And we'll talk about what the actual Big O is of something like merge sort.
But just I just want to show you there how much faster it is.
Maybe they give you some motivation for learning it so this faster family of algorithms that we're going
to learn they can improve time complexity from around 0 and 2 0 and log in.
So if you can think back I'll show you a chart again.
But oh of and again this is not bad it's pretty good.
It's much better than quadratic time over and squared.
It's not as good as log in and it's not as good as 0 of N but it's still pretty darn good.
So in this section we're going to learn three algorithms that improve time complexity and we'll also
learn why it's and Lagann for example where does the end log and come from we haven't really talked
about it.
We introduced the idea of a log.
We said that all of log in is good.
It's pretty fast but we haven't really seen where it comes from.
So we'll see that there's a tradeoff though as I mentioned between efficiency and simplicity unfortunately.
So these more efficient algorithms are definitely harder.
They're longer.
Or even if they're not longer in the amount of code they're just weirder they're not they're not how
we think as humans most the time is not how you would sort something.
So they take a little longer to understand but it's worth it right.
That's a very big difference that I just showed you and that was only 100000 items.
Now imagine a million or 10 million pieces of data massive differences in time.
So let's dive in in the next video merge sort.