Hey welcome back.
So now we get to the sorting part of merge sort.
And this is actually the code itself is pretty short.
It's only my solution is what 5 ish lines.
The problem is that conceptually it's a bit hard to understand and that's because most merge sort implementation
to use recursion.
So if you skipped the recursion section I highly recommend you go take a look at that because this is
going to seem a little insane.
If you've never seen recursion before and even if you have it's not immediately intuitive to write code
that's recursive.
So here's how it works.
We have a merge function that that works.
We just assume it works at this point.
If you didn't write it just go to the last video copy the code if you want to try and implement this
yourself.
But again don't feel bad if you can't.
This is really about the concepts how it works not about you being able to write it from scratch immediately
get some merge sort we have our merge function takes two sorted arrays.
Now remember the goal is to basically keep raking up the array into halves.
So how do we break an array just a single array into a half two halves.
Think about that.
My recommendation is to use slice to array slice and you go from zero until the middle theory.
And then you go from the middle array until zero and that gives you two halves.
And then what are you going to do with each one of those halves.
Welp you're going to call merge sort again and you're going to break each half into its own halves and
keep going recursively.
And once our base case when the arrays their length is less than or equal to one meaning that it's 1
or 0.
OK.
So that breaks them all up into these small elements the smaller arrays using slice recursively Intel.
Again our base case is we hit the end length is less than or equal to 1.
Then once we have those small arrays we merge them back using our merge function that we've already
written.
Until we're back at the full length of the array now it seems simple.
When you write it this way but the code it gets confusing when you're writing it recursively put it
that way.
But that's pretty much it.
So once the array has been merged back together we return the merged array at the very end.
OK so if you want to take a stab at this definitely do it.
But in the next video I'll walk through it.
Remember recursion is kind of crazy it can be.
It can be a bit of a leap to get there.
So don't feel bad if you can't get this one.
OK.
See in the next video.