OK so let's get writing our own merge sort.
So I have a new snippet again.
I have our merge function that works from two videos so we can get rid of this line for now.
Now I'll define our merge sort function which takes a single array.
And if we go back to our pseudo code all that we want to do is keep splitting it up into smaller arrays
and calling merge sort on those arrays until they the length of the array is 1 or 0.
So we can start with the base case if we want if array length is less than or equal to 1.
We're going to return the array not array one array.
So right now that doesn't mean much.
Basically we're not doing any recursive calls remember every recursive function has a base case and
then the recursive case a recursive function call.
So we're going to call merge sort on something again but it needs to be on the two halves of the array.
So how do we how do we put this array in half.
So for example if I call merge sort down here on this array 10 for 24 76 73 72 and 1.
So how do we split this in half.
So if we just took this I recommended using slice.
So if I save this variable var a r r equals that how do we splice it or slice it in half.
Well we go from zero for the left side we go from zero until what.
How do we find the midpoint.
Well we could take the array length divided by two and then floor that.
All right.
So remember binary search we did the same thing.
So that's what I would do math the floor of array length by 2 and that gives us 3.
So then I would do array does slice from 0 to 3.
And that gives us the first three items and then we need to array that slice from three to what we need
to do just see what we can actually just do it right up slice 3 and it will go from 3 until the end.
That's how it works you don't have to pass in the second number if you don't want to.
So that will split the array.
That's our first step and then we'll call merge sort on each of those.
So let's just write that code to start so we can define the midpoint here.
So let midpoint or let's just call it made equal that stop flow or just the same thing we saw a radar
length divide by two.
So that gives us the halfway point then we're going to say the left side equals a dot slice from zero
until the midpoint and then we'll say the right side equals what the right side is going to be a great
slice just from midpoint until the end.
So now we've split that array into two pieces are missing and are here.
There we go.
Now comes the tricky part instead of just doing the left equals a right out slice.
I'm actually going to call merge sort array slice and same thing here merge sort right out slice until
the end.
OK.
So what's happening here.
If we called this the first time through with this array right at length is not less than or equal to
1.
So we skipped that.
We find the midpoint and we find left and right.
So if we focus on left we're calling merge sort again on this array that you can see right here.
So that goes through and it's called again out like this not less and equal to one.
So we skip that line and then we split it in half again.
And now we call merge sort from the left and right and then one time through one of them has the length
of one.
So we turn that array.
But the other one has length of two because there's three items.
So we call merge sort again.
And then at that point we have three single item arrays and now we have to worry about merging them
back.
And this is the other bit of magic we merge the left and the right.
So this is the code and I'm going to walk through line by line how it works we're going to step through
the call stack with a smaller version but let's just make sure that it's working if I execute it looks
good.
1 9 10 24 72 73 76.
OK.
Now let's call it on let's do four items and I'm going to put a breakpoint right here.
Now if we look at what happened just with these four items to step through it's going to run the code.
And when we close the console so we have more space.
Look at our call stack over here.
OK here we go on our journey.
So we start and merge sort is called on this array it's four items long.
So this first thing does not happen.
Then we find the midpoint which is two.
Now here's the first thing.
Watch what happens to a call stack.
We are recursively adding.
So there's another merge sort that's been added to the call stack.
And if you look now at this merge sort it's been called on the left half right.
So the left half is just 10 and 24 is the array length less than or equal to 1.
Nope.
So we skip it and what happens again we find the new midpoint which is just index which is just the
middle of the survey we're calling merge sort on what if we look at our stack again.
There we go calling merge sort on a single element 10.
All right.
Now this time rate at length is less than or equal to 1 right.
So we're going to return the array of 10 and you'll see it pop off the stack here.
Just a second return value array and it pops next.
We're back to this one.
So now we're back to we left off right here right.
This was this is a hard thing about recursion.
I wish I had a white board diagram this all up but we were waiting.
This function call waited for left to go all the way until it returned something and now right needs
to go all the way until the returns of being so right on that second half is 10 common 24 we split it
and the right side goes in and we get the array of 24 length is less than or equal to 1.
So we return array and see it pops up the call stack and just the second now we merge the left and right
10 and 24 and we merge them together.
It calls merge all this code happens and at the end of the day we end up merging.
And then finally returning and watch the call stack.
Now we pop off again.
Now this time we've finished left right that was waiting.
And this code we are waiting to merge the left side.
Now we need to do the right side.
We never even ran this line.
So now the right side is now going to go and if we take a look it's calling merge sort again with what
is it passing in just a moment ago.
76 and 73 so that length was not less than or equal to 1.
So we didn't return it.
So we move on now we call merge sort on the left side which gives us 76.
The length is less than or equal to 1.
So we're going to return array and you'll see it pop off that call stack go in there we go.
And now we're back here at merge sort for the right side.
It's crazy I know this is the hard part to understand but we're back here and this time we're calling
it was 73 or read at length less than or equal to one that's true.
We return that array which is 73 pops off the call stack.
Now what we have is left and right so left to 76 right is the array 73 we merge them together.
So we call back up here go through this merge them and then eventually return results which is the merged
array.
Now we returned that from this merge sort call to our original call of merge sort which was waiting.
So we have left and right that have now been merged.
Well they haven't been mercy weather excuse me they have been sorted they've been split up and sorted
individually and then merged.
Now we have two item two arrays that are two items long and we merge those together with our final merge
left and right now this code takes a bit longer because we've got two pieces of data for each one.
You can see results down here.
We return results to merge sort.
So now we have 10 24 76 73 and that is what we return out.
And finally I think for show the cons. We end up with that return value.
So as you can see it's a lot to keep track of in your own just four elements trying to keep track of
it all in your head can be a lot.
So I diagrammed it out and let's just take a look at the actual order thing happening.
So when we call merge sort on 10:24 76 73 first thing that happened array is this array we check is
the length bus some are equal to one.
No.
So we find the middle point and then we'd call merge sort on the left side from 0 until the midpoint.
So this is called merge sort of 10 common 24.
So then in that code if our list is 10 24 it's still not less than or equal to one the length.
So then we call merge sort again on the left.
And now this time the length of this array is less than or equal to 1.
And in that event we return array.
So we return 10.
So now this merge sort of 10 common 24 the list of two items long it now has a value for left.
So next it finds a value for right.
It was waiting for this to come back.
Remember now it came back so it moves on to the next line.
Right now would call merge sort of the right side which is 24 merge sort of 24.
The length of that array is less than or equal to one.
So it returns 24.
So now we have our left and we have our right.
So now we can move on to this line merge left come right.
So when we call merge left come right with 10 and 24 remember our merge function takes into sorted arrays.
It merges them and that returns a value which is the array.
10:24 Yes it was already sorted but ignore that part and our code doesn't know that.
So it returns a value now.
So that was returned from this merge sort call which was the left side of our first merge sort.
So now our very first merge sort was waiting and it has a side returned.
Now its going to do the whole right side.
So we call merge sort on 76 73 in that code.
The length is not less than or equal to 1.
So it computes the midpoint and then it does the left side merge sort of of 76 which that that is a
one item array so it returns a value 76 then this right side which was waiting we can we completed this
side.
Now we're going to merge sort the rest and that gives us 73 as a return value because it's a single
item array.
Then once again we move on to this line.
This was waiting.
Merge left and right.
Well now we have our left and our rights we merge them and that returns 73 Comus 76 to item array then
this merge sort appear.
Now has the left and the right that it was waiting on.
So it finally got this then eventually this.
Now it can actually merge left and right and to the left and right merge we end up with this 10:24 73
and 76.
I know it's a lot.
But remember I've said this a couple of times.
Just focus on being able to explain what's happening or walk through if you have a white board or a
piece of paper I think it can be really helpful to write down exactly what's in the call stack at any
given point.
And I recommend you don't try it on a super long array.
If you go into like six seven items it takes a lot more time and a lot more space to diagram.
Please don't feel too intimidated by this.
In the next video we'll talk about the big O of merge sort.