All right welcome back.
I just want to quickly talk about Big O time and space complexity for merge sort.
So we kind of we haven't mentioned it really although I showed you in the very first intro to merge
sort video how much faster it is at least anecdotally compared to something like bubble sort.
But the best case the average case and the worst case for merge sort are all the same.
Oh of and log and so unlike something like bubble sort bubble sort did did OK it was quite well I wouldn't
even say OK it does pretty poorly.
It's quadratic and squared time in Must the data in the best case is already sorted in which case it
improves to linear time of an merge sort has no such.
I don't want to say this.
There is no edge case like that and merge sort.
It doesn't care what the data looks like.
It doesn't have an impact it's going to split it up over and over and over and merge things over and
over and over no matter what the input is.
If it's already sorted or if it's reversed or totally random It doesn't really matter.
So that's the first point.
Now the second thing is why is it end log n where does that come from.
And definitely I would not expect you just to know that or even necessarily to be able to compute that
right away.
But here's a basic overview.
So if we have this if we start with an array of eight elements.
So this is showing at the end of the process merging them together.
But just we have let's say we're starting here and moving upwards.
So we have to split it into two pieces.
So that's one decomposition.
Then we split it again and that's another decomposition.
And then again until we get items that are 1 or arrays or one item long.
So what is the relationship here.
If we have eight items in the array and is eight.
How many times do we have to split in order to get single element arrays.
In this case it's three.
But if instead we had an array of 32 items.
I will not I'm not going to type it all out but imagine that I'm just writing the length here.
So we have an array of 32 items.
We could do a split which gives just one array of 16 and another 16 and then we can split that again
which is what would happen we'd get an 8 8 8 8 so 4 8 item arrays.
And then we split that again.
And what do we get.
We get 8 4 out item a race and then we keep going.
And I am not going to count these precisely.
It doesn't exactly matter.
Anyway forget this the number right.
The point is though eventually we're going to end up with 32.
One item a raise.
Now how many splits did we have to do to get there.
I'm not counting.
Please don't hold me accountable here.
How many splits.
Well here's the first split the second the third the fourth the fifth.
So highs and grew to 32.
We had five splits when N was eight.
We had three splits.
What's that relationship.
Well going back to the big O.S. that log and now remember we're talking about base 2.
So log base 2 of.
And what that really means is two of what power gives us.
So in our case if we have eight elements we take two and raise it three times one to three to get eight
or if we have 32 elements that means two times two times two times two times to two to the fifth power
is going to give us 32.
So that's where the log end comes from as and grows the length of this array the number of times we
have to split it up grows at the rate of log n.
Now what about the N log and where does that come into play.
Well each time that we decompose it we have o of and comparison's when we're doing the merge.
So for example let's take a look at this row right here.
This is on the way back to the merge towards the the last it's the last step of merging.
There's always eight items for Compare it comparing each time through right.
We're not adding or removing items at any point we're just splitting them up and moving them around.
But there's always eight things total.
So here we would start and compare one and three to single comparison and then one of those is chosen
which is 1.
So then we move on and we compare two and three and then we compare three and six and then four and
six at the end of the day we have 0 of and comparisons on each of these.
So as the length of end grows the merge algorithm itself not the merge sort just the merge has time
complexity of Ovett.
So if we have a thousand items in the array there's roughly a thousand comparisons that need to be made
if we have eight items in the array.
There's roughly eight comparisons that need to be made to merge.
So in total we end up with analog again.
So o of all again is the number of decompositions as and grows.
There are the number of times the split and the number of times but the array grows at the rate of Flugge
end.
But then each time we do split each decomposition we have a live and comparison to actually perform
the merging.
So in total we end up with 0 of end log end.
So if we look at a chart here and log in could see its way better than something like 0 of squared quadratic
time.
Its not as good as laga And of course or linear time of and but this is actually the best that we can
get for a sorting algorithm unless the algorithm itself takes advantage of some weird quirk in the data.
So theres an algorithm will look at called radix sort that uses a particular quirk of numbers and it
won't work to sort anything else.
But if we want a data agnostic sorting algorithm the best we can do is 0 of and log in some merge sort
is doing great.
It's always over and log in best worst and average time.
And then finally space complexity.
So this is a bit different compared to things like bubble sort which have a constant space complexity.
When we talk about merge sort as we have a larger array we have to store more race in our memory and
not in our memory.
We have to use more space.
So that is a tradeoff.
Now usually we care about time complexity but if space is a consideration then absolutely something
like merge sort takes up a lot more space compared to bubble sort or any of the other earlier sorts.
OK.
So that is the big O of merge sort.
Next up we have a whole other fun sorting out for them.
See you then.