Hey welcome back.
So this is the first of a couple of sections on a somewhat notorious topic which is sorting and sorting
algorithms.
So when I get to this point in my in-person classes I think this is a topic that a lot of people have
been dreading.
So people look forward to it but it's something that has taken on a bit of weight in the developer.
So I don't know Zeit Geist.
It's a heavy topic to people and it's something that is important and part of the reason I think is
that it's sort of like the quintessential computer science topic that every blog post ever about getting
your dream job at Google.
Here are 10 things you must master or every book about aging the computer science interview.
There's always a large section devoted to sorting and for good reason.
It is an important topic it's a great challenge and something that we do all the time whether we're
writing our own code or using a built in sort method.
It's important but it also doesn't have to be that scary.
So let's start by just talking about what sorting is referring to when we say a sorting algorithm.
It just is that it's referring to the process of rearranging items in any collection.
So we could take a string and sort the individual characters inside a sentence for example but we're
going to usually be working with arrays at least for now.
Later we'll talk about sorting other data structures like linked lists or trees.
But for now we're focusing on an array.
So let's say we have an array of data we want to write a function that takes the terrain and spits out
a reordered array.
So that could be sorting numbers from smallest to largest or the other way around ascending or descending.
It could be sorting names alphabetically or if we have movie data that say objects movie objects.
Each movie has a year.
A total revenue.
It has a director a title.
We could sort them by release here or we could sort them by revenue or we could take their international
and domestic revenue add those together and then sort by that.
So the point is that it doesn't really matter what we're sorting by what the comparison is whether it's
alphabetically what comes first or numerically what comes first that doesn't matter.
The algorithms behind it don't really care.
We're going to focus on working with arrays for now and just in numbers.
So imagine that I asked you to write a function called sort and it just takes in an array and it should
return that array sorted.
So if I called it like this with let's just say some random numbers like that you would need to write
code in here in order to make this work so that it should return but C in this case what are we looking
at six comma 12 13 23 and 45 from in ascending order.
What we're going to start with.
So it's a simple It's a simple challenge right.
We can we can look at this it doesn't seem that bad but there's a million ways of doing this.
And that's part of the problem part of what makes sorting algorithms kind of scary is that I can think
of 15 probably named algorithms that exist that actually have a name that are kind of well-known that
do the exact same thing and there are definitely some better ones overall that we will be floating about.
Then there are also some that are very niche that are terrible most of the time but they do well in
certain situations.
So just to give you a really quick preview.
This is a video I like to show when I'm teaching sorting.
We're not going to look at.
I'm going to skip around for like 15 seconds but it visualizes the different approaches to sorting.
So basically over here we have some unsorted data representing let's say numbers.
The taller items are taller rows our columns are a larger number let's say this is 100 the tallest one
here and the smallest one is representing the number one.
So they're all in this order totally random and we write code to go and order them.
So here's one approach called selection sort.
And you can see that it builds up the array one item at a time.
It sorts it one thing at a time till we're done.
Then here's another approach.
It's called insertion sort and it's a little bit different.
We've got quick sort.
Very different.
We're working from the start and the end at the same time.
We've got one called merge sort.
Another approach heapsort radix sort.
We're not going to learn every single one of these there's 15 in this video shell sort bubble sort.
But the point is that these are all different approaches.
They all end up with the exact same resort resort.
They end up with the same results but how they get there is very different.
So this video was kind of fun to take a look at.
I will warn you the sound is the sound is a little bit of noxious.
I'm not playing it here but definitely don't play it on high volume if you're going to check this video
out.
So why do we need to learn this.
That's the next question.
So there are all these different algorithms and we're going to learn a bunch of them but why.
The first is that sorting is something that is really really common in programming and even if you are
using the built in javascript sort or the built in sort that in Ruby or in Python for example it still
is important to understand what algorithm it's using behind the scenes because that will help us understand
what it's good at and what it's bad at.
And that brings us to the next point which is there are many ways of sorting things and each algorithm
that we see will have pros and cons.
So while some are objectively faster than others there are certain situations where one algorithm would
say that the data is almost sorted and there's just a couple of pieces that are out of place.
Some algorithms that are usually slow will be really fast at that.
So if you know for example that you're working with data that is pretty uniform it's almost all sorted
but there's a couple of things that are out of place and you want to make sure that it's being sorted
as fast as possible.
You might want to implement your own sort rather than having to rely on the built in one which isn't
going to be as fast in that situation.
And just to illustrate my point this is a really cool Web site I'd like to show called sorting algorithm
algorithms animations and it shows seven of the most common sorting algorithms insertions selection
bubble shall merge heap and quicksort.
These are all different approaches and what it's showing here are different data sets.
So a totally random set of data versus nearly sorted so you can see we're almost there but there's a
couple of items out of place totally reversed data and then data that has few unique items so a lot
of very similar items.
Now what I'm going to show you is first of all what this does is it just visualizes what happens just
like the video I showed you in the past but this compares them all at once.
So if I hit play on random you can see how basically how their speeds compare.
Whoops I missed it.
There you go.
Their speeds compare and their approaches compare.
So this is totally random data and you'll see things like keep a quick merge and shell finish much before
insertion and selection and bubble and poor selection just finished.
But then if we look at nearly sorted you'll see that insertion actually finished pretty shirt finished
first didn't it.
Yep it's done before anything else poor selection still very slow.
And I won't go through all of this but you can feel free to play around with this but all that this
is showing is that something like insertion which was slow when our data is totally random was actually
very quick when our data was nearly sorted.
I think I was the first one to finish.
So they have pros and cons and it's worth understanding them.
And the other reason I didn't put on here that we already hinted at this is a classic interview topic.
It's something that is a great well it's just a good problem.
There's so many approaches it's really a good critical thinking challenge complete from using that phrase.
And like my dad it's just it's a good challenge to do and it's something that comes up in interviews.
So of course that's a good reason to know something if you're trying to interview.
So without further ado let's talk about what we're covering in this section.
Our objectives are.
First we're going to implement bubble sort.
So this is one algorithm we'll learn how it works and implement it.
Same thing for selection sort and then insertion sort.
So these are what I'm calling the elementary sorting algorithms.
They definitely are less commonly used because they're less efficient but that doesn't mean that you
shouldn't learn them.
And we'll talk more about why it's important.
But I kind of already hinted that hinted at it.
We saw that at least one of the algorithms performed very well in a certain very specific situation.
So we'll be able to analyze these as we go through and figure out when they perform well and then after
this we will move on to more advanced sorting algorithms as well.
So let's start first before we even get to bubble we're going to talk about the built in javascript
sort the sort method and just learn how that works.