Hey this video will be super quick.
We're just going to talk about the built in our radar sort.
So in javascript every array has a built in way to sort it.
Yes it does.
Thank you slides but it doesn't always work how you would expect it should.
For example take this array of strings.
We sort it and I think this makes sense if we get the result that you would probably expect there's
sorted alphabetically.
So a for algorithms and C and D for data structures and then steal.
That makes sense I think to go from a down to Z or up to whatever we're going from A-Z.
Then if we do the same thing with numbers 6 for 15 and 10 and you sort it what we get doesn't really
make sense.
So it starts with 10 and then 15 then for then six.
So it would be one thing if it was just the opposite order like if it was descending instead of ascending
greatest to lowest instead of lowest to highest.
But it's not even ordered in any discernible way that we that we can make sense of no numeric order.
What's actually happening as if we read the arrays sort documentation on MT-NW is that here we go to
default sort order is according to string Unicode code points.
So there's this thing called Unicode use to represent strings.
And what happens is that every item that array is converted to a string.
And then the Unicode value of that is taken and then they're sorted.
So it's very bizarre and it's almost never what you want unless you're working with strings to start.
But even then it's not always what you want.
So how does it actually work.
How do we use it in the real world.
That's only what happens.
That's the behavior when you don't pass anything and you just do dot sort.
With empty parents.
But there's this whole other thing we can do where we can actually specify how it should sort.
What property it should sort by what to compare.
So it accepts an optional compared or compare store function and we can use this to tell javascript
how we want it to sort.
So basically the structure that we write this function is it takes two items which will call a and b.
And we tell Javascript the sort order to make based off of what we return.
So if we return a negative number.
So if we have two elements again a and b Javascript can call this function every time it's comparing
two elements.
If this function returns a negative number then javascript will decide that a comes before B if it returns
a positive number then it's the other way around.
A comes after B.
And if we return 0 javascript treats and B is the same and just sorts them basically together it doesn't
matter.
So here's an example number compair is what we called our competitor function.
And all we're doing is returning one minus two.
So javascript gets this.
Remember this is what comes first.
This is what comes second.
If this returns a negative value then number one comes first before number two if it returns a positive
value then number two comes first and then 1.
So when we do this you can see that it's now sorting things appropriately in ascending numeric order.
So if we get four and then 6 and then 10 and then 15 and have it over in a snippet here.
So if I run a little big.
There we go.
So if I run this now you'll see that we get 4 6 10 15.
But if I just change this order so numb to minus 1 for example we get 15 10 6 and 4.
So that's sorting just by numbers which that's what you would do if you're trying to serve something
numerically rather than working.
You know the Unicode characters and worrying about all that we can also do something like this to sort
by the length of a string rather than alphabetically.
We want to sort from whatever the shortest string is so cold up and hold the longest string which would
be data structures.
So it would do the same thing string one of length minus string to downlink and we call this compared
by line but remember it doesn't matter what we call this it's just a random function.
But it needs to except these two arguments.
And then we use them in here and we return a negative number a positive number or zero.
So what do we get.
There we go.
And if we started around change the order of string to adult length might a string one length.
Now we have the other order.
So this is how we can define our own basic sorts using the built javascript's sort method.
Now I just showed that to you so that you know that it exists and it's an option.
Now what we'll focus on in the rest of this section is writing our own sorting algorithms that actually
do the comparisons.
That's the hard part.
And so that's coming up next.
We're going to kick it off with a fan favorite.
It's not a fan favorite but it has a fun name bubble sort.
See you in the next video.