All right let's do this let's get implementing bubble sort.
So I had pretty specific instructions here.
Start looping.
Oh I just realized this is a bit of a typo.
Sorry about that.
Start looping from the end of the array towards the beginning with a variable called I.
What I'm actually going to do is show you the Domer.
I shouldn't say dumb the the less optimized version that doesn't follow these instructions which just
uses two nested loops that go from the beginning to the end of the array the entire way.
So that would look something like this.
I'll define my function I'll call it bubble sort.
I made a new snippet.
By the way it accepts an array and we know at the end it's going to return the array.
And let's say I'm going to call it with a super simple array like is 37 45.
I have such a tendency to pick odd numbers like this.
It's not on purpose.
OK we'll put eight in there.
OK.
So this is what we start with.
And we're going to loop over every item in the array.
So for our i equals zero and I'm going to do like I said just starting from the beginning.
So zero up until are less than great length plus plus.
So that's going to give us a single pass right.
If this is only going to loop What is it four times.
So we'll start with zero and end it at 3.
So that gets us enough to sort one item so we could compare and do our swaps and at the end of this
loop if we did swap things we would have 45 at the end of the array but we self to sort everything else.
So we need to repeat that process for every item technically.
Remember we don't have to do it for every single item every time in that array because as we progressed
the end becomes sorted.
So if we started with this the next time through we would end up with 45 at the end.
So then next time we only need to sort these three.
And if we did that we end up with 37 bubbling here and now we only need to sort these two.
But for our naive solution let's just have the code go all the way to the end.
Every single time.
So for that we just need another loop.
So for call it J equals zero while J is less than a length J plus plus.
And now we have J.
So J is going to be zero starting at the beginning and we want to compare whatever item we're looking
at with J to the one in front of it.
So J and J plus one that just looks like this array of J.
Comma array.
Well no comma.
Ignore that.
We want to check if it's greater.
So if array of J is greater than the one in front of it.
Swap.
So let's let's right that logic now.
Now as far as swopping I'm going to start with the basic.
Swap the tried and true swap where we make a value.
So a variable I'll call it temp and set it to one of them it doesn't matter.
I'll set it to array of J.
And then we change the value of array of J to be array of J plus 1.
Thankfully we save the old version in our temporary variable.
Now we set the array of plus 1 equal to temp.
OK.
And that's actually it.
This is a working version of bubble sort but it's just not optimized because of what we talked about
it keeps running over and over and there's actually another small problem.
Let's start by pointing out a peer counselor log what the array looks like as we go.
All right let's see if it works.
Here's our first pass.
We had thirty seven forty five twenty nine and eight.
We compared the two.
Thirty seven and forty five.
We don't swap.
Now we move on.
J is incremented by 1.
So we compare 45 and 29 and we do swap.
He can see that change reflected the next time through.
Then we compare 45 and 8.
And once again we swap.
And so that's what happens here eight and forty five.
That looks good.
We have 45 at the end.
But here's the problem.
And actually I've changed my mind a little bit.
I think we'll even be clearer as if rather than just printing the array consulate log array.
If we also print what we're comparing.
So I'm going to do a array of J an array of J plus one so we can see the comparison as it happens.
I me clear my counsel here.
It Again.
OK.
So now you can see we're comparing 37 45 45 29 45 and 8 but then 45 and undefined.
So what happens is that we went too far.
J hit the end of this loop at 45.
Well J is equal to three index of three and we're comparing it to index of four which there isn't.
So we're comparing 45 and undefined.
Now our sort still works but we're going too long.
We don't need to do this.
Not to mention the fact that now we know this is sorted.
So we start over.
We compare these to 37 and 29 that is swapped right.
So we do swap them.
Then we have thirty seven and eight.
We swap again and we should be done with this iteration we should start over and start sorting this.
But instead we compare 37 and 45.
But we know that that's already sorted 45 isn't moving.
Nothing is going to be higher than 45 because of the way bubble sort works.
It is cemented in place the first time through.
So we haven't need this comparison.
And once again next time through you'll see we do the same thing.
Thirty seven and forty five there's no reason.
So what we want to do is basically at the beginning we want to make three comparisons.
So there's four items in this array.
We want to have three comparisons.
One two one two three.
And then we should start over and next time only make two comparisons.
These this comparison right here 37 and 29 and then thirty seven and eight.
And then next time through it we should make one comparison.
Does that make sense we want to we want to shrink the number of comparisons we're making because we're
sorting the array as we go.
So the solution to that if we come and make a couple of edits.
The first is that I'm actually going to change the way this loop is set up.
I'm now going to follow the pseudo code I set up.
We're going to start with variable i.
It goes from the end of the array towards the beginning.
So that looks like this set to be a red dot length.
And we go wow i is greater than zero minus minus.
The reason we do this is so that we can use I in the definition of the loop for J.
So J now runs wild less than I dot or I mind this one.
What am I saying Don.
I'm minus one.
OK.
So at the very beginning our ray length is four.
It's always four.
But I started at four.
So then this loop the inner loop we're going to compare J is less than four minus one.
So three comparisons.
This gives us three comparisons the first time through because I is four.
That means J goes for minus 1 3.
Next time through I has gone down I'm on this minus.
So we end up with I equal three.
So then we have J less than three minus one.
So that means to this loop will run while J is less than 2.
So as I goes down so does J.
So we end up running the loop fewer times each time through.
So if I save this get rid of that extra X rerun it may clear the cons. no.
Now let's look at the comparisons that are made.
So we do 37 and 45 that make sense then 45 and 29 and then our final comparison on this first time through
forty five and eight and we end up with the first time through 45 is at the end.
Then we start over.
We're no longer sorting undefined and 45 because of this minus one.
So then next time through we do two comparisons 37 and 29 so we swap and then 37 and 8 and we do swap
again.
And at that point these two are cemented.
So next time through we only have to do one more comparison and you can see that eight twenty nine we
swapped them and we're done.
So what I could do.
Let's increment let's change this to be 8 12.
88 one hundred.
Now let's see.
Negative 3 area negative value.
And if we run it now let's clear the console first.
There we go.
Let's let me actually.
Sorry this is annoying but let me make this easier to see.
So after that loop finishes let's do conses log 1 pass complete like this.
OK rerun this.
OK.
So now you can see really what happened the first time through we did one two three four five six comparison's
then that was one full pass.
Next time through it we did one two three four five comparison's and then four comparisons and then
three then two and then one.
So this is one version of the solution.
Get rid of the concert that logs.
I also have East 2015 version where I decided to first I use the old version or sorry the new way of
swapping things and I decided to make it into a function.
You definitely don't have to do that.
I mean this is only three lines honestly.
But if you want to hear is the nicer some people consider this solution nicer.
Use less as well and otherwise.
What else.
Big arrow function.
Everything is pretty straightforward though.
You just let's run it and make sure it still works of course
there we go.
They give three up to 88.
OK.
So these are two working solutions to bubble sort.