Hey welcome back.
We're moving on to our next intermediate sorting algorithm which is called quicksort.
So it has a bit of a catchy name it sounds better than merge sort.
I mean who doesn't want a software that is called quicksort.
But I have to I have to admit personally this is the bane of my existence as far as sorting algorithms
not because it's bad.
I mean it's very useful as we'll see later on it's efficient.
It works well.
It is indeed quick.
But for some reason my brain just is not like the way that quicksort works.
And each time I have to teach these sorting algorithms I usually you know the night before a lecture
we'll go review make sure I remember how everything works.
I can rewrite the code and occasionally you know I'll have to like reference previous code or something.
But with quicksort every single time I have to double check my work my brain just rejects storing it.
It just won't it does not like it.
So not to poison your opinion of it ahead of time because I have had many a student who really loves
quicksort just for me the way my brain works.
It's just not very intuitive.
So we're going to spend special.
We're going to pay special attention to trying to understand it and make sure we step through it.
OK so quicksort it works on the same assumption that merge sort does it.
It's one that is going to be easiest to solve through recursion where we keep basically splitting up
the data the array until we hit arrays that are 0 or 1 item long which means that they are individually
sorted.
We have an item of one.
You have an array with one item.
It is sorted.
So that's what we take advantage of but we do something different.
We work by selecting a single element which we're going to call the pivot point.
So in any array you pick any element it doesn't actually really matter.
We'll talk about some of the implications.
But let's say we pick the element in the middle.
What we're going to do is move all the numbers that are lower than that number to the left of that number
in all the numbers that are greater than that number to the right.
Now we're not going to sort them all.
We're just going to move them to one side and then from there we know that that one number is in the
correct spot.
That is only that one number.
Every other.
All the other numbers on the right side of things are the left side but we don't know the exact position.
So then we repeat the process for the left side and for the right side.
So if that explanation made zero sense I don't blame you.
Let's take a look at a little diagram.
So if this is our array we have 8 elements 1 to 8 the numbers and they're in a random order.
What we do is we just pick some element and for this example we're going to pick the first one which
is 5 and then move all the numbers that are less than 5 to the left of it and all the numbers that are
greater than 5 to the right.
So if we count the numbers that are less than 5 we have 1 2 3 4 numbers.
So that means that we should have 1 2 3 4 here.
We're going to move them all here and then at this index right here we'll move five.
And then on the right side we'll have 7 6 and 8.
And if you look at the next step that's what we've done.
So five is in the correct spot.
We know that in our sorted array 5 is going to have index of 4 0 1 2 3 4.
We don't know these aren't sorted.
This isn't sorted.
This is sorted right now.
So now we recursively repeat the process on the left side and the right side.
So on the left side let's just start again.
It doesn't really matter what we pick it will work no matter what.
But let's pick the first item again and put that in the correct spot.
So that means it's going to be at index of 0 1 2 because 1 and 2 need to come before it.
And that's what we end up with.
So now this is in the correct spot we know in our final array 3 is going to have index of 2 5 is going
to have index of four.
The next we have an element of two or an array of two elements.
This is nice and easy.
So we pick the first element which is one and we figure out where it needs to go.
And that all that we have is one other element which is greater than that.
So the right side now becomes two and we can sort that.
And it's a single element.
So we've now hit the end on our left side.
And if you kind of look.
Imagine drawing.
Imagine putting these all in the same line.
We end up with the sorted array.
At least the left side of the five.
Then we have to get to the right side.
Remember all the way at the beginning we split right there.
We just took care of this.
No highlighting the wrong thing.
OK.
My computer doesn't me to highlight that.
We took care of the left side here.
Now let's get to the right side.
So we pick the pivot point which is seven in our example and we have to figure out OK where should 7
go.
What's the index where it should end up.
We move the other elements so we move six to the left of it 8 to the right of it.
And those are both single element Arrays no.
And actually if you look at where we have 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 we have the sorted array there.
I got to have my slides again.
I'm always doing that.
So this shows us how it works roughly.
It's it makes sense I think in a nice diagram.
But when we actually start working and trying to write the recursion and visualize it when we have code
it can be a little bit tricky.
OK.
So I have visual I'll go pulled up with quicksort now.
So here's another visualization.
We start with this unsorted array and we pick 11 as our first pivot point.
So we want to move all the elements that are less than 11 to the left of it and all the ones that are
greater to the right.
So we start and just compare it.
OK 40 is greater than greater than greater and greater than.
OK here's a 10.
So that's less than.
So what we're going to do.
This might seem you might think that we would swap them or something.
What we're actually going to do is keep track of how many elements are less than 11 so so far it's one
element.
And then we're just going to swap 10 and 40 but we're mentally keeping track of in our code not mentally.
There was one element that we just that is less than 11.
Now we keep going.
No that's greater than greater than greater then.
OK here's another element.
Less than 11.
So we do the same thing again but now we know we have a variable and we say there are two things less
than 11.
So once we hit the end because there's nothing greater than 11 or nothing less than 11 anymore.
Now we know OK there were two things that we we added in.
There are two items that we now need 11 to leap frog over and that's what happens.
So now all 11 is in the correct spot.
So does that make sense we count 1 2 and then we move to that position.
And now everything on the left side is less than 11.
Everything on the right side is greater than 11.
Now it happens that these two values are sorted already.
But that's not our code doesn't know that it's not guaranteed.
OK.
So now our code is going to take the left side and repeat the same thing.
So this is showing us 11 is cemented in place and now it does the same thing with six in 10.
But this is super short because there's really no other values to compare.
And so it cements 6 and then it cements 10.
But now let's focus on the right side.
So next up we have 50 and I'm just going to count how many numbers are greater than 50.
Or how many numbers are less than 50 as we go through 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 numbers.
So now we're just going to swap 50 to the end there.
Now fifty's in the correct spot so it should turn orange.
OK.
So now we have to sort the left and the right side.
But there is no right side.
So we have to sort this love side.
So we picked 27 again.
Again why did it start again.
We picked 27 for the first time.
Now we compare it to 43.
That's greater than it.
Greater greater greater.
OK here's a less then.
So we swap and we keep track of.
OK.
There's one element that was that was less than.
Keep going.
Here's another swap.
Now we have two elements that were less than keep going.
Now we have three elements that are less than.
And finally four elements.
Now where do we put 27.
Well we know that we had four numbers less than 27 so we swap it there.
All right.
So I'm not going to walk through every other step.
I'm just going to fast forward.
But you can see 27 is now correct position.
Now we do the left side.
Keep going.
Now we did the right side 43 is in the correct spot.
Now 42 in the correct spot.
OK.
And we're almost there every go full is sorted.
So it's it's kind of this is why.
For me personally maybe that made more sense to you but trying to write this in code can be very intimidating.
And I'm going to give you the pseudocode in the next video but it's not at all the expectation that
you just go and write it.
This is a hard one.
So the actual code is not that long either.
But just conceptually it's a lot.
So I'm going to give you the pseudo code if you want to attempt it.
Go ahead.
But also don't beat yourself up please.