Welcome back.
And this video will read the first part of quicksort.
Just like with merge sort.
We implemented the merge helper.
First we're going to do the same thing here.
You might hear this called partition or pivot.
It does the same thing.
So we're going to write a function that given an array it designates an element as the pivot point and
it should rearrange the elements in the array.
So this is basically what I already said got ahead of myself.
And ahead of the slides.
Surprise surprise.
All values less than the pivot are moved to the left and all values greater than the pivot are moved
to the right.
But the order on either side doesn't matter.
It just needs to be less than the pivot and greater than the pivot on the right side.
But inside the left and right it doesn't matter what order that are in.
So the other really important thing is that this helper should do it in place.
So it should not make a new array and it should return the index of the pivot so it returns the index.
It does everything in place so don't make a new array to do it.
So the first thing to discuss picking a pivot is actually an important decision.
The runtime of quicksort can change depending on where you pick the pivot from.
Ideally it should be chosen to.
It's the median value in the dataset.
If that makes sense if we had to if we could perfectly get it we would pick the middle value of our
sorted data so that the left and right sides would be equal.
But that's not very easy to do if we don't know what the the data itself is and how it's ordered.
That's the whole point we're trying to order it.
So there are other strategies you pick the first element or the last one or the middle or a random element.
For simplicity's sake in this video we're just going to always choose the pivot to be the first element
that does actually have some consequences with as far as big-O that we'll talk about later but we're
going to just pick the first element to make it simple.
So here's how here's here's how it could work.
If this is our array and we call our pivot function of that array it should return index of 4.
So notice it doesn't return the array.
But if we look at the array it's been changed.
Any of these configurations are valid.
So what it does is it picks the first element and chooses that as a pivot.
So 5 and now it needs to rearrange the array so that 5 is in the correct spot where every number to
the left is less than 5.
So if we look at all these examples that could be the value of array it doesn't matter the order if
we have 2 than 1 and 4 than 3 or 1 than four then three then two and so on.
As long as we have one two three and four on this side and then on the other side we have six seven
eight in some order.
Now this isn't all the possible options.
I just didn't want to go and list every single possible combination out.
But it's important to note it doesn't matter for our code.
What we actually have on the left side or SUV.
It matters what we have it doesn't matter exactly the order that it's in on that side.
So these are all acceptable.
All that matters is that 5 is in the correct spot and we return the index which is for 0 1 2 3 4.
So this is basically saying in the if the final sorted array if you kept doing this on the left and
the right over and over and over 5 is in its final position this is where it's going to be.
Once you sort the data.
OK.
So here's the pseudo code.
Here's one version of it at least.
So write a function call it pivot or partition and accepts three arguments an array a start index and
an end index.
And I would have to start default to 0 and the end default to array length minus 1.
Then we're just going to pick the pivot from the start of the array remember and we could change it
to be from the middle or the end or a random place.
But for simplicity's sake we're picking from the very beginning and then store the current pivot index
in a variable.
So this is going to keep track of where we're going to swap that pivot to the very end.
So I'm going to walk through on the next in just a second on visual I'll go and show you what I mean.
But we're going to loop through the array from the start until the end and if the pivot is greater than
the element that we're looking at we're going to increment that pivot index variable from a pier and
then swap the current element with the element at the pivot index so it's a nightmare trying to just
read the pseudo code.
But it will make sense since I show an example.
And then we at the very end we swap the pivot that we started with with the pivot index.
And then we return the pivot index.
So rather than just talking about text.
Let's let's look at it.
So at the very beginning we're going to pick the first element to be our pivot.
We start at 28 then what we do is loop through every other element and we compare 28 to 41 in the first
case.
Forty one is greater.
So we actually don't do anything.
But then we get to 4.
28 is greater than four.
So we know that we need to have four on the left side of 28 and we're just going to keep a mental note.
We're going to have a variable called Pivot index and that's going to keep track of how many things
are less than 28 so that we can then swap 28 at the very end to the correct spot.
So we move four over and then we have this pivot index that currently is going to be equal to index
of 1.
So if there was nothing in Ignore everything on the other side of the era if there was nothing else
we know that 28 needs to be in this position at the end so that 4 can be less then but if we keep going
11 is also less than 28 so we're going to swap that with 41 and now increment the pivot index by 1.
So now we know.
OK.
There are two things.
Less than 28.
Go Again.
Whoops didn't click it.
Here we go 16 that's less.
So we swap.
And now we know there are three things less.
Then again we swap.
There are four variable variables there are four pieces of data in this array four elements less than
our pivot.
Nope.
OK here's our fifth one we swap.
We go again and again and again.
And here's our sixth element that is less than 28.
So we swap.
Now we've hit the end and we have this pivot index variable.
This mental note I mentioned and it's now equal to 6 because every time we found an element less than
28 we added 1 to it.
So we have 1 2 3 4 5 6.
This tells us we need to swap the element at index of 6 with our pivot which is at the beginning.
And if we do that there we go.
Now we're done.
All we have to do is return this index.
So everything on the left is less than everything on the right is greater than the pseudo code on it's
own isn't all that helpful.
But if you look at this side by side with something like this where you step through it I think it can
help.
So go ahead and implement this if you'd like to.
Again it's not all that easy but give it a shot if you want to stick around.
I'll do one more example walkthrough but I know that it can get boring if you if you understand it all.
And you're ready to go.
Or are you just bored.
Go ahead and skip this but I'll put it here for extra practice.
New data the very beginning.
We pick our pivot point at the just the first thing.
26.
Now we compare it to every other element.
23 is in less than 26.
So we're going to keep track of that.
We need to have we have that counter pivot index and we know at the very end at least we're going to
have to swap 26 to index of one.
We get to 27 that's greater then.
We don't do anything that's greater than again.
Now we get to 17 which is less than.
So what we do is we swap with 27 in this case and then we're going to increment our pivot index by once.
Now we know there are two things.
Less than 26.
So we need to swap at the end.
So 26 is here where 17 currently is we go through again that's greater than grade greater then greater
than greater then finally we get to one which is less than and we swap with 44 and now we increment
pivot index by 1 again.
So now it's at 3.
So at the end of our code we're going to swap the pivot and index of zero with the pivot index which
is 3 0 1 2 3.
So we swapped these two things and Whyalla.
Now we have the left side correctly the partitioned and the right side.
So 2006 is that the correct spot in our code should return index of 3 which is saying that the correct
spot for 26 in this array is index of 3.