All right welcome back.
So let's start by defining our Nope not in caps.
Our function called pivot and it accepts an array we have a start.
And you can go back and look at the pseudo code.
It should default to 0 and an end.
Defaults to arrayed at length plus 1.
And then here's my sample call.
So pivot of this take a moment and figure out what you think this should return positive you'd like
but it should return is the index 3 because it's going to take this first item which is 4 as our pivot
and figure out the correct index that it should be in.
So if we look at the sorted array like this this is the final array of these numbers.
This will not be returned from this but from our eventual quicksort it will be.
If you look at where 4 is that index of 0 1 2 3.
So our code should return the index of 3.
Now the array it could look like this at the end but more than likely it will look like this possibly.
And then on this side we might have 8 6 7 5.
All that matters is that four is in the correct spot.
So anything on the left just needs to be lower.
Anything on the right is greater but the order doesn't matter.
So the first thing we'll do is to find a variable called pivot and remember that our example we're starting
with the pivot always that's the first element.
So if start defaults zero will set this to be a array of start.
So we start with four for example as our pivot or if our array looks like this it would be 10.
So we start with that and then we're going to make a variable called Swap index.
Now swap index is going to keep track of where we're going to swap this for you at the very end.
And also is what we're going to return.
This is going to be the index.
In our case it should be 3.
Hopefully at the very end that we return.
So I'm going to start it at the beginning index of zero.
So it starts at zero.
Now we need to loop over every item in this array but there's no reason to loop over this first one
and compare it to itself.
So let's loop over everything after start.
So that means four of our equals instead of zero.
Let's do start plus one is less than a length I plus plus.
So rather than doing for comparing it to four and then 8 just do four and start off our loop right here.
Now all we want to do is compare our pivot.
So that's going to be four.
So if pivot is greater then we want to compare it to array of I.
The next element that we're looking at.
So our first time through is for greater than 8.
No.
So we're not going to do anything next time through though we're comparing four and now I had gone up
to the index of two.
So we compare four in the value of two.
Four is greater than two.
So what we're going to do is increment swap index by 1.
So this tells us OK there is one thing at least so far that is less than our pivot.
But then we're also going to swap two with 8 because our swap Index is one.
All we have to do is swap array of I with array of swap indexes that make sense or swap index was zero.
Now we found the first item that is less than four.
So we increment the counter that's keeping track of how many things to less than for where we moving
forward to at the very end it's equal to 1 anyway.
Now we need to swap.
So now what I'm going to do is just copy in any swap function.
This is our basic one.
It just takes an array and then two indices and it swaps the values in that array.
And I'm going to put it in a function because we're going to actually use it more than once in our code.
So we're actually almost there.
What we're going to do now is swap the array inside of it.
The swap index followed by I.
So our first time through the first swap we make is 2 which is indebt which is I of two actually the
same number and then we're going to swap it with swapped index which is one.
OK.
So then we repeat the code.
Next time through we compare four and one.
Well one is still less than four.
So this time we increment swap index again.
So swap index is now two and then we're going to swap the item an index of two with the item index of
it which means we're going to swap one with the idon the tier which is actually 8.
So if I were to visualize this whole thing you start off like this.
And the next time through we don't do anything for Nate but then we do swap two and eights like that.
And then the next time through we're comparing four and one.
Well one is less than four.
So we swap one in eight like this.
And now our swap index is right here.
So at the end of the code if we if there was nothing less than four which there actually is.
But if there wasn't at the very end we're going to swap 4 and 1 and if we did that we end up with all
the numbers less than four on this side.
Ignoring the fact that we still have to account for three.
So we keep going and next you compare four and five nothing happens and we compare four and seven nothing
happens.
Four and six nothing happens.
Four and three this time three is less than four.
So what do we do we take three and we swap it with our swap index which was right here.
So now we swap eight and 3 and so we added one to our swap index which now makes it index of three which
are yes it also has the value of three that's confusing.
But this is our swap index.
So the very last thing we have to do after our loop is take that last swap index and swap it with the
start like this.
And now for is that the correct position.
So basically all that we've been doing.
We keep going through here and we move things over to the left.
We swap them anytime it's less than four.
But we've left four at the first position.
At the very end we can just swap four to the correct spot but we need to do.
Now if we actually just printed out array.
I think this would make it clear for us.
You can see here we start off I'm only printing it out when we do the swaps.
But you can see the final state is this.
And then we need to do our final swap move four and three swap them and then we need to return that
index of swap index.
So let's come down here after the loop and add in our final swap which is in the start the pseudo code
swap the starting element with the pivot index.
So we just do swap which again is coming from here.
And what are we going to swap.
We're going to swap the array.
Start and then swap index.
So we're not swapping the pivot because pivot is the value the start is the index of that pivot.
So this is kind of a headache to try and walk through.
Totally recognize that but let's just make sure it works first.
We need to return at the very end swap index.
Remember that's the whole point is to return the swap index.
We run it it returns three.
And if we start off with a different number like nine here returns 8 because nine the correct location
is at the very end of the array of index of 8.
So go back to 4.
So we get three if we don't log the array at the very end you should see four is in the correct spot.
All the lower numbers are before it all the greater numbers are after it.
So that's our pivot helper.
So that kind of a lot of work.
So now that we have that done we need to move on to the actual sorting part.
We're doing this one time.
We need to repeat this on the left side and then on the right side and then repeat that and repeat that
until we hit the one item race.
So we'll get there.
Oh and before I forget.
Here is the E.S. 2015 version where we just use our fancier version of swap and I use LET instead of
far and that's pretty much it.
It's the same exact logic.
It still works.
We still get three.
So I'll leave them both in there.
You can use the one you prefer.
All right.
Next to a quick sort.