All right.
Welcome back.
So in this video.
I mean to quickly run through the pseudo code for quick sort.
But it's pretty short so I'm actually going to just implement it too.
Rather than doing a separate video to show the pseudo code and then implement it just to keep things
a little briefer.
So we have our pivot helper finished we pass in a full array or any array and it's going to take the
first item and figure out where it should go and then put all the smaller items to left all the bigger
items to the right and then return the index.
So that's important that it returns the index because what we're going to do in our quicksort function
is that it's going to call that pivot helper at the beginning with a full array and we'll find out you
know index of four for example is the first pivot point.
And then what we're going to do is recursively call the same thing call quicksort again on the left
side and on the right side of that pivot point.
So imagine we call quicksort with this array.
Well the very first thing that happens is that we find the pivot which is 4 and that is moved to this
index right here.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to then call quicksort on this side from 3 the beginning
up until but not including the pivot because we already figured out this is this is in place we don't
want to read we don't want to move this.
So we're going to sort the array here and here with quicksort.
So the rough logic when the helper returns the updated pivot index we recursively call the pivot helper
on the left side and then on the right side as well.
Now it's important to notice or to point out we're not making new arrays.
This is all happening in place.
We're not making new arrays.
It's happening in the same array.
So our base case it's not quite just to check if the array is item of length or if the array has one
item in it.
It's to check if the sub array has one item in it and what that means is we're always going to be working
with this array for example.
But we're only going to be looking at this portion or this portion where eventually this portion.
And so what we're going to check is not to see if the length of the array is 0 or 1 because this length
will always be the same.
We're not adding and removing elements.
We're going to check if the start point that we're looking at and let's call it left and right if the
left and the right are equal to one another or if the right is less than the left.
So that happens when a suburb has less than two elements.
So I'm just going to implement it.
This is a tough one.
Honestly to just take that pseudo code and try and write it yourself.
I applaud anybody who wants to do it and who tries it out.
But again no expectation on my part that it when I teach this in person it's very rare that anybody
can can implement it right away.
And even once I show the code it can be hard to come up with it again.
And I've already mentioned my struggles with it and how it's just unintuitive for me.
So I'm going to define my function quicksort and I've already done that actually and it's going to take
an array.
And the first thing that we'll do is call.
So let's make a variable called Pivot index and it's just going to be equal to calling pivot with that
array.
But the thing is our pivot.
First of all if we go back it accepts an array a start and an end.
And this is important because the very first time through.
Yeah we want to call it on the whole array but then this recursive function eventually is going to call
it again on this array or this one where we have a different start an endpoint is not just the default
0 up until the end of the array.
So what I'm going to do is in here I'm going to make very an argument called left and set it equal to
zero and another one called rights which is arrayed up like minus one.
And then we're going to pass in a left and right when we call pivot.
So the first time we call this right here the default value for left is zero.
And for right is going to be 0 1 2 3 4 5 6.
So we're calling pivot on this array with 0 6 right.
So then that goes.
Deleted a bracket takes the first item inside of that pivot function and it figures out that this needs
to actually be at index 3.
So it changes the array to look like this and it returns the index of three to us.
So pivot and x is equal to three at this point.
Then we want to repeat the same thing but we want to do it on the left side which basically means from
the left the start point which right now is zero.
So from the left up until the pivot index minus 1.
So we already have this cemented in place.
We want to now sort from here to here.
And then the same thing on the right side.
But we want to go from pivot and X plus one up until the end the.
Right.
So let's do the left first.
So the left side is just a quick sort of the array.
This time we're going to pass in a left and a right on mike down here when we call it the first time
they defaulted to zero and then great length minus one.
This time the left that we're looking at is still going to be the same left that we looked at before
zero.
But next the right where we're going to stop is going to be what we've already discussed the pivot index
minus 1.
So that way we don't include that pivot indexing.
So this is cemented.
We just want to look at that and the same thing on the right side.
Well not quite exactly the same same idea but it's going to be quick sort of the array.
But we're going to start at pivot index plus one.
So that means this is our index.
We want to go from here until the end.
So pivot index plus one Intel.
Right.
So those are the recursive calls.
However if I just run this as it is right now there is a big problem.
It's going to run forever.
So actually if I do this we get our stack overflow maximum call stack size exceeded because there was
never a base case nothing was ever returned something ever stopped this recursive call.
It just keeps going and going and going and going and going.
So where do we want to stop.
We want to stop in this situation or the situation where we've hit a subway that is one element long
and how do we how do we know that and remember that at any point if we looked at array.
It's always the entire array.
We're sorting it in place.
So even this step right here for example array is still the entire array.
But what has changed are left and right because left and right are constantly changing as we're calling
quicksort and recursively because left and right are based off of the pivot index and so we're getting
a new pivot index each time left and right are changing.
And so as these suburbs become smaller left and right get closer together.
So for example here left with zero and right with six then here for example left to zero and right was
to hear left zero right as one now here.
Left and Right are the same so are conditional.
We want to keep doing this code keep running.
If left is less then right and so as soon as they are equal as soon as life is now equal to right that
means that we're looking at one element that makes sense.
Remember that left and right are just pointers inside of this full array.
So it started like this.
And then on one of them the recursive call moved to this and then to this and then it became the same
thing.
And that's when we stop because that means that we've hit the end at least of one of the branches.
So I need my bracket there.
There we go.
OK.
So we're still not quite done.
We have one missing piece which is really important.
We're not returning anything.
We need to return Irais at the very end because remember how these recursive calls work.
This quick sort here is waiting on the results of quick sorting this and quick sorting that.
And then those in turn are waiting on the result of quick sorting this and that.
So we have to return the array here so that we can get it back here and keep going up and then the same
thing on the right side.
So let's save and clear my console Let's see if it works.
No it's not clear zero area.
Let's see if it works now.
And it looks good.
We're getting 1 2 3 4 5 6 9.
Not sure why I chose that and let's just verify Let's mix it up again a little bit put the negative
number in here.
All right.
And it looks like it's working.