All right.
So Leslie let's just step through the call stack visualizing what actually happens with the chrome debugger.
So I have a simpler array with six elements in it and all that we're going to do is execute it so I
put my breakpoint command center and I'm going to step through it.
So first up at the beginning this is our array left is 0 5 right is 5 and the the last index.
That makes sense.
So now we're going to because left this is less than right we're going to call pivot from 0 to 5 on
that array.
So we have to pivot and at the end a fast forwarded we get to swap index is two which has returned and
the array now looks like this where four is an index of two and two in one urn to the left of it and
six and five are to the right of it.
So we return that then we get to this line.
So we have pivot indexes now too.
We just calculated that and the array looks different.
And now we're going to do quick sort of this array.
But from the left until pivot index minus 1.
So if you watch the call stack there's a new call of quicksort on top of it but left to zero and right
is 1.
So now we're looking at these two items.
And so we do the same thing we find the pivot pivot index is 1 so we return 1 and then we move on.
And there's a new quicksort has been added this time we're going from zero to zero of this array which
now left is not less than right.
So what does that mean.
It means that we return the array.
So now this is the array that gets returned back to the previous quick sort which is waiting for this
side the right side.
So now the array looks like this one two and four.
The left side is sorted.
So this quicksort is now waiting to do the right set.
So pivot Index is one.
So this quicksort is the second part it's the right side.
So when we did these two elements we did the left.
Now we do the right thing is if there is no right because right is less than left.
So all that is returned is the array again as you'll see it's unchanged 1 2 4 6 9 5.
We go back to an earlier quicksort that was waiting and this time.
Here we go.
And now we're sorting the right half.
So pivot indexes has which is right here.
And we're going to call sort of sort the array from that pivot index plus 1 meaning index of three.
Up until this the end.
So here we go we call it and you can see that.
Now this time around left is three and right is five.
Now we find the new pivot.
We find that the pivot index is forward.
This is what the array looks like now.
So we found that 6 was our pivot.
We put five left.
Nine is on the right.
We return the value of four.
So back here we now have a new pivot index of four and we're going to take that index.
Now we're going to call quicksort.
On the left side which is really if you look it's from three which is the left until our index was four
minus one.
So three to three as you can see here.
And what does that mean.
Well left is less than right.
Notice the new quick stack on the stack.
Quicksort on the stack left is less than right.
So we are going to return that array as it is and then we get to our next one quick sort.
On the right side which also is going to be sorted because you'll see that left his five right S-5.
That means that we need to just return the array which is what we do and that takes us back to the next
quicksort which is waiting to return array which now has been updated.
So we return the array and then we're on our final.
This is the original call where now we have both sides have finished left and right and we're finally
going to return array.
And here's the return value.
And there we go 1 2 4 5 6 9.
Congratulations on not quitting this video early if you made it through.
Is a lot but that's the basics of quicksort.