Welcome back.
Our last video on quicksort.
Good riddance if you ask me.
We're going to talk about the time complexity and space complexity of quicksort.
So first off notice that best and average are both 0 of and Lagann which is the same as merge.
And if we look at why let's look at best case for example.
So here's our array and you have to make a composition and then another decomposition.
Another one just like we did with merge sort where the pattern here as end grows we have to make log
and log base to an decompositions.
So as we have more elements for example we had 32 elements we have to make 5 decompositions slice it
in half five times.
If we are and this is the best case remember we're going to see the worst case in just a moment.
If we have I don't know what's next 64.
We would have to make six decompositions so that grows at rate of the rate of fly again.
But then each level each decomposition that we make we have to make all of any comparisons per decomposition.
So that's happening when we're pivoting remembering or finding the pivot we're comparing to every other
element one time.
So that is how we get analog and it's very similar.
It's the same reason really why we got.
And again with merge sort.
Now let's talk about worst case.
So with our algorithm our pivot function it takes the first item as the pivot always.
Now that's problematic if our data is already sorted.
So here's the worst case for our current quicksort.
If we have this array and we're trying to sort it and of course our code doesn't know that it's sorted.
So we take this in and the very first thing we do is find the first item and use that as the pivot.
Well we compare it to every item in that array but nothing is less than that.
So our entire the next array is that the composition really only gave us a single item.
We have this entire Subah array left.
So every time we go through each decomposition is only one item that we're pivoting on.
And so everything moves to the right side with our current algorithm and we have to keep going and going
and going over and over and over because we're only taking the first item and it's already sorted.
And then for each one of those so that is an decompositions the worst case with our current setup is
of and decompositions and on each level each decomposition we have to make up and comparisons which
results in 0 of end squared quadratic time for the worst case.
So basically the problem arises when the pivot is chose when the pivot that is chosen is the minimum
element.
Every single time or the pivot is always the maximum element.
So to fix that in this example at least if we're dealing with a sorted array we could get around it
by instead of pivoting around the first item no matter what pivot around a random item just pick anything
in here doesn't matter.
Just pick a random item or try and pick the middle element every time.
And that way even if we have a sorted array we can avoid the problem.
But of course there's still a chance that if we pick the middle element every time it's possible that
the raise is unsorted and it's supposed to be in random order or we think it is.
But somehow we're always picking the minimum every time we can never avoid that worst case entirely
because the way the algorithm works if you're pivoting around the minimum or the maximum repeatedly
that's going to be quadratic time.
But we can just do our best to avoid the chances of constantly picking the minimum or the maximum.
Which is why you would do a random number or the median instead of the first element every single time.
But by doing that what we did picking the first element every time it allows me to illustrate this problem
the worst case scenario.
So take a deep breath that was quick sort as a lot I know.
Again I do not feel any pressure to be able to write that on your own.
It's really more about understanding how it works.
Being able to walk through if you had a whiteboard could you write down the value of the array each
time through.
Could you diagram out the recursion.
That's the sort of thing that I hope you took away from this.
Get moving on.