OK.
Welcome back.
In this video we're going to talk about instance methods as well as static methods or class methods.
So to start instance methods are something we're going to use all the time in the course much more frequently
than the second type of methods we'll see instance methods are methods that basically don't want to
say they live on a particular instance but they they provide functionality that pertains to a single
instance of in our case our case student or when we talk about a singly linked list.
We will define many instance methods on those particular instances.
Think of for example when we're working with an array.
If I make a new array.
So let's just call this array.
I don't know.
Data equals and I'm going to do this this syntax and pass in some numbers.
Here we go.
So we now have our array called data.
If I do something like data dot push This is a method that acts on the individual instance of the array
which is data.
So an array is a pattern and we can define individual array objects based on that pattern.
And so this is one instance and push is a single method.
I was going to do something like sort and I realized that I made a sorted array so it will do push and
push it 20.
And about 99 and there we go.
Now we look at data and it's changed.
So we work with the instance methods all the time or the rough idea of instance methods in Javascript.
So we're going to do the same thing now on our student.
We're going to create a method or two methods that correspond to individual instances.
So not things that that work on the class level but the things that are relevant to individual instances.
So for example here's one called full name.
Again not very useful but it returns a string.
Your full name is.
And then inside that string we're adding in the first name and this last name.
And again this refers to the individual instance.
So whoever is calling this whether it's first student or second student will get a different output
assuming that they have different first and last names.
So if we go back to add this method in right here and now if I execute my code I have first student
and second student if I try first student.
There's no grade for either of those.
That's OK.
So let's do first student dot and now we call full name and I need to if I just leave it at this it
returns to me.
It's basically saying yes I know there is a method called that before to execute it.
There you go.
Your full name is called Steal.
If I do second student full name I get your full name is Blue Steel.
So these are silly examples of what we're doing here when we get to a linked list though we will define
a reverse instance method or a push instance method things that will actually work on individual instances.
For example in the next section here's our singly linked list class.
We have our constructor but then we have a push instance method a shift in unshipped get insert.
What else reverse remove.
Those are all.
Oh and pop.
Those are all individual instance methods that work on a single linked list on a single singly linked
lists.
It's confusing.
So we have to instantiate a length list in order to use those just like we can't if we're trying to
pop from an array.
We have to have an individual array to pop from.
We don't just pop from nothing.
We need an instance.
So let's extend this class.
Let's add it in a different method that actually updates the value of one of these properties.
So let's say in our school students can only be late three times.
So let's create a new property.
I'm going to call this absences too hard to spell.
Let's just call it at least in the U.S. we call them tardies.
I don't know how universal that word is but we're going to call it tardies and it's going to be set
to zero whenever we create a new student by default.
They've never been late but now we're going to have a method called Mark late and all that it does is
it adds 1 to tardies so need to access this stuff tardies which is referencing the individual student
instance his or her tardies.
And I'm just going to add one physical one like that so that updates it and then let's return a string.
Or we could just return the number of tardies But let's return a string that says let's do full name.
This does still this tell us to stop first name the last name has been late and then in here let's add
in the number of times and we're not going to pluralized correctly or anything we'll just say this dot
tardies like that.
So blue still has been late three times.
OK so if we save this now and we instantiate a new student we're not using grades so I guess I could
pass one in here so I'm in first grade or first year.
And blue is in second year.
Now I'm going to run this code and if we look at students now.
So let's look at first student.
Now if I access Mark late I have a method available to me and if I execute it I don't need to pass anything
in code still has been late one times and if I look at first student tardies Now I should have earlier
looked at it it was 0 0 0 and make this a bit larger.
I've now marked it and I can do the same thing one more time.
And how about two more times.
So now I have been late.
Three times.
We don't have any logic in there.
I mean we could add in a little conditional to check if it's greater than 3 then we expel you.
Why don't we do that really quickly.
So we'll add one to tardies and then we'll just add a conditional if this does tardies is greater than
or equal to 3 return.
You are expelled.
So if I rerun my code instantiate or let's go back to 1st student and do Mark late the first time the
second time and the third time you are expelled and every other time you're expelled.
OK that's good enough for us.
The last thing we'll talk about with an instance method is to finding one that takes some sort of argument.
Let's also add in an array here called scores.
It will start as empty because there are no tests at the beginning when we create a student but then
we're going to create a method and our first one this will be super easy we'll just call it add score
and it will take in a new score and then we'll just do this dot.
And what we call this test scores push score so this will just add the score on to the end.
Now yes you could just you could access this directly but we'll talk about that in a second.
So this stops scores up push and then let's return the stop scores.
So if I rerun my code and I now look at let's do second student this time.
Second student scores.
It's empty and I could just do manually just push on from here.
There's nothing stopping me from doing that but it's more conventional to define a method that will
do this to prevent.
There's nothing stopping anybody from manually changing any of these properties.
But the conventional way of writing a class is that you assume that a developer or somebody will use
a method that you put there.
So we're going to use this instead as our interface to the data rather than we would ask someone not
to directly change our data.
Instead go through some sort of method.
So we have ADD score.
So I'll do second student up and score and then here what do we want to add but say the score is blue
is pretty good.
He has a 92 and let's do one more this time in 87 and now if we look at second student debt scores you
can see where we were returning it already.
But we have two scores in there.
So the last thing that I want to do is create something called calculate average method and just need
to take any arguments in and it should return the average of the scores in the individual student's
scores array.
So we'll have this study scores and we're going to need to some of them all up and then we'll need to
divide them by the the length of the array So to calculate the sum of all the elements first.
You could use Reduce like this and I'm going to make a separate variable here so let's call this sum
and then we're going to return some.
Divided by this scores dot length.
So this logic is just here to reduce it's going to take each item and you can add it together and create
a total So each number in that this dot scores array save it to the sum variable and then we return
some divided by the Dutch course length.
Let's test it out so first student dot scores and a way we want to use add score to 98 and then I did
poorly and I got a 76 and then I did let's just leave it at those to be easier to tell if it's working
actually.
So now if we do calculate average There we go 87.
Now if I add a different score in C I do really well get 100.
Now our average goes up and we could round it and all that.
OK.
So although I want to show here is the basics of defining class with instance methods.
So we can define a simple instance method that just returned a string using some properties we can find
when a little more complex that manipulate one of the existing properties on our instance or we can
do something like calculate average which is going to you know have a little more math than that.
But the idea is that all of these operate on individual instances.
So next we'll take a brief look at creating a class method which we won't do very often but I should
put it in here just because we're talking about classes in East 20:15 at this point and it's covered.
OK.
See you then.