Welcome back.
In this video we're going to talk about class methods.
So we talked about creating a class or defining the pattern writing a constructor method.
But the new keyword we talked about instance methods.
Now we're talking about a second type of method you can add to eight years 2015 class called a class
method where we use the static keyword in front of the method definition.
So this allows us to do is to find methods or functionality that is pertinent to classes but not necessarily
to individual instances of a class.
So this is actually not that common and most of what we do in this course is going to be around instance
methods for our data structures.
But if we go to the docs on MDI and again I like this explanation the static keyword defines a static
method for a class.
Static methods are called without instantiating their class and cannot be called through a class instance.
They're often used to create utility functions for an application.
So the example that I added here which is not a complete method by the way I didn't write the actual
functionality but the idea is that we can have a method called enroll students and this is a class method
you could pass in multiple students in an array.
For example like we have down here and this would go and maybe send emails to each of their each of
their associated email addresses or something like that.
The idea is that this has to do.
It's more like a utility function I like that explanation.
It's not related to a single individual student where we are using data from that instance like we were
here.
We're using the name first name and the last name of each individual student.
And so we would call this first student dot for name but this enroll students which again is not fully
defined.
What it does is not related to a particular instance.
It's just part of the class in general and some some overall functionality some utility function that
we want and the way we call that is student with a capital S..
So back here in our code if I try and add a class method down here we'll just call 1.
Enroll students which is fine but we're not going to actually enroll in the.
We're just going to return a string and rolling students.
Oh boy.
OK.
So just the most basic possible class method here and what I want to show is that if we instantiate
these first student I can't call first student dot what we call it enroll students.
I'll use a capital E which I did not mean to do.
But either way it's not going to work.
I need to do student.
Enroll students and need parents.
And now we can execute that method.
So this is functionality that is not relevant to an individual instance but we still want it as part
of the Student class it has to do with students in some way or the helper method a utility method and
with students it's kind of hard to show an actual example that makes sense.
So we actually have a second example here.
This is one that I took from the documentation on MDA.
So we have a class called point.
So imagine a point on a what's it called a cartesian plane an x y coordinate basically.
And if we're working in this this coordinate system each point has an x value and a Y so we can initialize
new ones down here 5 come five 10 come a 10.
But then there's some some utility method that we want like distance calculating the distance between
two points which it's been a while probably for me definitely for some of you probably since you've
had to use this or maybe you never learned it.
There's a distance formula where this is the math you need to do to figure out the point between two
or the distance between two points which it has to do with the forming a right triangle and the hypotenuse
of that triangle.
Anyway let's not go into it but this is the math for it.
So you could make this into a class method.
It doesn't make sense to have the distance method B on an individual instance.
So for example I'm going to run this.
So I have P1 and P2 if I wanted to find the distance between P1 and P2 rather than putting you know
how would I do that P1 dot distance.
And then I pass in to I mean that could work.
You could implement it that way.
But this is more a utility function so we make it a class method.
So instead I'm going to call Point Capital P point distance and then I pass in P1 and P2.
And this is the distance between the two.
Does that make sense why you would maybe organize it this way.
Of course all of Object-Oriented Programming all of everything we're doing with this class syntax.
It's just about making things organized better or easier to understand and more logical.
So that's pretty much it two class methods all that you do is put the static keyword in front of them
and that makes it a class method which means that you no longer call it on an individual method or on
an individual instance you call it on the class itself like point or earlier in our example we had student
capital S dot enroll students.
OK.
Versus instance method to call on an individual instance like second student or one dot.
Well we don't have any instance methods in this example but if we did we would call them on P1 or P2
and so on.
So as I mentioned earlier this is how we'll be using classes ourself.
Well mainly be defining a class some data structure class binary search tree class doubly linked list
inside of it we have our constructor all the default values are the initial properties we need are singly
linked list or are binary search tree to have and then we'll have a bunch of instance methods as I showed
in the last video.
Some of these these data structures will look at might have 10 different methods that we define and
it's going to be pretty rare that we're going to use any static methods but I felt that this would be
incomplete if I didn't at least explain their existence if I only mentioned instance methods.
It would be disingenuous.
Is not the right word.
It would be incomplete if me so I needed to show that they exist.
But most of what we're going to do is going to follow this pattern.
Class data structure whatever it is called Our constructor and then a bunch of instance methods that
make it all work.
And lastly remember that the word the key word this behaves a bit different than normal.
If there is a normal it always behaves differently but the way that it behaves instead of just 20:15
classes that instead of any instance method or the constructor the keyword this refers to the object
created from that individual class the actual instance.
And we've already mentioned that but I just put a slide in here just to to make that extra clear.
So to recap everything here.
Classes are blueprints that one created make objects known as instances.
Classes are created or instantiated with the new keyword.
The constructor function is a special function that gets run when the class is instantiated.
When you run new student the student constructor is run instance methods can be added to classes similar
to methods and objects and class methods can be added with a static keyword.
All right.
Now that we get all of that out the way.
Now we can look forward to actually diving into our first data structure are going to start off with
singly linked lists so that's up next.
We'll be defining our first class sivin.