Ladies and gentlemen may I please have your undivided attention for an important announcement about
this Course's content.
I'm very excited to announce that we have hit a major turning point in this course from this point forward.
We will be discussing the structure of the data structure data structure structure data structures.
Well as you may have heard we're talking about data structures which it really is a big turning point
in this course.
We've spent a lot of time talking about many different topics different types of algorithms approaches
for problem solving Big O notation recursion sorting searching a lot of stuff.
But now from here on out everything we cover will be a new type of data structure or related to a new
data structure that we learn.
So when this video and this section there's a couple of things that we have to get out of the way before
we dive into the many data structures we're going to cover this will be quick but I want to talk about
why you should care what the data structures are why there's so many of them.
Like are they how do they differ.
What's the point of learning these.
And then also we're going to learn about.
Yes 2015.
The class syntax to create classes in javascript which is how we'll be defining our own data structures
from here on out.
So if you already know about that you can skip it but it's like 10 minutes of content across three videos.
If you do want to check it out see how it works.
OK so I've mentioned we're covering a ton of structures binary search trees Qs singly linked lists undirected
unweighted graphs.
Talking about binary heaps priority queues at in Pathet on here directed graphs hash tables double linked
lists stacks.
And there's actually some more that I didn't put on here.
What the heck is going on why are there so many.
Why am I teaching them.
And what do they all do.
So we're not going to get into what each one does individually here but just know we will implement
each one of these as their own class.
So we'll define it from scratch.
Sort of like if we were defining our own array or our own object although it's a little bit more it's
a little higher level than that.
The structures we're going to build are a little bit more complex.
So let's start with what all of these have in common.
What did they do.
What makes something a data structure.
We've kind of touched on this early early on we talked about arrays and objects.
Those are data structures as well as all of these things.
These are data structures and there's hundreds dozens of very well-known ones and hundreds of maybe
thousands of very nuanced niche variants of data structures all of them.
What they have in common is that they are collections of values.
They contain the relationships among those values and the functionality or operations that can be applied
to the data.
So think of an array an array holds many values.
It also contains the relationships between those values.
The order in the case of an array and arrays come with all sorts of built in methods and functionality
ways of interacting with them adding to them removing push pop that sort of thing but also sorting reversing
whatever other functionality there is.
So we'll define our own structures that fit this exact same mold when we define a singly linked list.
That's the first one we cover.
It will not only hold data but it also puts them in obviously in a particular way where there's a relationship
between each piece of data.
It's not just randomly deciding how to store it.
There is a particular pattern or relationship so it holds a collection of data and we'll be writing
a bunch of methods.
We'll add our own push our own pop our own reverse what else.
There's probably seven different methods we add to a singly linked list and they all help us interact
with the singly linked list.
Same thing when we talk about graphs and trees and heaps and everything else we do from here on out.
We'll be defining a class called Whatever our data structure of the day is.
And then on top of that we add a bunch of functionality.
So why are there so many.
That's a good question.
It comes down to the fact that different data structures excel at different things.
So some of them are very specialized but some of them are pretty general commonly use things like an
array or an object in javascript which is why those come for free.
Right.
We don't have to implement those on our own but if we're trying to work with a red and black tree or
I don't know an undirected graph or something like that you usually don't get that for free in a programming
language.
You have to go and implemented but that doesn't mean they're not useful.
It just means that they are very useful in special cases and you have to you have to be able to know
when to use one of those you have to know about them in order to write one.
If that makes sense.
So they all do different things.
And as we go through this course you'll see when certain ones make sense and we talk about usages and
examples and real world use cases as well as interview problems.
So you might see a data structure like this.
This is a visual representation of an array.
Here's another one will look at a length list.
This is a singly linked list will also talk about doubly linked lists.
Here we have a hash table.
These are just visual representations but you can see these are all different relationships between
the pieces of data but they all are storing numbers just totally different ways of storing the same
type of data.
This here is a binary heap.
It's also a tree.
This is a binary search tree.
Slightly different rules.
This is a graph in this case and unweighted undirected graph.
This is an unweighted directed graph similar but different.
So the point is all of these do the same thing at the end of the day they store data.
But their behavior the relationships between the data and their functionality the methods we get to
act upon them are very different.
So the next question is why should I care and why should you care.
Well there's a lot of time devoted to data structures in this course and there's a couple of reasons.
First of all the more time you spend as a developer the more likely you'll need to use one of these
more advanced data structures.
Usually there's a time and every developer's life when using an array for every single possible problem
just doesn't cut it.
You might need something more efficient.
You might need something to express a different relationship.
You might be working with more complicated data that isn't linear and you needed another way of storing
it.
There's many situations where this can come up or you might be working with an API or a library that
gives you like a database for example that returns a graph graph representation and you need to understand
what the heck a graph is.
In order for that to make sense.
Also another reason worth knowing that you've already worked with many data structures probably unknowingly.
So if you have ever worked with the Dom in javascript you've manipulated and interacted with a tree.
That's just one example.
But as we go through through the different structures all constantly point out existing use cases things
that you're probably familiar with with each data structure.
And then finally a really important one of course especially in this context interviews.
So these data structures are the fodder of many an interview.
It's worth knowing alone just for that.
But I don't want to make that the focus of all these data structures.
These exist for a reason they're taught for a reason.
And it's not just a random hard interview questions though it can definitely help with that and a lot
of people like to ask data structure questions.
Can you reverse a singly length list.
Can you implement a priority.
Q Can you balance a binary tree.
All that stuff is worth knowing.
But at the same time these data structures are useful in the real world.
If you never interview they're still worth knowing.
So we'll come back to why as we visit each individual structure an important note.
A lot of people ask this What is the best one which one should I know.
The answer is there is no one best one.
They all do different things right.
They each have specific talents if you will.
Some of them are more general just commonly use like an array but some of them are very specific.
But they all excel in different environments.
Otherwise why bother having them at all.
Why bother learning them.
I wouldn't be teaching them if there was one data structure to rule them all.
One you could master and then call it a day.
So they all excel in different situations.
For example maybe you're working with map or location data.
You're writing a GPS application like Google Maps which should be a huge undertaking but let's simplify
it even further and say you're trying to write code that will route you to the nearest gas station or
something like that that has the cheapest deals whatever you might want to use a graph a graph would
make sense for this.
And we talked about graphing data we talked about finding the shortest path between points on a graph
representing GPS data and location data using a graph.
So that's one situation.
It would be very difficult to represent a map using a single array.
What if you need an ordered list like an array but you need fast inserts in removals at the beginning
and the end.
So if you watched early on we talked about arrays they do not do well when you insert at the beginning
or remove from the beginning.
Everything has to be indexed.
So maybe you have a huge data set and you have to have it ordered it take a million data points and
you are always inserting and removing from both ends.
Then you might not want to use an array thats where length lists could come in handy.
So knowing about a linked list would help you in that situation.
Are you web scraping nested aged DML.
Are you writing some sort of app that is scraping data from.
I don't know airline's Web sites or hotel web sites.
And you're interacting with that aged him now.
Or maybe you're using a library to help you.
Well it's almost guaranteed to give you the data in a tree.
I have another example I need to write a scheduler so this might be a bit more nuanced than Timo But
if you're writing an app that that has tasks that are scheduled and you need to find what's the highest
priority task to handle at any given point you might use a binary heap.
So we'll talk about priority queues and primary heaps in that section.
OK so enough of those examples but hopefully that makes it clear these all excel in different situations.
There is no one data structure to rule them all.
Definitely go through all of them.
But along with that a quick message there's a ton of content here from here on out.
This data structure stuff gets dense and I highly recommend you don't just go one section at a time
and sit through the night or even do it all in a day or two.
It's a lot.
I beg you please.
It will burn you out.
This is the content that in my classes we do over two weeks of an intensive bootcamp where it's 10 hours
a day sometimes eight hours but usually 10 hours a day.
We do two weeks that ten full days to cover this data structures content and those are people who have
been you know in this classroom for 12 or 10 weeks at that point.
So they're relatively skilled developers and they are expecting a tough time for the last two weeks.
So I beg you don't try to fly through this in a night or two or even a single week.
It's a lot.
For example watch the singly link section.
Take a break.
I mean take an hour two hours three hours an entire day.
Come back after the weekend.
Whatever it is.
And then do double length lists don't do them one right after the other.
I mean it's up to you of course but that's my recommendation.
There's a lot there.
OK.
And one last little note.
Please pay attention to the prerequisites listed for each section.
So a lot of these data structures build upon one another or in some of the later sections like when
we talk about graphs we talked about a particular algorithm called Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm.
And in the algorithm itself we actually use another data structure from earlier in the course called
the binary heap.
So if you skipped the binary heap section and go right to the graph section you will be missing some
important information.
So I made it at the beginning of every single section is a text lecture that explains what you need
to know for each section.
So you don't have to go through them in a linear order but they are in an order that makes sense.
And if you do want to learn them all just start at the beginning singly linked lists and go all the
way up through graphs.
Ok I'm done with all these little announcements and pep talks and whatever else this has been.
So welcome to the new section of the new sort of portion of the course devoted to data structures.
There's a lot of important content here some very useful stuff but there's a lot of stuff in general.
So again take your time the first thing we're going to do before we actually implement our first data
structure the singly linked list.
We need to just discuss East 2015 class syntax we're defining a new class for every data structure we
learn.
So if you already know how to do that skip the next two video or the next three videos after this one.
But if you don't I highly recommend you start there because we use this syntax.
The classic keyword in every single video from here on out.
Ok I'm done I promise.
Welcome to data structures.
Let's get going.