Hey welcome back.
So as I've already mentioned this section marks a significant turning point in the course.
We're now going to focus our attention on a bunch of data structures so classic data structures like
singly linked list double-D linked lists stacks CU's.
We're also going to implement more complicated ones like trees and binary search trees graphs but along
the way not only are we going to learn about these these data structures and talk about why they matter
and how they're useful.
We're also going to implement them.
Javascript doesn't come with any of these pre-built.
And so the point is that we're going to go through and write our own.
But in order to do that we need to take advantage of the east 2015 class syntax and Javascript.
So depending on how familiar familiar you are with javascript and with object oriented programming you
may know that javascript doesn't really support O.P. or object oriented programming.
However with the 2015 a new class keyword was was introduced.
We're going to take advantage of that throughout this course because it makes it really easy and simple
for us to define our data structures.
So if you're already familiar with it if you feel good about writing using the class keyword writing
constructors instantiating new instances using your class in javascript then you could skip this section
but if you need some review over it then or if you've never learned it before.
I think that this will help you out.
Also if you've never worked with any sort of Object-Oriented language before or you've never defined
any sort of patterns whether it's in javascript or in Python or Ruby or any other language then this
is going to be kind of a lot to take in right away.
But I recommend that you watch this video you try some of the examples and then you start out with a
singly linked list which is up next and see how that goes.
But take it slow if you.
If you've never written a class before so first our objectives were going to start by talking about
what classes are going to understand how javascript implements the idea of classes.
Bolded because it's not quite true.
Object Oriented Programming.
Well different.
Define terms like abstraction encapsulation and polymorphism and then we'll use as 20:15 classes to
implement data structures.
OK so first up what the heck is a class.
So in general a class is like a blueprint for creating objects with pre-defined properties and methods.
So we'll learn how to make a singly linked lists are doubly linked list.
We define a pattern for a doubly linked list but then we can actually instantiate many objects many
individual linked lists using that blueprint using our class.
It's sort of like arrays and Javascript although it's not quite the same.
We have a pattern for for an array and arrays come with a bunch of methods and things that they can
do.
But we have to first instantiate a new array and then we can get access to all of those so there's an
array.
It's not technically a class but you can think of it as sort of a blueprint and then we can instantiate
objects based off of that blueprint.
So as I kind of hinted at javascript doesn't really have classes.
If you go to the documentation on M.D n Mozilla developer network you can see up top on the this is
there are classes main page javascript classes introduced and as 20:15 are primarily syntactical sugar
over javascript's existing prototype based inheritance.
The class syntax does not introduce a new Object-Oriented inheritance model to Javascript.
So this is saying this is basically javascript.
It has never really been truly object oriented.
It takes advantage of something called prototype based inheritance or prototype CL and all that happens
with East 2015 is that this class syntax was introduced but it's not changing how things work behind
the scenes.
It's just an easier way to work and to define class like structures.
So if you are not familiar with either those with object oriented programming or prototype based inheritance
then that probably made zero sense.
But all that will say is that it does help to know that technically this is not true.
Object Oriented Programming.
But that's not going to hinder us in any way.
We just have to it's good to know that.
Let's just leave it at that.
So next why do we need to learn this.
Well as I've already mentioned we're going to implement tons of data structures as classes.
So any time we build We're going to learn how to build a tree or a graph or a singly length list.
We're going to define a class define a pattern in javascript that we can then instantiate individual
lists from.
For example here's a little spoiler.
Here's two classes we defined for our singly linked list so you can see we have the class keyword constructor
will go into all this detail.
But here is the class for the singly linked list is kind of long.
There's a lot of methods we add in there.
This is a blueprint though this doesn't actually represent any data.
There's no there's no instance of a list.
We still have to instantiate one.
Here's another really short class called a node and the singly linked list class utilizes the Node class
inside of it.
So that's all I'll say about it for now.
But this is just a single example of many that we're going to see and implement on our own.
So I think that I'll leave off here.
Just know that classes are what we're going to use throughout the rest of the course.
Coming up next a bunch of data structures in the next video though are going to introduce the syntax
for classes.
So if you know what you can skip it take get some review.
But if you don't know it I highly recommend that you just sit through the next couple of videos.
I know it's not on an data structures just yet but it's really important because we're going to use
this.
OK I'll shut up.