All right.
Welcome back.
Now we're going to actually take a look at how you declare a class in East 2015.
Here's a really simple example.
So we have a class called Student conventionally.
Classes should start with a capital letter that should be OK.
So you've got student here so this is a pattern for a student and every student is just going to have
a first name and a last name.
That's it.
Obviously this is something we don't need a class to do.
Yeah I mean you don't really need a class to do any of the things that we're going to do in this course.
It's just a nice way of organizing your code.
We could use just a plain old object just key value pairs.
But instead we're going to create this blueprint so that our code is easier to work with easier to understand
and just nicer better organized.
So we define our class student and then we have our curly braces but then we have to have this thing
called a constructor.
So it has to be named constructor and it's a special method that will be used to instantiate new student
instances.
So we pass in when we when we create a new student we're going to provide a first name and a last name
and then all that we do in here is set this first name equal to whatever the first name was and this
dot last name equal to whatever the last name was that were that was passed in.
So this is just a way of saying that whatever is passed in when a new student is created assigned those
two properties to the individual object the individual student.
So the next to actually create a new instance we have to find the pattern here.
The blueprint.
This doesn't make any students we have to use the new keyword.
So this is how we instantiate objects from a class.
So we say new student.
And then we pass in first name and last name.
So we have two cold steel and blue steel.
And each of those is going to basically create a new student object based off of this pattern where
first name will be set to Colt last name will be steel in the first one and then the second one first
and then will be blue in last name will be still so if we just copy this over quickly here and let's
expand on this and let's add in first name last name and let's also add in year or grade level or whatever
you want to call it.
But the idea is that it's just going to be you know how far it's in school the student is.
So let's say that our school goes from zero to four it's high school in the U.S. at least there's four
years of high school.
So I'm going to say this year equal to year.
Now this name can be anything I want just like this can.
So if I call this instead grade that's fine.
This grade will be set to whatever is passed in when a new student is instantiated.
OK.
So just on under-tone if I run this nothing happens.
But now I'm able to instantiate questions and nothing happens.
No students are created.
We've just defined a pattern.
We're basically saying All right here's this thing that now we have this blueprint we can actually go
and make new students we've made like a mole's like get a factory you make a mold for a part that's
not actually making the part.
You just are ready to make the parts.
Now I don't know if that's very helpful.
So if I did something like this new student and then I pass in some data so let's say let's have a new
student named not email it and M. I don't know.
Katz and he is a he's in year 3.
Sure you can see what I get back is just javascript object that has a first name set to M-L a meal grade
is 3 and last name is cats notice year is nowhere to be found the actual name year because we just called
it grade instead.
This is just a placeholder just like any argument in function.
OK.
Now if I say that to a variable let's call it.
Let's just call it person.
Now this then terrible at this.
Let's go with a mill like this.
I can now access for example first name.
So nothing revolutionary at this point.
This is just a nice way of organizing our code.
But I just want to make that really clear that when we define a class it doesn't do anything on its
own.
We have to actually instantiate using the new keyword instances of that class.
So we will eventually have a class called let's say tree for example or singly linked lists defining
the class is just the pattern that then we are still going to have to say new tree or new singly linked
lists and then do something with that call a method on it.
So now if I run this we have two students by the way if you're just skipping to this I use command enter
to run my snippets.
You can also click here or wherever you're doing this.
But I realize that might have looked like magic I hit command enter.
So now we have a first student and we have second student and notice that grade is undefined and all
of them.
And also if I wanted to I could now define a greater updated grade to be C for second student greatest
for now if we look at second student greatest set to 4.
So you might be wondering what the this key word is referring to here.
So often the key word this is a source of confusion pretty much always in javascript for many students
and it changes its meaning changes depending on its context.
But in this situation when we're inside of a constructor or another instance method We'll talk about
instance methods in the next video but when we're inside of a constructor let's just say that for now
this refers to the individual instance of the class.
So the individual student.
So this refers to this student or this student depending on which one we're talking about.
So when we instantiate a new student let's say let Kitty equal new student and her name is Kitty cat
and she's in grade 1.
I like that when I do this.
What it is saying is that on this new instance of student this specific instance its first name should
be equal to whatever is passed in.
Kitty its last name should be equal to whatever last name is passed in which is cat and this up grade.
It's individual grade should be set to whatever the value of year is.
Hit enter.
And now we have our kitty defined.
OK.
So that's the basics of the class syntax the idea of the constructor.
I guess I never win over the fact that we're never explicitly calling the constructor right we're not
saying student Dom constructor or something.
There's some magic behind the scenes some syntactic sugar that we use the new keyword but the constructor
method is going to be executed or data will basically be patched on through and our constructor will
run when we instantiate a new student or whatever our class is.
OK so next we're going to talk about defining methods on our classes.