It there.
Welcome back.
So this section as well as the next section they're really one massive section but a split in half just
so I don't end up with this one behemoth section.
But both of them have to do with algorithms and problem solving patterns or strategies game plans approaches
whatever you want to call it.
Basically you're faced with a tough challenge some code a problem you have to solve and you don't know
how to do it right off the bat.
What are the steps you can take to make it solvable.
And it really falls into two categories.
This first section is more about the basic approach to solving a problem you don't know how to solve.
Steps you can take things you can do to make it easier.
And then the second section that comes after this is about specific blueprints or archetypes little
strategies you can keep in your back pocket that help solve a lot of problems so it's more code specific
in the next section.
But both are equally important.
But first objectives really quickly we're going to start by defining what an algorithm is in like 10
seconds.
Devise a plan to solve algorithms and then compare and contrast problem solving patterns including things
like frequency counters to pointer problems and divide and conquer.
So that's coming up in the next section.
Like I said this section is really more focused on devising a plan sort of an approach to solving problems
and then afterwards we'll dive into specific named patterns.
OK quickly what is an algorithm.
Well in today's world it's like the trendiest of the trendy buzzwords.
I was watching an ad the other day for was on Instagram and there was an electric toothbrush and they
were advertising you know this finely tuned algorithm for the vibrations and the toothbrush.
It's a word that you can't escape.
Really it just means a process or set of steps to accomplish a certain task rather underwhelming definition.
But that's all that it is.
So when we say algorithm I mean we could be talking about you know a set of mathematical steps that
we need to do to solve a problem.
We could be talking about Facebook's algorithm that you know suggests certain ads to you or Google's
algorithm when you search for something where it's a matter of you know 50 developers working together.
It's probably vastly underestimating it maybe 100 developers who are working on search result algorithms
over you know 10 plus years.
So it really runs the gamut.
But at its core it's just a set of steps to accomplish a task.
So that could be something simple like you know calculate the first 100 prime numbers.
There's many ways of doing that or it could be something like you know Instagram's algorithm that used
to just show you results in chronological order and then they decided to change it.
And now you miss a million posts by your friends anyway.
Why do you need to know this.
Well hopefully this is sort of clear already.
Almost everything that you do in programming involves some sort of algorithm whether it's super basic
things that you're doing your or you're building a complex application.
You have to make these decisions you have to come up with a way of solving problems.
So this stuff is super important but I do want to sort of constrict our definition of algorithm for
now.
We're not going to learn how to you know solve Instagram timeline algorithm.
We're focusing on really a much narrower category and that is things that come up in interviews.
So this is probably why a lot of you are taking this course.
Yes this stuff is good to know especially this section applies to a lot of programming pretty much everything.
But it also really applies to interview settings.
Being able to you know sit in a office somewhere you've never been an answer tough questions or solve
a problem you've never seen before.
So just to reiterate this stuff comes up all the time in interviews.
Oh boy how many of these do get interviews every go.
So how do you get better at this stuff.
You know a lot of people think this is just inherently people or good or bad at it.
And I've seen that a lot when I'm teaching some.
Some people are just naturally better at solving problems.
I would say or they're more find their brain works right out of the box solving problems but that doesn't
mean that it's hopeless for people who struggle.
I've seen it many many times in my classes.
During our interview weeks towards the end where we're doing computer science and sort of what this
course is based off with some people pick it up much faster.
Other people have to work towards that just like anything in life honestly.
But I've seen many people turn it around and struggled during our first mock interview and have a panic
attack basically in the middle of our you know conference room and then a week or two later.
Brand new problem they've never seen before.
Equally as difficult.
They're able to sit there calmly and solve it using some of the steps I lay out here.
So how do you improve.
There's two things have already mentioned this first devise a plan for solving problems.
So this is more of a non-technical.
It still is technical but it's more about how do you approach the problem strategies for breaking it
down.
There's a couple of steps that I read it and then afterwards master common problem solving patterns.
So a lot of algorithms especially in interviews a lot of these problems that come up can be broken into
sort of different categories.
And if you can identify some of those categories there are some steps you can take in your code.
Some recipes you can keep that you can pull out and that will help you solve the algorithm or the challenge.
We're starting off with this first one problem solving strategies.
So this section is focused on a simple foolproof magical miraculous failsafe approach to solving every
problem ever which can be yours for only two payments of nine hundred ninety nine dollars ninety nine
cents.
Call now.
No not really.
This is not at all what the section is about.
This is just laying down a set of steps that can help you.
But of course it is not going to solve the problem for you.
It's not foolproof but I've seen many people like you already mentioned turned their problem solving
approaches around many people who have gone from feeling really apprehensive about solving new problems
and lock up in the middle of an interview setting and giving them sort of a game plan a set of steps
that you can keep in your mind it's a concrete thing to refer back to.
Step by step what you should do.
And I've seen it help a lot of people so it's not miraculous it's not magical or foolproof but still
is pretty helpful.
So what are those steps.
Well first understand the problem.
So each of these bullet points will get its own video.
Understand the problem.
Explore concrete examples.
Break it down.
Solve slash simplify the problem and then look back and refactor.
So these are the different videos we're going to have in this section.
Each of these points there's a lot more behind it and it's all.
Each one is part of this plan.
This game plan this recipe for solving a challenge or a problem.
So that's where we're going here.
And then the next section is on more concrete archetypes for algorithms.
But we're starting here.
All right.
So problem solving hopefully.
You know why this is important.
Don't make me go back to this slide.
It's too many button presses interviews.
Yeah.
Great stuff.
OK.
Let's get started in the next video.