Welcome back.
So as I mentioned in the last video one of the biggest challenges for new developers new programmers
has to do with solving problems.
So I think for most people it's easy enough to learn the syntax.
It might take a little bit of time but you learn the syntax and you're done.
You can copy other people's code or remake an application following step by step instructions.
But the hardest thing has to do with solving new problems and new challenges.
And you do get better with time regardless of the technologies you use.
You know the language that you're working in it's really important to have a strong problem solving
skill set and a lot of it will come naturally with time but it's worth being deliberate.
It's worth having a game plan to follow step by step guide.
It's not going to solve your problems for you but it helps you sit and think about and break problems
down.
And it helps solutions come about more naturally.
So I mentioned these five steps that we're going to talk about.
This video is going to start with understanding or understand the problem before we go any further.
I should mention that many of these strategies are adapted from a really good book on problem solving
in general.
It's sort of more slanted towards mathematics but it's by this guy named George polio polio.
The book is called How to solve it.
A great resource and it's where a lot of these tips come from.
OK.
So we're starting with understanding the problem.
So imagine you're sitting in a room.
It could be a beautiful room or it could be like a prison cell made of cinderblock.
And there's an interviewer ahead of you and he or she asks you a question and you don't know how to
solve it.
And it doesn't come to you right off the bat.
It's not one of the practice problems you memorized over the weekend studying before.
So the first couple of things I would do have to do with understanding the problem and it can be tempting
just to dive right in and start solving something in particular when you're under some sort of time
constraint like in an interview.
So most people just want to their heart starts racing they want to get started immediately.
And this is true in programming in particular you can make progress even if you don't get it right.
You can just type a bunch of code pretty quickly and feel like you're making progress in a short amount
of time.
But before you start typing or whiteboarding or whatever you're doing I think it's really important
to take a step back and just make sure you understand the task ahead of you.
And that sounds silly it sounds trivial but there are some very deliberate questions you can ask.
A thorough investigation of the problem or a question and it can really help clarify things and sometimes
will give you an aha moment although not always.
So here are some of the questions that I recommend you ask yourself or if you're in an interview setting
ask the interviewer but also if you're working on your own challenge you're trying to build something
out and you're not sure how to approach it.
Ask yourself these questions.
So can you restate the problem in your own words.
This is always the first thing I ask my students to do in an interview setting.
You get a new question.
Just make sure you can restate it back.
Not word for word.
Don't just copy with the interviewer said but change it a bit in your own words to make sure that you
actually understand what the question is What are the inputs that go into the problem.
So this is a really important one.
What about the outputs.
So what are the outputs that should come from the solution to the problem.
What should the output look like and we're going to dive into an example just a moment.
So what are the inputs what will the inputs look like.
What are the outputs what should come from my solution what should be returned from my function.
Can the outputs be determined from the inputs.
Meaning do you have enough information to solve the problem you have the inputs can you get the outputs
that are expected.
Just using that information and sometimes you need to wait a bit until you can figure that one out.
How should I label the important pieces of data that are part of the problem.
So this would be you know what are the things that really matter in this problem what should you call
them.
What's the terminology that you should use.
So it might seem like a lot.
It is but if we walk through an actual example we're going to do a really simple example which is write
a function which takes two numbers and returns there so.
So imagine that someone asked you this in an interview setting.
Let's explore sort of understanding the problem through this lens.
So let's let's walk through some of these steps.
Write a function which takes two numbers and returns or some.
Can I restate the problem in my own words.
All right well this one is nice and simple.
You know we could just say something like write a function that adds two numbers or implement addition
or something like that.
OK.
Easy enough.
What are the inputs that go into the problem.
Well this might seem like an open and shut case.
Just add two numbers so we need two numbers right.
But if you start to really think about it there it really depends.
I mean are we talking about integer numbers or are we talking about floating point exclusively.
Depends on the language that we're working in of course.
How large are these numbers going to be.
Because in some languages most that I've worked in there's an upper bound for the size for numbers and
if you're trying to add really really large numbers it doesn't work well.
For example if we tried to do this here it's a really large number plus you can see a plus sign.
Another really large number totally valid mathematical operation.
But in javascript What do we get.
Infinity just gives up and gives us infinity.
So in other languages you might be able to represent this better as a string.
Each one of these numbers.
I mean I won't actually do it for both but an implement addition using the strings.
So it actually really does matter right.
It's not a trivial question.
It's silly to just add two numbers together we already have addition.
Why do that.
But if we just think about it we already start to figure out that there are some important distinctions
between these inputs and if we are trying to add these really really large numbers suddenly the problem
becomes a lot harder because in javascript we can't do that just with plain old numbers.
Another thing is are we only working with two inputs.
Is it always two.
What happens if someone leaves and is put off.
Or what if someone wants to add four 10 numbers like that's totally valid to add 10 numbers together
mathematically as our function only going to work with two numbers and the same applies to the third
question which is output What should the output look like.
This is simpler in this case.
We still would have the question of should it be an integer.
Should it be a float depending on you know if you pass into floats do you want to float back if you
pass in an integer and a float.
Are you even allowed to pass in a float.
Or what about the string returning a string A for doing this massive addition.
So it's sort of the same question.
Well it's not the same question but it's a lot of the same issues.
Next up can the outputs be determined from the inputs.
Basically do we have enough information to do the problem.
And in most cases the answer would be yes.
But if you think about it what happens if someone only passes one number and it's already discussed
we don't have enough information to do addition at that point.
So do we add zero.
Do we return undefined or no or something.
What do we do.
And that depends.
You ask your interviewer that or in most interview settings it might just tell you to ignore that for
now but also in most interview settings they probably wouldn't ask you to write a function that takes
two numbers and I turned to them.
And lastly how should I label the important pieces of data that are part of the problem.
So I like to put this in here because it's important to start thinking about this what matters.
So we have the inputs and we have the outputs and that's pretty much all we need.
So maybe you know name our function add and then we'll have number one and number two is the arguments
and then some is our result that we return.
So this is simple but once you start getting into more complicated problems thinking about this step
by step really can make a difference and I'll show you some examples where it helps.
But first let's move on from understanding the problem to exploring concrete examples.
So this was only the first step.
But there were still multiple questions that we can ask ourselves or ask our interviewer about the problem.
All right.
Next up exploring examples.