Welcome back.
So let's move on to part three.
Step three of solving a problem or at least trying to.
So we understand the problem.
We explored concrete examples.
Now before we start typing code I like to break it down and I actually like to do it sounds like I don't
start dancing in the middle of the interview.
I break it down.
I mean take the actual steps of the problem and write them down.
Doesn't have to full pseudo code it doesn't have to be valid you know syntax.
I like to do just little comments as a guide for the steps they need to take in especially in an interview
setting.
This is really important what a lot of interviewers are looking for is you know you to communicate what
you're doing.
You don't want to just start typing right away or start writing code on a white board silently with
your brow furrowed angrily writing code.
It's much better to say All right here's just the steps I'm going to try and take.
You know sometimes you can get a little hint you can throw in.
Do you think they'll work or you know does that does that sound crazy to you or could this be the right
way of doing it.
And sometimes they'll give you a little hint.
So breaking it down can be really important.
So I recommend explicitly writing out the steps that you need to take.
It doesn't have to be a ton of detail it doesn't have to be a line by line every line you need to write
just the basic components of the solution.
So this forces you to think about your code before you actually write it so that you're not just Freewheelin
and trying to come up with it on the fly.
And it also helps you kind of catch or figure out any lingering questions or you know parts that you're
scared of that you don't understand.
So that's why I really recommend doing this.
It helps you just lay out your steps and that's always nice and it helps you stay focused.
But also it helps you highlight the problems you might still not be confident about.
And then you can just dive in and start writing the code.
So let me show you what it looks like.
If I were to break down this same problem write a function which takes in a string and returns count
of each character in the string.
It's the same problem from before.
All right.
So I have a sheet of paper or a white board or whatever it is in my interview.
I've written down some examples and now I'm going to type up the skeleton of my function so we'll call
it Char count and we know that you know it accepts a string.
It's called as TR and then stop with the actual code and I'm going to start writing some comments.
We're going to break it down for myself.
And the simplest thing we can start with is just do something and then add in our return value return
an object with keys that are lowercase alphanumeric characters in the string.
So just to clarify I decided or my interviewer decided that we only need to care about alphanumeric
characters lowercase as well.
So that means you know in this example your PIN number is 1 2 3 4.
We are keeping track of the numbers and we are keeping track of all letters but only lowercase them
so p i n pin.
We're going to keep that you know one lowercase P to lower case I's this one here and this one here.
OK.
So we could start with something simple like this.
Put our return value down there.
I'm going to duplicate this and expand upon it.
So if we think about the actual steps of what we want to do.
Well we're going to need to do something once for every character in the string.
Right.
We're going to go over it at some point.
We also need to make an object that we're going to return at the very end.
Right that one simple we need to make the thing that we're going to return.
We need to return it at the end.
But the bulk of the logic involves looping over every character in our string and doing something.
So I might start let's get rid of this and simplify this a bit.
I would start with something like make object to return and then after that I would do no loop over
string and we'll come back and fill in the detail and then return object at.
And so now we have the very basic steps and we can you know fill in the blanks.
But looping over string is definitely the bulk of our logic.
So what do we need to do.
Well if we loop over the string we know that we're going to need to look at each character and let's
start with why we're going to need to look at why and lowercase.
So we know we could lowercase the entire string at the beginning.
That's one option.
Or we can lowercase each character as we go.
But we're going to start by taking a look at this character and what do we do we check.
Well are there any in our object are ready and technically it's going to start out empty so there's
nothing in there.
So then we would add why instead it's count to 1.
But if there already was a y in that object then we would add 1 to it.
So that's really the logic loop over string for each character.
Then we'll do something like if I'll just do char is in our object let's say is a key in Object add
one to count if the character is not in our object at it and set value to one.
So that makes sense although this isn't accounting for the fact that we only care about alphanumeric
characters so the spaces we're not going to add in the exclamation point we won't add.
And so we should clarify that.
We should say if the character is a number slash a letter and is a key and or object I'd want to count
if the character is a.
Slash letter and not in our object.
Add it to the object and set value to one and then Otherwise we'll say like if character is something
else a space period etc. don't do anything.
And then at the very end we return our object.
So we make our object at the beginning.
Then we go character by character.
We have our main logic.
It will just be a loop probably a for loop and then we'll take each character look at it make sure check
is it alphanumeric.
Is it a number or letter if it is then we will add it into our object.
And that means either incrementing an existing part of an object or adding into the object and setting
its value to one.
And if it's not alphanumeric we just don't do anything.
So we build up our object one character at a time and then we return it at the very end.
And now that we have these basic steps we can now go fill in the blanks and I highly recommend you know
this is a simpler problem.
Some of you probably could have a lot of you probably could solve this without having to do any of this
you know pseudo code and this isn't even full pseudo code but just writing these comments out.
But for more complicated problems it really can be a lifesaver because if you write out the steps especially
in an interview you write out the steps you know what you need to do even if you're not sure how to
accomplish it.
It demonstrates to your interviewer that you at least have formulated an approach and if you run out
of time and you only get halfway there but you have to lay out for what you would have done.
So like if we stopped here for example this is a short problem but say this is where we ran out of time.
Everything is implemented in code.
If we have these notes down here our interviewer could see that we knew where we were going or we had
a general idea and that can often make the difference in demonstrating that you know are competent.
Even if you don't finish the problem.
I've seen many people get jobs who didn't you know they thought that they failed the interview because
they didn't finish the problem.
They didn't have the right return value at the end.
But often these problems are made to be so difficult or so time consuming that you're not supposed to
finish.
And it's really about seeing your process.
So that's what all of this is about the process.