All right.
Welcome back.
We've made it to the final step out of five and this is probably the most important step when it comes
to improving becoming a better developer.
So we've understood the problem we've talked about concrete examples broken down into steps.
We solved it or simplified it to help us solve it.
And then once we have something whether it's an amazing solution or super scrappy it's time to look
back and refactor.
I know it's tempting that once you have something workable something good enough that does what it needs
to do.
It's tempting to just you know shut your laptop or close the book and go.
I don't know.
Play video games or do something else.
It's really tempting because often you can get by with something that just works.
And in a lot of jobs and a lot of scenarios.
All that matters is that something works.
It doesn't have to be beautiful it doesn't have to be the most efficient code on Earth but it's really
really important to strive for those goals.
Obviously if you're a one man team and you're her one woman team and you're creating your company on
your own and you have a deadline of tomorrow and you have to just write code that works then yeah it's
fine to be scrappy but it's really important to try and improve your code.
And it's a missed opportunity if you don't take the time to look at your code look back and reflect
on it.
And I don't just mean you know longingly in a poetic way.
I mean look at the individual components line by line talk about the parts you don't like or what do
you not like about how the code itself looks how it reads how easy it is to understand obviously what
most people care about is efficiency when they're looking at code.
But there's often a balance that needs to be struck to between those two pillars of efficiency and legibility
and in an interview setting.
It's really important to ask these questions often out loud.
You have a finished solution.
You can be proud of that something works.
I like to then take a moment and sort of go line by line and think oh you know this is not ideal I think
maybe there's a better way of doing this but I'm not confident I would google if there was a faster
way of doing this that sort of thing.
So I'm going to go through that.
But here's is sort of a checklist of questions you could ask yourself.
Can you check the results so that one's obvious we need to make sure our code works.
Can you derive the result differently.
So this is referring to the fact that there is rarely one solution and only one solution to a problem.
So can you think about different approaches now that you've solved it one way.
Is there another way that seems viable that you couldn't think of earlier.
Can you see it at a glance or understand it at a glance.
So how intuitive is your solution does that make sense when you look at it on paper on a whiteboard
in your code editor can you use the result or method for some other problem.
One of the great benefits of solving a problem is that it helps you sort of develop a spider sense an
intuition for solving other problems.
So whenever you write down a solution it's worth pausing and asking yourself if there's any similarities
between this solution or this problem.
In others you've encountered in the past.
So maybe not.
In an interview setting necessarily but this has happened to me a couple of times.
I solved some problem and it sort of unlocks the solution to another problem on a different project
or a different company or something like that.
So it's something to keep in mind.
OK.
Next up can you improve the performance of your solution.
So this is one that like I said is probably at the top of a lot of people's minds when they write the
solution.
So how can we make it perform better.
Mainly you know time complexity and space complexity.
And that's something we talk a lot about in this course.
So if you're not super comfortable measuring that or calculating it that's OK.
But we can still identify certain things that might be poorly performing or slow for example like a
bunch of loops that are nested try and avoid that.
Can you think of any other ways to react to your code if you're working for a company.
Does your code follow company guidelines style guide.
Does it follow conventions of the language.
Is the spacing consistent.
Just minor things but this is important to show even in an interview setting at least acknowledge the
fact that your code isn't neat and that you would prefer to make it neater if you didn't have time.
And lastly how have other people solved this problem.
So in an interview setting often you know the interviewers ask the same question to many different candidates.
Some companies I've seen of your same question for years and so they've probably seen a lot of candidates
and a lot of solutions.
So in an interview it can be really beneficial after you have something whether it works or doesn't
work.
At the end to pick their brain say you know what other approaches are there what did I miss.
How have you seen people solve this.
And sometimes people like to share the most effective or simplest solution.
Other times people like to talk about the craziest and most eccentric solution the most unexpected way
of solving it even if it's not the most efficient but you can learn a lot from looking at how other
people have solved the same problem.
Now if you're on your own you're working on a project and application and you're solving a problem.
Often you're solving something other people haven't solved before.
Otherwise you may not be prioritizing solving it yourself right.
If you need to you're not going to build your own database from scratch.
You can use someone else's database but sometimes there are certain things that you do implement on
your own and it's worth looking at other implementations whether it's in a different language.
This happens pretty frequently to me.
If I'm writing something you may not find it in javascript.
You can search around and you might find someone elses code in Java or in Python and you can take that
and compare it to yours depending on how comfortable you are doing that and it can be really useful
and you can find ideas in different approaches anyway.
So these are a lot of questions here that he can ask yourself.
But my point is that refactoring is really important and it doesn't even have to be refactoring which
is why I called it.
Look back and refactor because sometimes you could be happy with your code.
Or you might not want to make changes but it's worth thinking about it.
It's worth analyzing your code and reflecting on it.
Looking back on it rather than simply writing something that works and calling it a day.
So let's go through a simplified version of that process with my solution here.
So I changed my solution a bit.
Here it is.
By the way everything is the same as what we saw in the last video I added in a simple regular expression
to test if a character is alphanumeric.
So if it's a lowercase A through Z or zero through nine and this is how I'm weeding out all the non
alphanumeric character spaces underscores dashes periods commas and only doing the letters and numbers
and I lowercase first and then I test each character.
So if we make it to this point it's that character is either a number or a letter and then we just check
like we did in the last video.
If the characters already in that object meaning it's greater than zero it's set to 1 or 2 or 3.
For example just add 1 to 2 the value otherwise initialize it to 1.
I'm sure that extra one came from and then we return the object at the end.
So this works and if I finish this at the end of an interview this is my solution.
The main pain points to things that I would point out.
There's a couple one easy fix is I'm not really a fan of using a for loop.
Obviously for loops are great and they've been around forever.
But in today's landscape I would probably use four of loop just to simplify this so we don't have to
work with I.
Because if we do 4 of on a string it gives us each character immediately.
There's no reason to go you know this is an extra step.
Loop through a range of numbers then take that number to get an individual character.
When I could replace it so I'll refactor this.
Keep this here but slowly refactor it down here and this isn't really a performance thing.
It's just aesthetics I guess so for.
I'd say var char of that string.
Then you don't need to define char again.
We're going a lower case.
So this chart to lower case so we no longer have to do.
String of I were just working with char and this should work still.
Let's just verify that.
So I pasted in.
Let's do it on hello.
Hi throw in some punctuation and it looks like it's working.
We have two H's lower cased.
OK that's all good.
Now a small syntax change that we could make.
This isn't a huge deal but this kind of bothers me when I look at it takes up a lot of space to do a
very simple thing where either adding 1 to a number or setting a number to 1 or initializing a value
in a key.
Oh my gosh.
In an object you are initializing the value to zero.
So we're initializing to zero or adding 1 to it which is a pretty simple thing and it's as simple if
else so often I look to combine these into a single line if possible and it can be difficult if you're
in a stressful interview situation.
Often I just write the first thing that comes to mind the simplest most basic syntax and then come back
and clean it up so we can replace this here with this line.
So what this does is it takes a character like a Access's the corresponding value in our object.
So if it's truthy we're going to add one to it.
Meaning if there's a value in there already.
If there's nothing in there we're going to set it to 1.
So we basically have two scenarios.
Object char equals this object char plus one.
Or if it's falsie set it equal to 1.
So this is a nice way of cleaning up our code shortening it quite a bit and just to verify that it still
works.
One more time.
Pasted in correctly and it looks like it's working.
So the last thing and this is probably the most important thing that I would think about here.
We did a couple of stylistic changes.
You know we could use some more.
2015 syntax replace var with lut and constant.
That's probably a good idea to do.
But the most pressing thing in my mind that I'm unsure about if this was in an interview setting I would
say OK well I'm using a regular expression here because I know how to do that.
And it's a quick way relatively short way of checking for a certain pattern.
In our case to see if a character is alphanumeric a letter or a number but I'm not sure how efficient
it actually is.
And I would say that I'd say you know I've heard certain things that in Javascript.
And this is true in javascript regular expressions.
The performance can vary depending on what you're doing and depending on the browser that you're in.
In particular Chrome had some issues with regular expressions a while back.
So I kind of I'm trying to avoid them because they can be very useful for something like this.
This is a very simple usage of a regular expression.
Often people will use them to find patterns like credit card patterns or phone numbers or addresses
are much more complicated things like matching a u r l pattern which would be a huge pain otherwise.
But just checking if something is a letter or a number I think there could be a better way to do this.
So I would say that out loud and you may not.
This might not come to mind right away.
It didn't come to my mind right away either.
But what you can do I just did some research to figure this out.
Is use char at character at.
So if we you know take a string like high and then do Chaar code at rather than char it excuse me char
code at and give it an index.
It gives us a number 104 which is the character code for H for lowercase H.
If we did let's just do I it's one of five H I J comes next in the alphabet.
It's one of six.
So these are in a range of numbers.
And so what we could do is replace our regular expression with using a simple mathematical comparison
so we would do a character her char code at and give it you know let's just say always zero for now
and then we would check if it's a valid character code.
And I found someone doing this online which is what sort of inspired me to look at this.
This person wrote a little bit of a performance test where they're testing if something is alphanumeric
down here using a regular expression.
And here they're testing if something is alphanumeric using a character code so you can see between
forty seven and fifty eight are the numeric character codes between 64 and 91 are uppercase alphas.
Yes the alphabet and lower case letters are 96 to 123.
So we can just quickly a couple of boolean comparison which are very very easy and fast to do in any
programming language.
They're pretty much one of the simplest the simplest operation you could do are the simple boolean comparisons
and this person demonstrates actually that if you repeat this over and over and over again you can see
that the non regular expression version is indeed faster Fifty five percent slower using regular expressions.
So I'm showing this to you not to say you know I would come up with this in an interview because I probably
wouldn't have I might have considered it but I certainly wouldn't know the character codes and I would
have just gone with with what I felt most comfortable doing.
But then I would at the very end add a little note in to my interviewer saying hey maybe there's a better
way I would google it.
I have a feeling.
Regular expressions might not be the fastest way.
So what I did is actually turn this into a function called is alphanumeric.
But it works in a single character.
So you pass in a character one at a time and then we get the character code at index 0 because it's
the only it's a one character string.
Technically you can actually leave this blank and it still works.
But I like to be explicit so I'll put the zero in there.
It gives just the first character which is the only character.
So if we're passing in hello like this I would call is alphanumeric on H call it on e on.
And it should return true every time.
And then if we have a space or an exclamation point it will return false.
So I've created this function.
Now what I'm going to do is get rid of this regular expression and refactor it to be if it is alphanumeric
of character just like that.
Another thing to consider is the placement of when we do the lower casing.
Is it better to lower case everything at the beginning of the entire string and then check each character
to see if it's alphanumeric.
Is it better to first check for alphanumeric characters so that we weed out all the spaces the punctuation.
Everything that's not valid and then lowercase afterwards.
And I'm actually not positive on how I feel about it.
I've gone back and forth.
It depends on what your strings look like what the inputs look like if they are generally all alphanumeric
versus if you have really weird strings that have a ton of random characters that aren't alphanumeric.
I think that the answer would depend on that.
But what I'm going to do is just run it like this so if it's alphanumeric then we'll lowercase it and
then add it into our object.
So I like this solution one.
I like having this separate function so that this is pretty readable in my opinion.
For each character in or of our string like that's very nice and legible for a character in in the string.
If that character is alphanumeric we're going to lowercase it and then added into our object or initialize
it to one.
Add one to the current value.
So I like this solution.
I think it's clean and readable but also allegedly at least according to some some stuff we've found
a mine is more efficient to use character codes compared to a regular expression like we had up here.
So I know this is getting a bit long but I just want to show you my process.
This is the solution I wrote first and then I kind of just thought about it more and did some more research
and this is the solution.
I prefer not just stylistically not just because it's shorter it's actually not shorter because of this
code here of course you could put all this code right in here and not have a separate function but I
think it reads so much better like this.
All right.
So let's make sure it works.
Char account of.
Sure.
This one again.
Hello world.
Hi.
So there should be two H's there are there is one.
What else.
Three L's and we're ignoring case and also we're ignoring non non-alphanumeric characters.
All right.
So that was a lot there.
Hopefully you agree.
Maybe you don't have some feedback on my refactor but just in and asking myself those questions about
how did other people do this how could I am proof this.
Where are the stylistic changes I could make or solution looks vastly different than it did before.
Not that there's anything wrong with this one out of the box.
OK.