Hey we'll welcome back.
So the first of the sorting algorithms that we're going to take a look at is called bubble sort.
So bubble sort is not all that efficient.
It's not that commonly used.
There is one use case will discuss where it does excel.
But generally we're not learning it because it's going to be it's not going to rock your world.
You're not going to be implementing it all the time although it is a very good problem.
It's a fun one if you know how to do it.
And there are some optimizations we can make.
So it's a good thing to talk about.
And it also helps us understand why other algorithms improve upon it.
So don't skip it please.
OK.
Now that I've made it sound terrible.
Let's talk about why it's called bubble sort.
So the idea is that if we have an array and resorting from smallest to greatest So in ascending numeric
order the larger values will bubble to the top one at a time.
So what I'm going to introduce now is something that we haven't seen up until now.
I think it's called visual.
I actually don't know how to use this all the time in my classes.
Visual go visual Owego it's a combination of visual and I'll go for algorithm.
So I like visual go but the way it's highlighted it makes me question my pronunciation.
So what it is is a really cool interactive tool in the browser that lets you step through sorting out
rhythms.
Among other things I'm currently looking at bubble sort and you can see that we have some data.
If you open this up by the way your dataset will look different.
I I put these numbers specifically I didn't want to have a massive dataset that took me like 10 minutes
to step through.
So we have one two three four five six seven elements ranging from 10 up to 37.
OK so this is our array.
This is the first item and this is the last item.
The way that bubble sort works is that as we loop through each item we compare it to the next item the
one in front of it and we check.
Is this one larger than what we're comparing it to.
And if it is we swap.
So swapping is really important to bubble sort is how it works you basically swap if something is larger
and then you compare it to the next one.
Is it larger swap again compared to the next one.
So let's just step step through that.
So twenty nine and 10.
We swap because 29 gets larger 29 and 14.
That's next comparison we swap.
Now we compared twenty nine and thirty.
This time we don't swap.
So now we have 30 and 37.
Thirty is not larger than thirty seven.
So once again we don't swap.
Now we compare 37 and 14 and now we do soie.
Now we're on to 37 and 18.
Compare the two and we swap.
So that was our first pass all the way through the array.
And what happened is that the largest value bubbled to the top.
We've also heard this as sinkings sort where the largest values sink to the end to the bottom.
I think that's a little more pessimistic bubble that's so much happier.
He doesn't like bubbles.
So now we repeat the process.
I won't make you watch every single step of this but we started again at the beginning so we compare
10:14.
We don't swap we compare 14 and 29.
Again we don't swap we compare 29 and 30 we don't swap.
Now we compare 30 and 14 and we do next we compare 30 and 18.
Once again we swap.
So now we have the last two values cemented in place right.
13:30 seven Those are sorted.
So we're building this list as the values bubble up to the top to the end the largest values.
We know that those last two items are now sorted those don't need to change and on and on we go very
quickly go through this we swap 29 bubbles to the top and eventually we end up with the sorted array.
So on the slides I have a simple walkthrough of one of those iterations.
So if this is our re our array our array we swap if we compare five and three we swap.
So five moves up next we compare five and four we swap again next five and one we swap again.
And finally we compare five and two and we swap because five is the largest element in the array and
ends up at the end.
So thats for one single iteration then all we need to do is repeat that over and over.
And you could start by repeating once for every item in the array.
But remember that the as we go through the amount of items from need to sort decreases because we started
out with one two three four five elements that were unsorted.
Now we have four unsorted elements and one solidified sorted element.
So that means that we have fewer elements to sort.
As we go through so our loops can reflect that.
But first let's talk about swapping since that's such a crucial part.
We have to swap.
How does that work.
Well in javascript there's a couple of ways of swapping.
I have two two listed here.
This is honestly my preference.
It's not the it's not the newer way of doing it but this is how the tried and true way of shopping values.
I think it's kind of more legible easier to understand.
You don't even have to make a separate function to do this.
Of course.
But here what we have is an array and then the two indices that we want to swap and we set up a template
variable to store one of them and then.
So if that's the first one index of 1 we set up a temp variable and save that to that value then we
change what was in array of index 1 to now be what's in array of index 2.
And then lastly we use that temp variable to update array of index 2.
So that's how I like to do it.
But there's also in 2015 the syntax for doing it which I don't know I don't think it's very readable
personally but the syntax basically is take the whatevers in index one and swap it with index to take
an index to swap it with the next one.
And this works and it has a single lines.
So for those of you who are file size Queens who care about how short your files are you can use this.
I'll probably use both but it helps to define a function called swopped because then our bubble sort
code becomes even shorter.
The actual logic really is just about the comparisons in the loops.
And then we can just call swap but you don't have to define a separate function if you want to implement
it which I highly recommend you give it a shot.
Here are some of the steps.
Start looping.
So define a function.
I didn't add that and called bubble sort.
It takes an array and you can assume it's all numbers start looping with a variable called I at the
end of the array.
Towards the beginning and we'll discuss exactly why but it has to do with the fact that we're shrinking
down the amount of space that we're sorting.
Then an inner loop inside of that outer loop with a variable called J.
From the beginning until I minus one.
So I is referring to the first loop.
So we have a nested loop that is depending on the first loop minus one and then we just compare array
of J.
So that's going to be our individual for want back here.
Let's say we're comparing If J is zero.
We're going to compare it to array of J plus 1 which is the next item.
So whatever J is we're going to compare the item ahead of it.
So J and J plus.
OK.
So if a Ray-J is greater than array of J plus 1 that means you need to swap and you can swap however
you like using whichever version I showed you.
And then at the end just return the sorted array after the loops are done.
So give it a shot if you'd like.
And in the next video we'll have an implementation.