Hey welcome back.
So we're actually still talking about bubble sort.
Because there's one important optimization we haven't discussed.
So there's a very specific scenario where if our data is almost sorted or if it's already sorted it's
doesn't need to be sorted.
Our bubble sort algorithm as it stands doesn't really treated any differently.
It still tries to sort every single item.
So in this scenario where we're almost sorted 5 fast forward through this OK maybe this is a bit too
long.
OK OK.
We're almost there now.
We're sorted right.
So if we get to the end and as humans we can see that we're done.
But our code is actually going to keep going and it's going to go to the end.
No swaps are made but then it goes again and it tries to sort all these up until here then it goes again
tries to sort all these to hear even though nothing is happening it's just iterating over.
So if we have a super long array that's going to be a problem because it just takes up a lot of unnecessary
time.
So we can short circuit our code all that we have to do is check last time through Did we make any swaps.
If the answer is no if we didn't swap anything that means that we're done.
Because if you didn't swap in the last time you're not going to swap them the next time.
So back in our code what I'll do is make two versions.
We're getting a lot of solutions going.
If we comment these out for now never know what the best way of doing this is because students like
to have the different steps as I go.
But I also don't like making the super long files because it can scare some people.
What we can do if we call this right now with a nearly sorted array like eight come a one two three
four five six seven for example.
So we're almost there right after the first pass.
It's going to be sorted it will be it's at the end.
If we take a look right now how many times or how many comparisons we're making roughly.
Let's run it now.
Are making a ton.
Because it was sorted at this point and we kept going without making any swaps a ton of times after
that.
So what I'll do is I'm going to make a variable I'll call it no swaps and no swaps is if it's true that
means there are no swaps and we're going to break out of the loop.
So I could start with that down here even though it's not defined.
I could write if no swaps break that would get us out.
Of course we don't have no swaps defined so appear all do far.
No swaps like this.
And then inside the loop each time through I'm going to set it to be true we'll assume there's no swaps
every time through.
But then if we make a swap which is right here remember we can set it to be no swaps equals false.
Does that make sense.
So as we go through every time at the beginning so let's say we start with this no swaps starts that
true.
And then we make a swap right off the bat eight and one we swap.
So now there's no chance of breaking out this time through.
But then we finish the iteration and eight is now at the end you could see here for example next time
through no swaps is true and we never make a swap.
This is never true so we never set it to false which means we get through the all the way to the end.
One time afterward.
So we sort it all then we iterate through no swap No swap No swap.
Then we get done with it.
And this is true now if no swaps and we break out.
So now if we if we take a look at what this how many times just prince out with this line you can see
that we basically had to get it to the end which was right here.
This was our first time through and then we went through one more time and we finished and then that
was it.
We didn't keep going and compare that to the previous versions where we went through.
We got to the end and then we kept sorting over and over and over and over and over many more passes
in this case we shortened it significantly.
And as the array grows if it is nearly sorted that makes a very big difference.
OK.
So I just added a little comment.
This is our next version that we optimized with the no swaps variable just a small change but it really
can save a lot of time.