What is the time complexity of bubble sort.
Well in general it's squared because we have a nested loop and we're roughly making a comparison for
each item in that array.
We are making an number of comparisons in order to get 8 to the end.
We had to compare eight to every single other item in the array.
However if the data is nearly sorted or already sorted then with this new version with no swaps it's
more like linear time that's the best case possible.
And there's eight items we go through.
I mean technically in our example it was to N because we went through the first time and then we went
through again to make sure nothing was swapped.
And then we broke out of the loop.
So but that rounded down shouldn't say round but simplifies down to 0 of end.
So that's the best case but that doesn't mean that we should be using bubble sort in.
You do know that your data is very nearly sorted.
It's a good candidate.
Possibly also see another good candidate in a little bit.
This is more just to show an optimization this is a classic optimization to make.
And yeah I think this video here.
So we have this version which doesn't use the fancy swopped syntax.
Then we have this version that does using light as well as the east 20:15 syntax and then down here
we have a version Murray added that no swaps variable in to short circuit.
If we don't make any swaps that is bubble sort.
It's a lot I know.
Now we have another sorting algorithm coming up next.