All right.
Welcome back.
In this video I just want to do a quick walkthrough of the curriculum talks about what to expect.
This course is a little different than others including my other courses in that it's not exactly linear.
You don't have to go through every section in order at the beginning of every single section.
There is a text lecture an article called prerequisites and that explains at a minimum the sections
you need to have finished before you start the new section.
And so let's just begin the very first section or technically the second one but the first technical
section is called Big O notation.
Really important stuff.
We come back to every single section from basically there until the end of the course.
It's a way of describing or talking about the performance the efficiency of code.
So we use that all the time so definitely don't skip that.
Then we move on to a really quick section called analyzing performance of arrays and objects.
Nice and short.
We take what we just learned about Big O notation and apply it to some built in data structures.
We work with all the time.
So that's really quick.
Next we shift over to talking about interviews and algorithms challenges.
Basically what do you do when you're confronted with a tough problem and you don't know how to solve
it.
Whether that's in an interview and you're on a whiteboard and you're panicking or it's at home you're
working from side project or at work.
How do you approach a difficult problem.
And then the second sort of what will goes in tandem with that.
These are two sections problem solving approach problem solving patterns.
When we're talk about patterns we actually get into specific sort of archetypes here code they have
different names things like divide and conquer sliding window frequency counter patterns.
These are all different patterns we describe.
There's a lot of challenges.
This first section that comes before is more about sort of setting up a framework for you to think and
approach a problem this is about concrete patterns.
Then we move on to recursion.
So recursion a really important topic.
Definitely don't skip this if you're not familiar with recursion.
It comes up later on in many of our algorithms.
There's also to challenge sections sort of intermediate recursion problems and then tougher recursion
problems that follow this section then we move on to searching algorithms.
Fun one to talked about things like binary search here we've heard about that.
Then we moved to sorting out algorithms.
So I think we have six sorting algorithms at least.
And these are kind of fun if you've never worked with sorting out for them so you've never heard about
them.
They have some odd names.
We start with bubble sort which is often considered the easiest or one of the easiest.
Move to selection sort.
And then insertion sort and those three form a little group sort of the intermediate or elementary sorting
algorithms then we move on to everyone's favorite and merge sort.
I like merge sort.
A lot of people don't.
Then we get to quicksort.
So these all involve recursion.
They involve Big O notation.
So it's very important that you pay attention to the prerequisite little text lectures at the beginning
of every session to explain what you need.
And then we finish up with radix sort a pretty rare sort and very fast in a special situation and not
very often taught.
Not in my experience I've never really seen it taught.
It's a fun one though.
I actually really liked it.
So from there we get to sort of the second section of the course up until this point it's been about
sort of steppingstones recursion Big-O notation problem solving approaches lots of algorithms searching
sorting algorithms.
Then we transition to data structures.
So from this slide until the end of the Course there's a ton of different data structures we talk about.
And this intro section compares them all it tries to answer the question what's the best data structure.
And the answer is that there isn't one.
But we talk about where they excel on certain structures.
So we also talk about East 2015 class syntax if you're not familiar with how you can approximate an
object current class using javascript.
We talk about that in this section.
Then we're going to run through these quickly singly linked lists then recovered doubly linked lists.
So if you've never heard of these data structures.
Very understandable.
But we spend a lot of time talking about them.
Then we move on to two more stacks and Qs very commonly use structures.
Then we go to binary search trees really trees in general and then we specifically hone in on binary
search trees.
Then we have a section devoted to tree traversal.
So if you have if you've ever heard the term breath first search depth first search post order preorder
in order depth first traversal.
That's the kind of stuff we cover here.
Important.
Somewhat intimidating.
And again recall's on things like Big-O notation and recursion.
It builds on length lists so a lot of this is interconnected.
But you could also jump here and just look at the prerequisites and figure out what you need to learn.
So then we go to binary heaps which is very related to trees but a very special case we talk about building
something called a priority queue.
This is a fun section in my opinion.
Then we go to hash tables.
I also like the section hash tables we talked about very your data structure that what we're doing here
is sort of understanding how javascript objects work how they're implemented behind the scenes.
How would you implement a key value pair data structure.
And we talked about hashing algorithms.
I think it's a fun one.
Then we go to Graf's something that a lot of people are intimidated by.
We talk about how you would model GPS Global Positioning Ogaden my cat it can interrupt me like that.
What is it.
GVS mapping to figure out how to find basically how would you represent a map and traffic data and all
these different variables so that you could create a GPS application or something like that.
We also talk about storing social network data and one way relationship to a relationships.
We explore a lot of stuff around Graf's networks routing.
We talk about graph traversal which Well I won't get into too much same thing breadth first depth versus
If we've heard of that.
And then one of my favorite parts of the course and one of the more complicated things you talked about
is called Dijkstra's algorithm and this has to do with finding the shortest path between two nodes on
a graph to vertices if that means nothing to you.
Well this course is still definitely for you.
You're not expected to understand what that is.
But if we go back to the idea of GPs say you want to get from point A to point B from New York to Los
Angeles which is the fastest way to do that on the roads.
If we have a complete map of all the roads and let's ignore traffic data just distances What's the best
way to calculate that.
I mean there's so many possibilities.
So we learn an algorithm to do that and we do basically an approximation of the same thing.
It's this very famous mathematician and computer scientist.
DYKSTRA came up with it and that's what we talked about here and this is sort of a pinnacle of the course
because we talk it relies on Big-O notation recursion it relies on heape Spiner heaps priority queues
stacks a lot of things that we talked about earlier in the course come back in this last section.
Oh Graf's I forgot to mention graphs.
So that's where we finish up really just to revisit this.
There's a division right here intro to data structures where everything else is focused on individual
data structures from there on out.
And before that there's some really important stuff sorting algorithms searching algorithms.
But no matter what I recommend you start with Big-O notation.
Don't skip the recursion sections and then from there till they get to you just pay attention to the
prerequisite lectures.
You absolutely can go in order.
I mean it's designed in an order.
It's not just arbitrary but if you don't want to sit through all of doubly linked lists you could skip
it as long as he did singly linked lists anyway I'll see in the course.
Goodbye.
I don't know how to end this by.