Welcome back.
In this video I want to address my developer environment.
I'm keeping things really really simple for this course.
I'm not even having I'm not downloading any software.
I'm doing everything in the browser.
That doesn't mean that you need to do that at this point.
The only requirement for the course is that you know the basic syntax javascript.
You know that you're comfortable writing J.S. code.
So however you do that up until now.
I would just do that continue on but I want to show you what I'm going to do if you do want to follow
along.
So I'm using Chrome as my browser.
I always do in all my courses and chrome comes with a little developer tool called snippets javascript
snippets.
So here's chrome and I just open up the con..
I usually use a shortcut on a Mac it's command shift or no it command option J but you can also go to
inspect and then that takes you to the elements and you can go over to the sources tab and then in the
sources tab there's a snippets sub tab I guess you would call it.
There's a couple of them but I have snippets as the only thing that shows and you can see I have a bunch
of names snippets I've I'm recording this after I finished writing and recording the rest of the course.
So you can see for example here's one of our snippets.
So I'm just doing everything in the browser here rather than using the terminal and running code with
no G-S.
You absolutely could do that.
You could write your code and Sublime Text.
You could use.
I think there's equivalents to snippets and other browsers you could use Jay Espen code pen there's
many options out there just run javascript but to show you how this works.
Let's say I'm going to make a new empty snippet.
You've seen me do this a couple of times in the course.
I'll just call this demo snippet and then in here close that I'll make it a little larger and then just
do some really simple thing like concept about log Hello from.
From this snippet.
Oh my gosh can not spell here.
OK.
So let's leave it at that.
And all I have to do is to execute this code is either go down here and click play.
But also it shows me the shortcut command return on a Mac and on the PC will tell you whatever the respective
equivalent is.
So when I hit that I'm going to do it right now if I scroll up I should see.
There we go.
Hello from the snippet.
So you'll see me do this throughout the course.
For example I might run this snippet here and it doesn't matter what it does it's a binary search tree
breath first search hit command enter.
It just ran.
And you can see this is the output.
This is what was returned.
And that's pretty much all I have to say about Crumb's.
Tippett So you'll see me work with them frequently.
I just have a bunch of them over here.
I usually make a new one for each thing so here's a double length list.
We add a set method and then I'll make a new one when we add a remove method for example.
But that's all I'll say for now.
It's a very easy way for me to run code in the browser that everyone can do.
You don't have to download anything that's not Mac or PC specific but also if you know how to write
javascript which I hope you do to take this course should know the basics.
You might just want to continue on with whatever you're most comfortable with.
This is not a requirement for the course.
We're writing basic javascript.
Run it however you prefer.
OK.