Hey welcome back.
In this video I'm going to introduce a selection sort.
Our next sorting algorithm.
So I wrote down that it's similar to bubble sort but instead of first placing the large values into
a sorted position at the end of the array we place small values into a sort of position one at a time.
So we're building the array.
We're still moving from the beginning to the end but the actual sorted data is accumulating at the beginning.
So let me give you an example of how it works.
We go through Here's a single pass so we have this array.
We start at the beginning and what we're going to do is go all the way through looking for the minimum
value and then we're going to put that at the front.
So for example we start with five and three which one is the smallest while three.
So three is going to be our minimum for now which is what the Green means.
But then we now compared to four which is a minimum.
It's still three.
So now we compare it to 1 which is a minimum.
Well now it's 1.
So you can see one is great now.
So that's our new men.
Now we compare one in two which one is the minimum one is.
So what we do now that we've hit the end is we swap we take whatever the minimum element was with whatever
we started with.
And so now we've put the smallest item in the array at the beginning compared to bubble sort.
Where we go through and we swap swap potentially to push the largest element the greatest value to the
very end selection sort builds it the other way.
We find the minimum swap at the end and put it at the beginning.
So let's walk through on vidual go visual go.
However you say this visual algorithms and I have a small data set here.
If we step through we start at the very beginning.
This is our first position and we set a minimum value to be 19.
So that's the smallest value we've seen so far.
Next we compare it to the value next to it 44.
Is there a new minimum.
Nope 19 is still our minimum.
Now we move on and compare it to 38.
Is there a new minimum.
No.
19 is still the smallest.
Now he gets a 5.
And we compare them five is now the new minimum.
So that's our new men.
We move on.
We compare it to 47.
No.
5 is still smaller.
Same thing with 15.
We've now hit the end.
We know that the smallest element in there is five.
So what we do we started here.
So we now swap the smallest element as you can see we have two things selected the beginning where we
started and the smallest element and we swapped them and now we start over.
But this time we start from 44.
So I think that's just showing us that this part is now sorted.
We don't have to care about it.
So we move on 44.
We compare.
OK the minimum now is 38.
Now the minimum is going to be 19.
Now it's still 19.
Now it's 15.
So the new man is 15.
So we swap it with 44.
There we go.
OK.
So now the first two things are sorted.
Now we move on 38.
19 19 is the men 19 and 47 19 still smallest and 19 is still smallest.
We swap 19 and 38.
All right.
Troy hopefully you get the idea from here.
Keep going.
Find a man in that place in that example the men was what we started with 38.
Now we just have to swap the last two and we're done.
So that's selection sort.
We are going through and selecting the smallest element the minimum and then putting it at the beginning.
Oh and actually this hasn't finished officially.
There you go.
Now instead we have a sorted array.
So as far as the code for selection sort.
It's actually not that bad.
We have.
So we reuse the swap code.
So if you made a function for swapping in the last video and bubble sort where you want to use the one
that I made then we don't have to worry about the swap logic.
So let's walk through some of the pseudo code.
OK.
So the first thing you want to do is make a variable to store the minimum value and at the beginning
you can set that equal to just the first item you have to start somewhere.
So the first thing in the array is our smallest value of this only thing we've seen then what we do
is we go through and we compare it to the next item.
If that next item is smaller.
Now we update the value of the minimum variable to be that next item.
And if it's not smaller we keep going and if we at any point find a new smaller value we save that to
the minimum.
Now what are we actually saving.
Well we're not actually saving the value itself.
What we're going to save is the index of where that value is found.
So then we can swap.
So we don't care if the value is 20.
We want to know where it is.
Index of three.
So then we can swap index of zero in index of three after our first pass.
So that's what we have here.
If a small number is found to designate that smaller number to be the new minimum and continue until
the end of the array if the minimum is not the value the index just right put that there you initially
began with then swap the two.
Otherwise if they are the same it means that we happened to have an array where the first element was
the smallest element we just got lucky or maybe it's already sorted which that's not going to be good
for selection sort.
And then we just repeat this process of course.
Next time we know that the first item is already sorted so we don't need to loop over every single item.
What we want to do actually is start from the next item afterwards and find the new minimum.
Otherwise if we kept looking at the whole array every time we would always find the same minimum right
if we just started from here again this is our men and we compare it compare compare our minutes still
going to be one.
And if we started again it's always going to be one.
So what we need to do is then look at this area and find the men and then look at this and this and
so on.
So we want to shrink the scope or window of what we're comparing as we loop through.
OK.
So give this a shot if you'd like to.
It's a relatively short one to implement as well.
Really it's just a loop plus another loop and a single conditional and then at the end a swap.
So give it a shot but also don't feel bad.
I don't want to make it sound so easy.
It's so conceptually can be tricky to get these to work.
So in the next video I will implement it and we'll see how it goes.