OK so let's try writing our own selection sort.
So I have another snippet called sorting selection and I'm going to start by just defining a function
I'll call it a selection sort.
And it takes an array.
And at the end we're going to return that array.
So let's say we're going to call it on the array.
Mean to do even numbers this time 10 and I'll add a single odd number at the end there and 17.
OK.
So this is what we're going to test it out with.
So what we want to do to start is we can just start by looping over every item.
That's a pretty standard place to start.
So for far i equals zero.
I less than a radar link plus plus.
OK.
And if we look at our pseudo code store the first element as the smallest value we've seen so far.
So let's make a variable and we'll just call it lowest or men and we're going to set it equal to I.
So that's the position of the smallest element at least at the beginning.
We don't know any better.
So this is the smallest thing we've seen it's the only thing.
And what we want to do is compare that to the next item after it and then next item after that and after
that and after that and if at any point we find of value that smaller then we are going to change lowest.
So let's do another loop to make that work.
Let's go with the J.
And we're going to set J rather than 0 because remember we don't want to base.
We don't need to loop over every part.
So if let me put this in a better way if we're starting here with our first outer loop I is referencing
here.
We don't want to compare it to i.
Again what we want to compare it to is I plus 1.
We want to compare it to this or if we're at this point in the array.
So if I it's now two these two are already sorted.
We don't want to start comparing i of 2 to J of 0.
We want to compare to 19 which means that we need to go one higher than whatever is.
So we can just do J equals I plus 1 like that and then we'll do.
While J is less than a great length J plus plus
perfect and if we just add a simple constant log just to show what we're looking at let's just do i
and j.
So you can see the comparisons that happen and we execute this.
So no sorting happens but we start by comparing 0 to 1 0 2 2 0 2 3 0 to 4.
Then the next time through we're going to compare one to two one to three in one to four and then two
to three.
Two to four.
And then finally three to four.
So this is working.
I mean we're not doing any sorting but these are the comparisons we want.
We don't want to we don't want to.
For example after our first pass compared 0 to 1 to 2 to 3 to 4 and then start over and compare zero
again.
We don't want to ever look at this element because whatever is here at the end will be sorted.
It will be the smallest value that self-selection.
So it works.
So now we just need a simple condition on here to check with the value of the array is at the lowest
and then compare that to the value of the array at J.
So we're going to have a array of lowest and then array of Jay like that and we want to know if we could
we could do this either way we can say if array of J is less than half lowest or if our current lowest
is greater than the array of J.
I actually prefer.
Logically I think it makes that sense this way because we're looking.
OK.
And we're looking for the lowest items.
I like to do it this way.
If the array of J is less than our current lowest remember the lowest it's just a number like 0.
So our first time through if we walk through this eye is zero which means lowest to zero.
And then J is going to start at 1.
So we compare if array of J is less than array of lowest is a range of one less than array of 0.
Yes it is.
So if that's the case we're going to lowest now to be equal to J.
So we've now updated the value of lowest.
So if we walked through we started the beginning with I set to 0.
J is 1 and lowest is now going to be 1 because we just updated it.
So it's referring to this item.
But next time through we have I it's still zero.
What is J now.
Well J is going up by 1 so j is 2.
So if we compare array of two to array of lowest which is one that's comparing these two now 10 is smaller.
So we're going to set lowest equal to J which means lowest is now to right index of 2.
Now we could repeat this and if we did we would go is 0 still J is now going to be 3 but the lowest
is still 2 because 19 is not great or 10 is not less than 19.
One more time is zero.
Jay is going to be for looking at the last item and the check is array of J which is 17 is that less
than array of lowest array of lowest.
Going to give us 10.
Nope that's not true.
So we don't updated.
Lowest is still too.
So what we've done now is we figured out the index at the end of this loop here we know that the lowest
index of the item that has the lowest value index is equal to 2.
In this case now what we need to do is swap.
So if you look at the pseudo code what we do is take the value we initially started with where we first
began which was the first item.
Right now we swapped that with the position of the lowest item.
So that means we're going to swap zero into this and this and to do the swap we can do it many many
ways we could do it with our tempo so we could make tempo equal to let's do array of eye and then reset
array of I is now equal to array of lowest and then we do a array of lowest.
If I could spell equal to 10 and that are semi-colons.
So hopefully the swapping itself for logic makes sense.
You can of course use the fancier syntax as well.
Also the same solution written in East 2015 at the end.
OK so this should give us a swap and see what happens.
Let's just take a look at what we get printed out.
Let's go through.
At the end of each time to do constitute a log array just like that.
And actually rather than just doing this with a free print I mean to do a concert log array and then
it's going to be kind of annoying.
Out log swapping to and then constant like the array afterwards.
OK.
And then to make it easier to see what's happening each time there's a lot of work just to show you
what's happening and you probably already know what's happening.
But I'm just going to put these dividers in there so we can see.
OK so now if we run this and I'm going to make my cancel larger.
Where do we start.
Here we go.
All right.
So what happens.
We start with this state and we make a swap Here's our first swap we moved 10 to the beginning.
So then we start with that state and we're looking at these and we move what we move 17 to the beginning
as you can see there.
Now we're looking at these three at the end and 19 is the smallest.
So we move 19 to the beginning as you can see now we have these two.
And what do we do.
We swap 22 to the beginning.
All right now we have one element left.
And what are we doing.
Well we're still swapping 34 as the men.
And you can see our code is still running.
We're swapping 34 and 34.
And then this is the return value at the end.
So the code works which is good at the end we get the sorted array and it is selection sort but there's
a change we can make which actually I think will be better illustrated if for example if I did this
is zero.
And then two at the beginning of this list and I guess we can keep this actually I'm going to get rid
of this because it takes up so much space.
I'm going to cancel that log.
The items that were swapping sconces the log I and the lowest end we'll see what happens when we clear
my counsel rerun it make this bigger.
So the first time through if we look at what that list looks like the men is zero.
But we go all the way through the list because we don't know that.
And we find out that 0 is the men who we still swap index of zero with index of 0 and that results in
nothing.
We're doing this.
This is unnecessary because we found that I was actually the same as the lowest and the same thing happens
again.
Next item index of one is our eye and we set the men to be are the lowest to be one as well.
We go all the way through and there's nothing smaller.
So at the end I and lowest are the same and we still do a swap and actually you can see that happens
at the end.
Well we have one thing left 17 where we still swaps 17 with 17.
So a slight change that we can make to fix that is just do a check.
I actually think it put this in the pseudo codea.
If the minimum is not the value you initially begin and then swap them.
Right now we're just swapping no matter what.
So we just add a conditional if and we'll just do if I is not equal to lowest.
If that's the case we're going to do or swap.
So if I rerun this piece clear down here we run here.
There we go.
Now you can see we're only making four swaps.
We didn't make a swap here.
We didn't make a swap here but then we made one and we made two.
They made three and we made four.
And then that was it.
We're done.
OK.
So I have the same code.
Get rid of the consulate log but written with yes 20:15 syntax.
So if you prefer that I brought swap out into its own little function appear.
And now if you look at our logic on here it's pretty short.
You can do it on a single line which I could've done the same thing I could've moved all of this into
its own function called swap as well.
But here are two versions and pick whatever you like I'm using the newer way of swapping data.
So same thing the loop over each item set Lois to be I.
Then we start J at I plus 1 and then we just check.
I actually did the reverse logic or the reverse comparison I checked if lowest was greater an array
of day appear I did it for Ray-J is less than I means the same thing.
And then we just reset lowest and then at the end if I is not equal to lowest swap them.