So selection is not terribly efficient.
We're talking about time complexity and squared.
We'll revisit time complexity at the end of this section to compare them all the algorithms that we've
learned so far.
But yeah roughly we have to compare every element to every other element in the array.
So as the length of the array grows the number of comparison grows roughly at the rate of end times
end and squared.
Yes technically the first time through.
We make six comparisons then five then four and then three and so on.
But that doesn't really matter in the grand scheme of things.
We're still going with over and squared.
It's drastically worse than if we only had to make a single comparison for each item.
Now where selection sort potentially is better than something like bubble sort.
Really there's only one scenario which is if for some reason or you're and you're in a situation where
you want to minimize the number of swaps that you're making.
So remember that bubble sort if you can recall how that works.
We're basically swapping over and over and over to get the largest item to the end we keep swapping
and swapping until it goes to the end and the next time through we swap if we need to keep swapping
in selection sort we iterate we compare a lot but we only make one swap at the end of each loop.
So if for some reason we're worried about writing to memory we're worried about actually doing the swap
which is not very common to be items.
But if you were then selection sort is better.
Otherwise it's just not it's not very good but it is easy.
Which is a good thing and it helped prepare us for some of the other algorithms we'll see.
So that selection sort.
Next we have one more of the elementary algorithms the basic ones which is called insertion.
That's coming up next.