All right welcome back.
Here's my solution using two pointers for the count unique values problem.
So as I mentioned we use two pointers starting from the left one starting here and next one is the index
0 and then index of 1 and then we look forward from there.
And then we update the first pointer only at a particular condition which is when we find two unique
values two values that do not match.
So let's hop over here.
And first thing I'll do is just define my function call it count unique values and it will take an array
and let me call it down here with a new list of unique value.
So let's do one come a one comma two three three.
All right.
That's good enough like this and I want to start with making a variable I and setting it equal to zero.
So it's going to start right here.
Right.
And then I'm going to make a loop and this will be a for loop let's call it J.
And I'm not going to said it equal to zero.
I mean a set is equal to index of 1 which also is value of 1.
I hate when that happens.
But yeah.
Index zero index of 1.
So J equals 1 while J is less than a red dot length.
We don't want it to go any further.
And then I.
Plus plus no J plus plus.
So J is just going to go through the entire loop from here to the end.
So we have one iteration and that's it.
Now inside of those iteration of the loop we're going to compare index array index of an array index
of J.
So we could just start with that.
So array Y and array of J.
So what do we want to check.
If they are not equal to one another.
So array is not equal to array J.
What are we going to do.
First of all it invalid syntax to make it a conditional statement.
If they are not equal.
If you didn't watch the entire video we talked about my approach in the last I guess yeah the last video.
Two years ago.
What we do is we compare them if they are equal we just move ahead until we find something that is not
equal to what I am looking at.
So they're not equal now.
We move up by one and then we put this value here.
So we don't have to swap them we just put two here as well.
So to do that we just can do I.
Plus plus that adds one to high.
So it started at zero.
Now we move it up here and then we set array of I to now equal what is an array of J.
And then we move forward again so that J goes up.
So now J is 3.
This has to be a two for us to do that.
So now J is 3 we compare it.
Oh well they don't match again.
So we move forward.
I plus plus and we set array of I to be three array of is equal to array of J.
And then the loop moves on.
This time they are equal.
When that's the case we don't do anything.
J increments automatically because of the loop.
So three and three are equal.
So next time through J goes up to four.
Well now we have a mismatch again.
So we take four and we put it here.
So first we technically move up and then we put four here.
So now we're comparing four to five.
So we do the same thing.
We move up.
We put a 5 here.
Now we're comparing six to five.
So we move up and we put a six here and then we move up again.
They match.
So we don't do anything move up again.
We put I right here and we put a 7 there.
So now we've built up this beginning part of the array that has all the unique values and it's basically
all we want is the length of this portion and we have that by default.
If we look at I and J at the very end.
J is going to be the very last index of our array.
So actually to demonstrate this.
Remember this only works with a sorted array.
So I can't directly use this array as it is I need to return it to how it was.
So that would be I don't actually remember it.
Now let's just say 1 1 1 2 2 3 4 5 5 5 6 7 like that.
How many unique numbers are there with those 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
So we should get 7 and we'll call count unique values with that.
And then what I'm going to do is in here let's go inside the loop at the very end of that log.
I Khama J.
And we have to do it in here if we want J because J is going to disappear.
And if we run it.
OK.
So we can see you know here's I here's J.
And at the very end J hits the end of the array and we stop the loop is at 6 because that's index of
six.
And that's because internally the array looks something like this where we have all the unique values
right here.
This is where I is get rid of this highest rate here which is index of six.
So we need to add one to I because it's basically the length of this section up until I and we don't
want to start with zero.
We want to start at 1 when we're counting.
So we want to return I plus 1 just down here.
Just like this and if we now test it out we get seven and that should be right.
Let's try it with something like this one.
Number three we should get to and we do.
Now there is a special case which if we have an empty array it's not working.
It's giving us one and it should give us zero there's no digits in there.
And why is that.
Well I started at zero.
And even if none of this runs and nothing happens and here we are returning 0 plus 1.
So I'll add a little short circuit at the beginning.
Just check if a rate length is equal to zero.
Just return zero.
That means there's zero unique digits.
Now we get zero.
But if we go back to one let's do like this we get 5 1 2 3 4 5 unique numbers.
OK.
So that is one way of solving this.
Using two pointers and it's over and time it's linear time because we're only looping once which is
pretty nice.
All right.
Moving on.