Have everyone the next problem solving pattern will talk about I'm calling multiple pointers again.
It's not really an official name for it but let me just read the definition first.
The idea is that we create pointers or values that correspond to an index or position and then move
towards the beginning towards the end or towards each other in the middle.
Based on a certain condition.
OK so what it really comes down to.
We have some sort of structure linear structure like an array or a string or later on we will talk about
things like a doubly linked list which you may not be familiar with or even a singly linked list.
If you don't know what those are don't worry.
And the idea is that we are going to be I don't know searching for a pair of values or searching for
something that meets the condition.
Usually we're looking for a pair and I'll show you an example in a moment and we use two references.
So we start one reference maybe here and another one here and we work towards the middle towards each
other.
Or we could start something here and another like when I say reference I mean a variable like i and
j which are numbers referring to indices.
So we get start here in J here and then we move them forward in a certain way.
So there's not you know a guaranteed direction.
This is this is sort of a loosely defined one compared to what we saw in the last video over the last
sort of pattern frequency counting.
But this does come up pretty often I'll show you a couple of examples.
So just to recap we have a pointer which is just a variable.
You know we're looking at a specific location in an array or a string usually And we have a second one
and we work towards each other or we work in the same direction.
We work from the end towards the beginning.
It doesn't matter but we use two pointers.
So let's talk about an example where this could make sense.
An example.
OK.
So write a function called Sum Zero which accepts a sorted array of integers so it needs to be sorted
not a sorted but in order sorted from lowest to highest the function should find the first pair where
the sum is zero.
So the first pair where you take one number and you add it to another number and it's equal to zero.
So you can see here you know negative three.
First of all this is a sorted array.
Negative 3 up to positive 3.
And in this case negative three plus three gives us zero.
So we return that pair in an array.
Otherwise like in this case there is no pair that sums to zero.
So we return undefined.
Same thing here.
So how would you approach this.
First of all it's important to note and remember him hitting us a lot but it is sorted.
If it was unsorted then we're kind of out of luck as far as coming up with an efficient solution.
But it is sorted and we're looking for something that sums to zero.
So we know that we have small numbers here and the largest numbers are up here and because of that we
can use two pointers and test for sort of certain conditions to see if we want to move down or want
to move our other pointer up.
But first let me show you the naive solution.
This is the simpler one that has time complexity of all of antiquarks quadratic time.
And you can see right off the bat we have two loops we're using one for loop and a second for loop.
So what this one does is it starts appointer looking at negative 3 and then we have a second loop that
iterates over the entire rest of the array.
The entire rest of the string the structure looking for something that adds to negative 3 and equals
zero.
So looking for three.
So we go all the way through and we happened to find a three.
And so that's a simple example but imagine that there was a three here then we would move on to negative
2 and look through the entire array to find a negative 2.
And if we're talking about a 10000 item array that's a lot of iteration when we have these nested loops.
But this is the simplest way.
You start here and then you compare it to every single other number and then if there's no match that
equals zero you move forward one and compare it to every other number and keep going.
So here's the example of the naive version.
It does work.
If I run this.
So we've got negative for negative 3 and so on we would start here.
We look for a match.
There is no more than we have to get three.
There is no match.
We compare all these different things.
We get to negative 2 and we compare it to every single other item until we hit 2 and we found a match.
So even in this case we had to do a bunch of operations to figure out there was no match for negative
for negative 3.
We have to do a bunch of operations and this is a small array.
So this could benefit from a refactor using multiple pointers pattern.
So here's how it would work.
We would start a pointer here and start another one up here because we know that this is a small number
and this is the largest number and we start by just seeing what the sum is what they add to.
Well negative four plus five that's going to give us a positive number which is 1 and that's too big.
We're looking for 0.
So one is greater than zero.
That's not what we want.
So what we would do then is move this pointer down to 2 because this is the small number we're going
to get.
So maybe just maybe there's a four here but there's not.
But our code doesn't know that so it's going to look one below and hope that now we're going to sum
to zero.
So we add negative four into.
Well this time it's too small because that's negative too and that's less than zero.
So that means we're going to add one to the left side because there's no match for negative four.
Remember it's a sorted array.
So we go up.
Now we're looking at negative three in two.
Well we add them together it's still negative 1.
Let's not still negative 1 it's still negative it's negative 1 which is less than zero.
So what that means is that we're going to try and add one to the left side which gives us negative 2.
And now we add negative 2 and 2 and we get zero.
And that is the first pair.
And we return negative to comment 2.
So WAY WAY fewer operations compared to using a nested loop and starting here looking at every single
other number then moving to here looking at every other number.
And this is a simple example where we find it relatively quickly because there is only what 7 ish numbers.
I didn't count them.
Is it 8.
OK.
It is 8.
So it's really small compared to 10000 items where it would save us a lot of time.
So here is that refactored solution where we have two pointers one starting at the left index of 0 and
the other starting at the last index in the array length minus 1.
And I'll take you over to the code in just a moment.
But you can see time complexity is linear it's o of N much better than 0 of squared.
So here's the refactored version and we've got left to zero.
Right.
Set array length minus one so left is going to be this index zero.
Is this index over here.
This is a slightly different array.
I put 10 in here.
Now it looks like our first pair should be negative 3 3.
So we start and we check the sum of array of left and array of right.
So negative four in 10 that's going to give us 6 and we check first is it 0.
Because then we're done.
No it's not.
So if some is greater than zero which it is we're going to subtract one from right.
So right was this index which I'm not going to count my position but we subtract 1.
So now we're looking at this place 3 and we're adding 3 to negative 4 so we start the loop again because
nothing else happens.
You have an if and else if in an else only one of those is going to run.
So we subtracted one from right moving it down to here and start over it.
So now sum is equal to negative 4 and 3 which is negative 1 now.
So this time it's not zero.
It's not greater than zero.
So this else runs which means we add one to our left.
So now left moves up to negative 3.
Next time through some negative three and three which gives us zero and we're done.
If sum is zero return array of left column array of right as an array a new array.
And just to prove that it works.
There we go negative 3 comma 3.
And if we give it something that doesn't have a pair like let's remove that 3 and change this to be
a 5.
There's no pair here right now no.
We have one a negative one.
Remove that one.
OK.
There should be no pair now and we get undefined which is how it's supposed to work.
So we stop because our while loop runs well left is less than right.
So if they crossover at some point that means that we've exhausted every possible pair We've tried here
and here that didn't work.
That was too large so we subtracted one from right.
We tried five and negative four.
Still too large.
So we went to zero and negative for too small so went to negative 3 and zero two small two into negative
2 and 0 two small and two negative one is zero too small.
So then we went 0 0 and we have to stop before there otherwise if we try and do you know zero minus
zero What are we going to get.
Zero.
Which is what we're looking for.
But that's a false positive.
And if it wasn't zero it could be any other number we subtract it by itself or subtract it from itself.
We're going to get zero.
So we have to stop there and that's why we have while left is less than right rather than less than
or equal to right.
So we have to have that.
That's our failsafe.
And that means that we're done and we could explicitly return undefined at the end.
But this works fine too.
Yep.
So that is using two pointers in this case working from the far left side and the far right side towards
the middle.
That's not the only way of doing it.
Next I'll show you a problem where we actually start from the same side and just look ahead rather than
going from the left and the right simultaneously.
We just have two pointers on the left side.
That's next.