Hey welcome back.
So here's a second problem we can solve using the multiple pointers are the two pointers.
It's a bit different.
As I already mentioned because we're not working from the beginning and the end towards the middle.
But we still have two pointers and that's really all that matters.
2.0 is moving some direction based off of a condition.
So the function you need to implement is called to count unique values.
And it should accept a sorted array again and it returns the count of unique values in that array and
it can have negative numbers in there.
But it will always be sorted.
So in this case it should return two because there's only two unique numbers 1 and 2.
In this case it should return 7 because we've got 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
As far as the unique numbers empty we have 0 unique values.
Here we have four unique values negative to negative 1 0 and 1.
So you can use two pointers to help you out here.
If you do want to try this on your own it's not a direct copy or a clone of the previous solution.
It is a little different but we still have two pointers.
So here is if you want to just try it.
Totally blank slate with zero pointers and zero help.
I mean zero hints.
Go ahead.
Pause a video and just started.
There's an exercise after this video if you want to try it and I'll have a solution after that.
But if you do want some some advice some hints pointers Here's how I would do it.
This is sort of the intended approach.
Start a pointer.
Let's do this example start a pointer here.
And then another one here and basically compare the two.
Well these aren't equal.
So you could create a variable to count how many times they're not equal.
How many times there's a different value.
But the other thing you could do that's kind of nifty is huge the array itself to store the unique value
so build the unique values at the beginning of the array because there is no rule that says you can't
you know alter this array that's being passed in.
You don't have to use a separate variable.
So the solution I'm going to do will actually build up unique values at the beginning.
So I end up with a 7 right here and then we'll end up with the 12 here and 13 and so are our first pointer
is only going to move as far as index of six or seven items.
It will move over.
So let me just show you an example.
So if we had this array that was passed in I would have a pointer here.
Let's call it high.
And another one called J.
And we compare them.
Well they are the same.
So I'm going to move Jay forward but leave I where it is then I'm going to do it again.
Compare them although still the same.
So I'm going to move J.
Sort of like J is like my scout leading.
Leading the pack charge or whatever the expression is.
And we look at two and compare it to one.
Well now they are different.
So then I'm going to move up here and then I'm going to put a 2 right here just like that.
So now I is going to be looking at two and I'm going to move Jay forward.
And now we're looking at three with three and two are different.
So I'm going to move up one and put a three here.
So I'm building up the unique values here.
And at the end I'll have all of them at the beginning and I can just figure out how many there are based
off of what index i is equal to.
So I moved Jay up again.
It's another three.
So we don't do anything we just increase J.
Now we get to 4.
So I'm going to move up and put a 4 here.
So now I am looking at.
J goes to another four.
We don't do anything.
Jay goes to a five Ah.
Now we have five compared to four.
So we add one to J.
And I put a 5 here.
Now we compare five to six.
Well they're different.
So we put six right here and now we're done.
Jay has hit the end of the array and this really only takes one pass through the array of end and we're
looking at how many items are here.
Well the way we would know that is by taking the current index.
So I is going to be 0 1 2 3 4 5.
So that's index of I we need to add one.
Of course because our index starts at zero.
So there's actually six unique values.
And this is one way of doing it.
We don't even need a separate variable.
We don't need another variable to keep track of you know unique values.
Now if we weren't allowed to alter the array then this might not be the best approach but it works well
for this exact set of circumstances.
OK.
So if you want to try it using two pointers starting from the left side you can also start from the
right side of course and move to the left but move from one direction to the other with two pointers.
I have a solution after this well after the exercise.