Hey welcome back.
So let's get on to implementing our own version of binary search.
So again here's the pseudo code.
First I just need to make a spot to actually write the code so I've already done that.
I'm doing it as a snippet again I'm calling mine search binary.
It really doesn't matter.
If I were you I'd actually I'd probably do this in a file somewhere save it on your computer.
But this is easier for me.
So I'm going to define our function all that we said was set to accept a sorted array and a value.
So I'll just call mine binary search.
For me this is large enough.
See shrink some of this down OK.
Binary Search takes in an array.
Just call it a r r and then the value will call it element or L-M.
So for example we should be able to call it with something relatively short to 5 6 9 13 15.
Almost all odd numbers do.
20.
28.
OK and then let's say that we're looking for.
Let's say we're looking for 15 in there.
All right.
So right now that's obviously not going to work.
Next we need to set our left and right and middle pointers or I'm going to call them.
I kind of prefer start and end and middle and what we want to do is set the start to be here the very
beginning every time.
We don't want to exclude any of the array so we always want to start at the beginning.
So that's easy just make a variable call it start equals index of 0.
Then I'm going to make end and it's going to be the length the theory.
But we need to do minus one.
Otherwise we're going to be out of bounds.
So we want this index which is set 6 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 yes.
So 0 6 and then we need to take the middle.
This is just to begin.
The middle is just the average of those two.
So in this case 0 and 6 The average is going to be 3 0 1 2 3.
So that's going to give us this position 3.
But if we had one more item in here like 30 then that throws everything off.
So if I just had start plus and then need to add parens to do the average otherwise he'll just be start
plus and divided by two.
This case it's the actual average for them.
But if you take a look we're going from zero up until seven.
Now the average is three point five.
There's no index of three point five zero one two three.
It's going to be right in between 9 and 13 that's not going to work for us.
So that's where I'm going to do math top floor.
That whole thing.
You could also round up if you wanted to.
You just need to be consistent in what you pick.
OK.
So at this point this is what we're looking at with this exact array.
We start start.
It's going to be set to index of zero just right here.
Then we have and set to index of seven in our case which is now 30 and then the middle is going to be
index of three point five rounded down which gives us 3 0 1 2 3.
So we have nine.
And just to verify we could do a count of that log start middle and like that.
And if we execute this they get anything we go 0 3 7.
So that's what we expect.
Now we get into the actual logic of what we want to do here.
We want to continue to loop and repeat this process where we select a middle.
Well first we need to check if the middle is correct.
Right.
Right off the bat we could have picked 15 we didn't.
We're working with nine but let's say we were looking for nine.
We picked the middle of nine right away so we need to check if we got it right.
And if we didn't are we greater or less than are we looking is 9 too big or too small.
In which case you need to start searching over here only or start searching only over here only.
So let's start with just the simple while loop.
So I'm just going to loop over and over while the element while array middle is not equal to what we're
looking for.
So while we haven't found while the middle is wrong let's put it that way.
So this first time middle is nine.
That's not what we're looking for.
We want 15.
So we're going to repeat this code.
Now the code that we're going to do first we're going to check.
We can assume if we're in here that means that the middle is either greater than or less than if the
number we're looking for is less than the middle.
So if our middle is nine let's say we're looking for six.
Six is less than nine.
So what we want to do is shift our end down to 6.
Now you might think we could shift the interest to 9 and that would work but it's redundant because
we know that 9 is not the answer already.
We checked it.
So we're going to set the end to be middle minus 1.
So this is our new window.
Likewise the other direction like in this case with 15 we checked 9 that's too small.
So we're going to move our window all the way up to here.
So our start is now 13 and our middle is going to be fifteen or twenty eight.
We're going to we'll round down to it will be 15.
So we want to do middle plus one or middle minus one because we've already tested the middle.
So let's do that.
Now I'm going to have a simple IF statement if the element is less than array of middle like that.
If that's the case like if you're looking for six We're going to set the end.
We're moving the end down to here.
Right.
So and he calls middle minus one and then we have else there's only one other choice.
Because if it's equal if we actually got it right then we're out of the loop.
But we haven't gotten there yet.
So we're either greater than or less than so.
Else That means that what we're looking for in this case 15 is greater than 9.
We need to move the start of our window to 13 so start equals middle plus one just like that.
Then the other thing.
Well this isn't the only thing.
But another thing we need to do is now change our middle value.
We just need to recalculate.
So our first time through we just copy this.
This is what we started with and then we checked it.
So middle class not equal to Element rate 9 is not equal to 15.
So is the element less than middle.
Nope.
So skip this else.
Start equals middle plus one middle plus one is 13.
So that means that our start is now 13 here.
Our end is still 30 it hasn't moved.
We need to recalculate the middle.
So we need to average 13.
And third will not 13:30 we need to average those indices which is going to be what are we as year 1
2 3 4 and 7.
So I'm just going to copy this exact same line without the var in that loop.
We just get a new middle.
So now middle is going to be what Matha floor of four and seven.
So that's what 11 to floored.
It's going to give us 5 index of 5 which is this item here so this will be our new middle.
And just to verify that.
Let's move this line into the loop that we see what we get each time through.
OK.
So I'm going to run this now.
Let me clear my counsel make this a little bit bigger.
And it looks like it's only running once because at the end we got the answer correct.
So I picked the example of 15 was too easy but you'll see at the end it's 0 3 7 so that's what we have
0 3 and 7 indices.
Then add updates to go from 4 to 7 which is what we have here.
And the middle is five.
And what do you know that's what we're looking for 15.
So we broke out of the loop because the middle is now equal to the element.
Now if I pick something else I'd say pick 28 this time we'll get an extra step.
Executed again.
There we go 0 3 7 the same thing.
But this time 28 is greater than nine.
So our window now is from here to here and the middle is 15 which is what we checked and that's too
small.
So then we have another iteration.
And in this case it's too small.
So what do we do we shift the start up again and get rid of the M and the start now goes to 28.
Here are Endace 30 in our middle.
When you take the average we're going to round down.
So our middle is also here.
So it looks more like this and that now means that we've guessed the number correctly because our middle
is 28 and you can see that Middle East index of six started this index of six or Endace index of seven.
We found it.
So at the end what we should be doing for now at least is just return middle and if we test this all
out or returning six index of six and that's correct when we're looking for 28 we're looking for five.
We're returning index of 1.
That's correct.
There's a big problem with our code though and the problem is if there's not if the number isn't found
in there our code doesn't handle it.
And I'm not going to do this actually I recorded this video once before and I actually showed what happens
there's an infinite loop going on.
Hopefully we'll see if you can spot why.
But let's say I'm looking for 50 in here.
We're not going to find 50.
Our code doesn't handle it and the browser just keeps looping over and over and over and with my recording
software plus the browser doing that my computer was really not happy and it got like a thousand degrees.
So I'm not going to replicate it here.
But what would happen is that we would get basically thousands and thousands.
Eventually it would be shut off but tens of thousands of iterations if not more because we're never
going to find that element.
And the only way our loop ever stops is when we find it if our middle index is equal to the element
we break out.
But our middle and next is never going to be equal to or the item at the middle index is never equal
to 50 or 1 or 14 or any number that is not in here.
This is going to go forever.
So what's her other stopping condition.
Well if we look at what happens as we approach a number that's not in there we start we do the same
thing right.
To is our start or zero is our index.
This is our end 7 and this is our middle and index 3.
Well we check 50 is greater than 9.
So we moved the window up to here as you see there.
So now our start has 13 or index of what for up to 7.
We take the middle index of 5 and 50 is still greater than 15.
So now we move up again and this is our new window and our middle is 28 and recheck is 50 greater than
28.
It is.
So what's our final iteration going to look like here or what should it look like is that we're going
to move the start to be middle plus one which is 30.
So then we end up with everything start middle and end all at 30 at the end of the list.
So then what's next.
Because our code is still saying All right well the middle is 30 we're looking for 50.
So we need to move start to go up one and there isn't anything after that but it's going to increment
our start or increment our start to be 8 at that point which is out of bounds.
So then if we tried to do that array of 8 we're going to get undefined and then we're going to start
comparing things with undefined and it's just not good and it's going to keep going forever and ever.
So we don't want that.
OK fine.
I am I am going to show to you what happens and my computer is not going to be happy.
Here we go.
As you can see it just keeps going and going over and over and it sets the start.
Now is it ok I'm back after my computers and I'm very happy with me but it worked out.
So what happens at the end is that our start middle and converge and then our start gets above our start
is set to be middle plus one.
So the next time through if we're working with the start is 8 the middle seven in the end to 7 if we
go through again we're checking the middle which is still 7 because we take the average of these eight
and seven and you floor it and you're still stuck with 7.
So our middle is not going to budge and it stays at 7.
And then we go through again.
Is element less than Array middle.
No it's greater than because we're looking for 50.
So 50 is greater than.
So we get start equals middle class once a start is seven plus one.
So we're not moving anything and we get stuck because we've hit the end basically and we've crossed
over if that makes sense.
Our start has eclipsed our end and it's stuck that way.
We're going to continually set this to be the start will we ate the middle will be 7 and it keeps going
over and over and over.
So you want to stop.
You want to make sure this loop only runs while our start is less than or equal to the end.
So as soon as the start becomes greater or the end becomes less then we have a problem.
So just in here I'm going to do.
And then we'll just check the start is less than or equal to.
And just like that OK.
So we're close now.
And if I if I run this this time we still have a problem which is that we're returning the middle even
if we don't find it.
Now we don't loop forever but it's returning index of 7 because that's where we stopped right.
That's our last point right here.
So index of 7 but that doesn't work because 50 clearly is not an index of 7.
So now we just need to add a little check at the end.
You want to check.
Basically if a ray of middle is equal to what we're looking for
like that if it is then we return middle.
Else we want to return we'll return negative one.
I think is what we said right.
Yes it is.
So that makes sense so we're checking if the middle the item at the middle index is what we're looking
for should do triple equals will return middle otherwise return negative 1.
So now we get negative 1.
But if we search for 5 it gives us one if we search for nine just three if we search for negative one
we get negative 1 negative 10 still negative one.
OK.
So a couple of small Clean-Up things we could do if we wanted to.
We can well first get rid of the cons. the logs you don't need that.
Next we can condense some of these conditional statements.
So I'm going to duplicate this solution because some people like to have a longer version but I will
also do a shorter version where we get rid of basically a lot of whitespace like this to do a single
line IF statement and then our else doesn't need brackets either.
So there's there's one reduction of a couple of lines and then we can also put all this on a single
line using the ternary operator.
So that looks like this.
Or one possibly there's two implementation so you can just do a return array.
Middle equals equals element.
If that's true.
So we need this question mark.
We're going to return middle colon.
Else which turn negative 1.
If you haven't seen that syntax the way you would read this is returned the result of this whole thing.
First of all and the result is going to depend on if array of middle is equal to the elements so if
array of middle is equal to Element return middle else return negative 1.
So just test it out again.
It looks like it's working.
Let's plug in a number that is in there like 30 and we get indexed 7 and 13 get index of 4.
If we find it in 103 we get negative 1.
OK.
So that's our shorter solution.
All that we did the logic is the same.
We just got rid of some of the extra brackets and the longer if statements.
So we made it through there.
Hopefully it makes sense how this all works.
And now we're moving on to a couple other searching algorithms.
So keep in mind this works great on a sorted array.
Otherwise it's useless.
So linear is the best that we can do.
Well we saw a couple of videos ago.
Is the best we can do on an unsorted array binary though.
Works great.
If our data is sorted.