All right.
Welcome back.
So I'd like to talk about the time complexity for binary search how it performs.
Let's just say on an array.
So as the length of the array grows assorted array.
Of course.
How does the time complexity grow in relation.
And you can see here on the left worst an average case 0 of log n and I'll come back to that and why
that is.
Best case of course is 0 1 because it's possible that the very first thing we pick is the very is the
element we're looking for.
If we pick the middle point of an array and that's what we want.
While that one operation is constant time 0 of 1 that's pretty rare.
But it's possible worst an average case are both 0 of log end and I have a couple of slides to detail
how we get log in if you're not familiar with logarithms and how this applies to big O.
I have a quick video.
I think it's the last video of the big O section.
I'd definitely recommend you watch it if you're not sure about logarithms.
If you were taught them a long time ago and you forgot them or if you were never taught them it's a
quick video.
So suppose we're searching for the number 13 in this array.
How many steps does it take.
Well we actually can see 13 not in here as a human.
It should be right here if it were to be in this array.
But the first step is to pick a midpoint.
And I know this looks like it's not the middle but these are all double digit numbers over here so it's
kind of skewed.
But this is the midpoint.
So we pick 19 and we we check is 13 less than or greater than 19.
It's less then.
So we know it's somewhere over here.
If it's going to be in here so then that's what this array is representing.
We're not actually shrinking the array down.
We're just looking at this portion of the larger array.
So then we pick a midpoint again which is 9.
Well 13 is that less than or greater than it's greater than 9.
So we're now looking at this some array 11 14 15.
So we pick the midpoint 14 is 13 plus cent. To then it is less then.
So we're looking at this supper now 11.
So we check is 13 equal to 11.
The answer is no of course.
And so we know that 13 is not in this array unless it's somehow an unsorted array in which case we shouldn't
be using binary search.
But given the conditions of binary search we can say without a doubt there are Tinas not in this array.
Nope not here.
So if we look at the number of steps here we had 16 elements.
It took four steps to say with certainty that an element is not in there.
So we could have found it earlier if it actually was in this array.
If we were looking for 9 for example it takes two steps for looking for 14 it would take three steps.
But if we're looking for something that's not in there or the very worst case it took four steps.
Now 16 elements 4 steps.
Let's grow our array.
Let's double it in size.
So instead of 16 I'M ADDING right I'm adding 16 more elements so we have 32 elements in our array.
It looks like this.
And let's say I'm looking for the number 32.
How many steps will it take.
Well in the first step we pick a midpoint.
This is not counting as a step.
This is just our starting array.
I pick the midpoint which is 16 and we testis 32 greater than or less than 16.
It's greater than.
So we can ignore all of this.
There we go.
The slide took a long time to make.
So now we're looking at this part of the array and we pick a midpoint which is 24 and we compare 32
Well third to it's greater.
So we can ignore all of this.
Next we're looking at this portion and we pick a midpoint again 32 is greater than 28.
So we ignore all of this Skip.
Now we're looking at 30 while we're looking at this portion and we pick the midpoint which is 30 and
32 is greater than 30 so we ignore this portion finally pick her midpoint again and we find 32 we're
good to go.
And that took five steps one step two three.
What is highlighting the wrong thing.
One two three four five until we found it.
So we doubled the number of elements from the previous slide we had 16 elements which was four steps
to find.
Or actually we didn't find the element but it took a maximum four steps here.
We doubled it to 32 elements and it took a maximum of five steps to find our element.
So that relationship is log based too.
And so log based to which we simplified to log and basically means to do what power gives us.
And so if we go all the way back here 16 elements what is log base 2 of 16 it is 4 because 2 to the
fourth power gives us 16.
Two times two times two times two.
Or here it was log base 2 of 32 elements and 32.
That means five two times two times two times two times two.
So every time we double the size of and every time we double it we are simply adding one extra step.
So log in is really good if we look at the big O complexity graph here you can see log in is all the
way down here.
It's really good.
It's so good in fact they don't even put a separate line in here.
So there's the O of end line our linear big-O and then down here they put constant and log in together
because in the grand scheme of things when you zoom out far enough so that you're looking at something
that also includes factorial 0 of log in is so so much better that it just looks like one anyway.
So log in is really good binary search is very fast.
Of course the caveat is that it only works on a sorted array and if you don't have sorted data then
you're out of luck and you've got to use linear search which is not anywhere near as good going forward.
We actually will see a couple of other algorithms when we talk about things like binary trees and graphs
where the big owner station for time complexity includes log and again or Also N log in.
So if you're not comfortable with logs yet again I really recommend you watch that video but also give
it some time.
I think we have a couple of sections before we encounter log and again but soon we will.