All right.
So we introduced the fact that we're talking about searching for now we're going to focus on searching
an array.
So imagine we have this array with states in it which I didn't type this myself just to be clear I copied
this.
And so it also includes I think 59 items.
It includes territories like American Samoa Puerto Rico's in here Guam things like that.
But that's beside the point.
So imagine that a user typed something in and they're trying to I don't know create an address and then
need to enter a state or territory and for our application we want to make sure it's in this array.
What's the best way of doing that.
And the simplest way is just to look at every single element in order and check if it's what we want.
Right so if the user enters let's say Indiana we would just start at the beginning and check.
OK.
Is this Indiana.
Nope.
Is this Indiana Indiana.
Is this Indiana.
And we keep going until we get to Indiana.
And in that case we return something you know true or we say the index that we found a debt or if it's
not in there we keep going until the end and then we have some some logic at the end that says if it's
not found return false or return negative 1 or something like that.
Now that approach is actually not a bad approach.
Now in this situation where we have sorted data alphabetically sorted there are better ways.
But let's go back to the think ahead had a list called usernames.
This is unsorted.
So there is no order to this at all.
Now somebody enters I hate cats.
It's a user name.
How do we check if it's taken or not.
In that case the best way of doing it is to check every single element one at a time.
Are you.
I hate cats.
No.
Next are you I hate cats.
Nope.
Keep going until we find it or we get to the end.
That is called linear search.
And in fact javascript is doing that things like Index of which you talked about includes.
Find find index all of these methods are doing the same thing behind the scenes.
They're checking every element one at a time to check if whatever we pass in.
So let's do two index of what to do usernames index of Tommy index of zero.
Let's do index of Q is towards the end 15.
We do index or something that's not in there.
Negative 1.
We could also do the same thing with includes.
I'm not going to go through all these methods but let's try.
Does it include Tom.
That's true.
Those include Tom's.
That's false.
So what's happening here is that it is going through and checking each item to see are you Tom's Are
you Tom's over and over until it hits the end.
And if you looked at the source code you would actually see the algorithm that we're going to talk about
and it's very straightforward.
It's called a linear search.
So we've already been describing it.
We visit one item one item at a time starting at the beginning moving forward.
Or we could start at the end and move backward but it doesn't matter.
All that matters is that we're moving at a set interval one item at a time checking every single thing.
So if we were to have this list of numbers array and we want to check for 12 in a search if it's in
there we just start the beginning is 12.
Nope.
Is 8 12 No.
1 is not 12 100 is not 12 12 is 12.
And then we return true or we return the index 0 1 2 3 4.
It depends on what we're doing.
So for index for example it would return for 4 It includes returns true.
So that's linear search.
And what I'm going to do now is something that is a bit different than how we've structured the course
so far.
I'm going to give you pseudo code to try and implemented and I encourage you to write this code on your
own.
This is a nice and simple one.
Here's a pseudo code and then afterwards we'll go through it and I'll write up the solution.
So write a function call it whatever you want but it accepts an array and a value.
So call it linear search and it takes an array full of let's just say its numbers but it doesn't matter
really it saves numbers and then a value another number you just loop through the entire array and check
if the current array element is equal to the value that we pass in.
And if it is return the index at which it's found and if it's never found return negative 1.
OK.
So loop through the entire array check for a value.
Whatever it is let's say we're looking for three.
If you find three return that index if you don't return negative 1.
So this is possible in just a couple lines.
Don't overthink it.
Give it a shot in the next video.
I'll show you a potential solution.
And keep in mind that even though this is simple that doesn't make it bad.
Like we discussed it's used by built in functions things like Index of for example.
OK.
So in the next video.