All right.
Welcome back.
So we're moving on to our second searching algorithm and this one can be a significant improvement on
linear search that we saw in the last video.
It's called binary search so it can be much much faster.
We'll get into the specifics with Big O later on but it can be faster rather than eliminating one element
at a time like we did in linear search where we checked one element.
Is this it.
Nope.
It's the next one it.
Nope it's an X on it.
Over and over and over in binary search we can eliminate half of the remaining elements at any given
point.
However there's a really big caveat here.
Binary Search only works on sorted arrays so the data has to be sorted from if it's numbers lowest to
highest or highest to lowest or strings alphabetical.
There has to be an order to it.
So imagine we have our same states array.
You don't have to imagine it's right here.
And this is sorted alphabetically so you can see Alabama down to Wyoming and let's say that a user were
doing the same example where we ask the user to enter a state and for their address or something.
And we're going to verify that it exists in this array.
Now first of all this is a very short array in the grand scheme of things.
So linear search isn't really going to be big.
It's going to take much time and that the millisecond probably less than a millisecond the tiniest fraction
of a second that we're saving.
With binary search isn't really worth it but since it's already sorted it's a good example.
Let's say that someone enters Oregon as their state so an end quote.
And we want to check the facts in here.
Well since it sorted alphabetically the way that binary search works is that we pick a halfway point
in this array.
So somewhere and I'm not going to count exactly I think there's 59.
I'm not going to count the exact halfway point but let's just guess roughly let's say that we pick states
of twenty nine twenty nine point five.
Right.
So we'll round down.
So we pick our first spot we pick the middle because we know it's sorted.
In this case alphabetically so the middle should be the middle sorted element and then all we do is
we check.
So we find Missouri where you are and we check is Oregon greater than Missouri or less than in our case
alphabetically.
Is it after m Missouri is it after that in the alphabet.
Or is it before and it's after.
So now we only care about this part of theory.
We've just eliminated all of this.
We don't care about the beginning and recheck halfway through the next little bit.
And I'm just going to eyeball it rather than doing the math let's say halfway through is around 44.
So let's say check States 44 that gives us Pennsylvania.
So now this is the middle of this array here.
And we go to Pennsylvania and we check in Oregon before or after Pennsylvania.
And it's before.
So now we care about this list.
From Missouri to Pennsylvania we know that it's somewhere in here.
We eliminated all of this here.
So now we're going from Missouri to Pennsylvania and we pick the halfway point again.
And I think this is 16 or so.
So let's go to the eighth one.
Three four five six seven eight so we go to New York and we check Oregon greater or less than New York
and it's greater.
So it's between New York and Pennsylvania.
So we pick somewhere in the middle between New York and Pennsylvania.
Let's say that it's Ohio and we know that it's greater than Ohio so much somewhere between Ohio and
Pennsylvania.
We pick the middle and now it's Oregon.
And I know that seems like a lot of work.
But remember that that was only what five or six guesses compared to if we started at the beginning
with a linear search we checked this is this Oregon.
Nope.
Is this Oregon.
Over and over and over.
So it saves a lot of time if your data is sorted.
So let's get down to the details of the implementation.
So the idea is dividing and conquering.
So we split up the array into two pieces.
We pick a pivot point in the middle usually And we check the left side and the right side and see where
it based off of what we're looking for where it will be in which half.
So let's search for 15 in this list.
Remember it has to be sorted.
This doesn't work at all.
If it's not sorted.
So if it's sorted here we're going to start by picking.
We're going to call them left and right.
So we're going to change the window of where we're searching because remember we can throw out half
of the array roughly every time.
So we're going to start with the left at one end right at the end 19 and then we're going to pick somewhere
in the middle.
And I think this is an odd number.
So you can round down or round up just be consistent.
As far as where you pick.
So I think we're going to pick 11 here.
I know we're picking 11 and we we check is 15 greater than 11 or less than 11 and it's greater than.
So now we eliminate all of that to the left and we make the new left 12.
And the new right is the same.
It's 19.
Now we checked somewhere in the middle.
So we're going to check 17 as our middle point and we check is 15 greater than or less than 17.
It's is on the right side or the left side and it's a leftside so we can eliminate 17 18 19.
And now we have left at 12 right at 16 and then the middle is 15 which is the only choice and recheck
is 15 equal to 15 is greater than or less than it's equal.
So we found that only took three checks.
Three guesses.
We checked at the middle first 11 and we knew it was greater.
So we did a second check.
We picked 17 that was too big.
And then we picked 15 and that was correct compared to starting at the beginning.
One two three four five six seven eight nine guesses using linear search.
So if we have a sorted array numbers or strings or whatever it is as long as we can compare easily to
check if something is greater than or less than in some respect if we can do that then we can implement
binary search which is much faster.